const psm1Test1Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Who supports the Scrum Master in removing impediments?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The customer"},{key:"B",text:"Management"},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"D",text:"The Developers"}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D"],explanation:"The Developers can help the Scrum Master because of their understanding of how the work is done and their internal interactions with each other. Some impediments are rooted in external causes and that's why the Scrum Master might need to have the senior management's support in removing them. The Product Owner can also support the Scrum Master by managing stakeholder expectations."},
  {id:2,question:"Which TWO of the following statements are true?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Early feedback gives the Developers more time to develop new system features because they spend less time reworking features expected in a given iteration."},{key:"B",text:"Early feedback enables agile teams to deliver features with the highest business value first, because the customer maintains focus on features with the highest system value."},{key:"C",text:"Early feedback reduces costs because it decreases the amount of time needed for system testing."},{key:"D",text:"Early feedback makes it more likely that the system built is what the customer wanted because they are given the opportunity to make changes throughout the iteration."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Agile teams are highly flexible and adaptive. They collaborate and interoperate with team members and stakeholders in order to maximize opportunities of success."},
  {id:3,question:"A Scrum Team has Developers working from globally distributed locations. Conducting the Scrum events via a conference call is proving difficult and an impediment to the self-management of the team. As Scrum Master, you have raised this in the Sprint Retrospective. Which are the two most appropriate things to do?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Have the Developers discuss, choose, and introduce suitable communication tools."},{key:"B",text:"Introduce the tools in use elsewhere in the organization that have helped other teams."},{key:"C",text:"Raise the impediment to management and discuss the challenges of the distributed nature of the team."},{key:"D",text:"Wait for the Developers to choose and implement a solution."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is a servant-leader for the Scrum Team. The Scrum Master coaches the Developers in organizational environments in which Scrum is not yet fully adopted and understood, coaches the Developers in self-management, and removes impediments to the Developers' progress."},
  {id:4,question:"Which two statements are correct during the Sprint?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Sprint Goal emerges as the Developers work through the plan and learns more about the work."},{key:"B",text:"The scope may be clarified as more is learned."},{key:"C",text:"The scope may be re-negotiated as more is learned."},{key:"D",text:"The Developers focus on finishing all Sprint Backlog items as their commitment from Sprint Planning."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"The Developers modify the Sprint Backlog throughout the Sprint, and the Sprint Backlog emerges during the Sprint. The work and scope of work to be 'done' may be clarified or re-negotiated together with the Product Owner if necessary."},
  {id:5,question:"What should be delivered at the end of the first Sprint?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A potentially shippable product Increment."},{key:"B",text:"A formulated plan for the subsequence Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"At least one piece of working software."},{key:"D",text:"A completely refined Product Backlog with estimations and task breakdown."},{key:"E",text:"A proof of concept."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"The Sprint's primary objective is to create a 'Done', useable, and potentially releasable product Increment that fulfills the Sprint Goal."},
  {id:6,question:"Time-boxing is an important principle of Scrum. Identify the INCORRECT statements.",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A Sprint is time-boxed to 4 weeks or less; Sprint Planning is time-boxed to 8 hours for a one month Sprint; Daily Scrum is time-boxed to 15 minutes."},{key:"B",text:"Daily Scrum is time-boxed to 15 minutes; Sprint Review is time-boxed to 4 hours for a one month Sprint; Sprint Retrospective is time-boxed to 3 hours for a one month Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Review is time-boxed to 6 hours for a one month Sprint; Sprint Retrospective is time-boxed to 8 hours for a one month Sprint; Sprint Planning is time-boxed to 8 hours for a one week Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Sprint Retrospective is time-boxed to 4 hours for a one month Sprint; Daily Scrum is time-boxed to 15 minutes; a Sprint is time-boxed to 1 to 6 weeks."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"The maximum time-box for each Scrum event is: The Sprint (4 weeks or less), Sprint Planning (8 hours for a one-month Sprint), Daily Scrum (15 minutes), Sprint Review (4 hours for a one-month Sprint), and Sprint Retrospective (3 hours for a one-month Sprint)."},
  {id:7,question:"A time-box is:",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"An event that starts at a specific time."},{key:"B",text:"An event with a minimum set time."},{key:"C",text:"An event that cannot take more than a maximum amount of time."},{key:"D",text:"An event that must happen by a specific time."},{key:"E",text:"A previously agreed period of time during which a team works towards completion of some goal and stopping when the time limit is reached."}],correctAnswers:["C","E"],explanation:"All events are time-boxed events, such that every event has a maximum duration. Once a Sprint begins, its duration is fixed and cannot be shortened or lengthened."},
  {id:8,question:"What are the common outcomes of Daily Scrums?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Everyone is clear on the next steps towards the Sprint Goal."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner is informed of the progress."},{key:"C",text:"The impediments are discussed and possible solutions selected."},{key:"D",text:"Impediments have been identified for the Scrum Master to address."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"The output of the Daily Scrum is the Developers' plan for the next 24 hours and identifying any impediments."},
  {id:9,question:"Which of the following characteristics is exhibited in effective agile team members?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Competence"},{key:"B",text:"Decision-making ability"},{key:"C",text:"Mutual trust and respect"},{key:"D",text:"Openness"}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C","D"],explanation:"How successful an agile team can be depends on the people becoming more proficient in living the values that build trust and having the right skills and competencies in order to optimize flexibility, creativity, and productivity."},
  {id:10,question:"When is the Sprint Backlog created?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Any time before Sprint Planning."},{key:"B",text:"During Product Backlog refinement."},{key:"C",text:"At least one or two Sprints ahead."},{key:"D",text:"During Sprint Planning."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The advantages of just in time delivery is minimizing waste and the ability to adapt more quickly than detailed upfront planning."},
  {id:11,question:"What is self-managing?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It refers to internally deciding who does what, when, and how in order to achieve the desired results."},{key:"B",text:"It refers to delivering maximum business value in a minimum time span."},{key:"C",text:"It refers to prioritizing the creation of high value deliverables over lower value deliverables."},{key:"D",text:"It refers to allowing all facets of Scrum process to be observed by everyone."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Self-managing teams choose how best to accomplish their work, rather than being directed by others outside the team."},
  {id:12,question:"Which of the following is NOT an example of the Scrum principle 'Empirical Process Control'?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Use of a Scrumboard to ensure clear visibility into the Scrum Team's progress."},{key:"B",text:"Use of Release Planning Schedule to ensure coordination across multiple Scrum Teams."},{key:"C",text:"Use of Prioritized Product Backlog to be viewed by internal and external stakeholders."},{key:"D",text:"Use of fixed amount of time for each process and activity in a Scrum project."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Three pillars uphold every implementation of empirical process control: transparency, inspection, and adaptation. Time-boxes, although a part of Scrum, is not an artifact that can be inspected but rather a practice to reduce complexity."},
  {id:13,question:"The Sprint Review is:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"an opportunity for the Developers to find ways to incrementally improve their velocity."},{key:"B",text:"an activity for the Developers to demonstrate their work to the Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"when the Scrum Team and key stakeholders inspect the Increment produced in the Sprint and adapt the Product Backlog accordingly."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Sprint Review is focused on inspecting and adapting the product."},
  {id:14,question:"Which group is required to be at the Sprint Review?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner, the Scrum Master and the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner and stakeholders."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner and Product Lead."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Team and stakeholders."},{key:"E",text:"The Product Owner, technical leads and stakeholders."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Sprint Review is an inspect and adapt opportunity for both the Scrum Team and key stakeholders."},
  {id:15,question:"What is the primary focus during the Sprint Review?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Team's process and any suggested improvements to the process."},{key:"B",text:"The Sprint results."},{key:"C",text:"The productivity and utilization of the Developers."},{key:"D",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Review is focused on inspecting and adapting the product."},
  {id:16,question:"What is the correct time-box for the Sprint Review event?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Minimum 2 hours."},{key:"B",text:"As long as required to update the Product Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"2 hours for a monthly Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"4 hours for a monthly Sprint."},{key:"E",text:"As long as required to inspect the Increment."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter."},
  {id:17,question:"During the Sprint Retrospective, what topics could a Scrum Team discuss?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Needed skills or knowledge."},{key:"B",text:"The process that the Scrum Team does the Scrum events."},{key:"C",text:"The way the team members interact."},{key:"D",text:"The Definition of Done."},{key:"E",text:"All of the above"}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"The Sprint Retrospective is focused on inspecting and adapting the Scrum Team and their process."},
  {id:18,question:"Is the Product Owner optional at the Sprint Retrospective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner is optional. He/she will attend when needed or requested by the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner is not allowed to attend. The Sprint Retrospective is only for the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner is mandatory. The Sprint Retrospective is an opportunity for the entire Scrum Team to inspect and adapt the way they work."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"In order for the Scrum Team to improve, all members must attend."},
  {id:19,question:"What is the Product Owner's responsibility during a Sprint Retrospective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Participating as a member of the Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner is optional as the event is focused for the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"Giving the Developers technical feedback."},{key:"D",text:"Discussing upcoming Product Backlog items."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"In order for the Scrum Team to improve, all members must attend."},
  {id:20,question:"What is the Scrum Master's responsibility during a Sprint Retrospective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Recording the meeting minutes."},{key:"B",text:"Participating as a member of the Scrum Team and facilitating as requested or needed."},{key:"C",text:"Selecting the most important action items."},{key:"D",text:"Ensuring conflict is avoided."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Master participates as a member of the Scrum Team and facilitates as requested or needed."},
  {id:21,question:"When should the Sprint Retrospective happen?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"At the end of every Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"When the project is over."},{key:"C",text:"Immediately after Sprint Planning."},{key:"D",text:"When needed or requested."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Sprint Retrospective occurs at the end of every Sprint."},
  {id:22,question:"Which of the following is an advantage of having the whole team responsible for quality?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Companies no longer need to recruit and train software testing specialists."},{key:"B",text:"Test automation tasks are now the responsibility of the Developers instead of the test team."},{key:"C",text:"Role barriers are eliminated and team members contribute to project success based on their unique skills and perspectives."},{key:"D",text:"Project costs are lower because the need for a specialized test team is eliminated."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The focus of agile teams is shifted towards the outcome rather than the process that produces the output. The outcomes for the project is the result of collaborative efforts of the team as a whole."},
  {id:23,question:"Which topic should NOT be discussed during the Sprint Retrospective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The people and interactions of the team."},{key:"B",text:"The health of the relationships between members."},{key:"C",text:"The Definition of Done."},{key:"D",text:"Product Backlog items for the next Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Product Backlog items for the next Sprint should be discussed during Sprint Planning, not Sprint Retrospective."},
  {id:24,question:"Which of the following would be the most opportune time to update the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"During the Sprint Retrospective."},{key:"B",text:"During the Sprint Planning."},{key:"C",text:"At the start of every Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"During Daily Scrum."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Sprint Retrospective is the most opportune time to update the Definition of Done."},
  {id:25,question:"True or False: An action item from the Sprint Retrospective can be added to the Sprint Backlog for the next Sprint.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"True."},{key:"B",text:"False."},{key:"C",text:"False. It will be added to the Product Backlog and will be worked on if the team has enough capacity."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The most impactful improvements are addressed as soon as possible and may be added to the Sprint Backlog for the next Sprint."},
  {id:26,question:"What is value-based prioritization?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It refers to emphasizing achieving results by focusing on the needs of the Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"It refers to making improvements through adaptation."},{key:"C",text:"It refers to prioritizing creation of high value deliverables over lower value deliverables."},{key:"D",text:"It refers to allowing all facets of Scrum process to be observed by everyone."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Our highest priority is to satisfy the customer through early and continuous delivery of valuable software. In Scrum, this is done through ordering the items in the Product Backlog to best achieve goals and missions."},
  {id:27,question:"Which of the following is emphasized in Scrum framework?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Self-motivation and team responsibility."},{key:"B",text:"Delegation of authority through proper planning."},{key:"C",text:"Individual responsibilities and accountability."},{key:"D",text:"Extensive upfront planning and adherence to the approved plans."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Team consists of a Product Owner, the Developers, and a Scrum Master. The responsibility for the success of the product belongs to the team as a whole."},
  {id:28,question:"What would be the best action to do if the Scrum Team has identified several important process improvement items during the Sprint Retrospective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Add them to the Product Backlog and work on them when there is capacity."},{key:"B",text:"The most impactful improvements are addressed as soon as possible and may be added to the Sprint Backlog for the next Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Order them on a separate list and work on them from top to bottom."},{key:"D",text:"Let the Scrum Master select which items to add to the Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The most impactful improvements are addressed as soon as possible and may be added to the Sprint Backlog for the next Sprint."},
  {id:29,question:"Who is accountable for the final order of the items in the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Stakeholders"},{key:"B",text:"The Developers"},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master"},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"E",text:"The Scrum Team"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Owner is accountable for the final order of the items in the Product Backlog."},
  {id:30,question:"The flow of value is reflected in the ordering of the Product Backlog. The higher ordered Product Backlog items is work that the Product Owner wants to have done in an upcoming Sprint. These items are usually clearer and has more detail than lower ordered ones and should be Ready enough to be presented during the Sprint Planning. What is the best description of Ready Product Backlog items?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"They are in a User Story format."},{key:"B",text:"They are testable use cases."},{key:"C",text:"They are clear enough and have enough information for the Product Owner and Developers to understand the work that needs to be done and to create a forecast of Product Backlog items to implement the Sprint Goal."},{key:"D",text:"They are functional tasks (i.e. design, frontend, backend, architecture) that are clear enough to know who will be doing what during the Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Ready Product Backlog items are clear enough and have enough information for the Product Owner and Developers to understand the work and create a forecast."},
  {id:31,question:"A client has just hired you to lead a new project where three teams new to Scrum will be working on their new product. What would you propose?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Combine the teams into a single Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"There should be separate Product Owners and Product Backlogs for each Scrum Team."},{key:"C",text:"The product only has one Product Backlog and there should only be a single Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"For a single product there is one Product Backlog. For a single Product Backlog there is one Product Owner."},
  {id:32,question:"Which best describes the management style used in the Scrum framework?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Authoritarian"},{key:"B",text:"Decentralized"},{key:"C",text:"Persuasive"},{key:"D",text:"Assertive"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"In Scrum, decisions are made locally and in a collaborative method. Self-managing teams choose how best to accomplish their work, rather than being directed by others outside the team."},
  {id:33,question:"Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory and one of the pillars that upholds its implementation is transparency. In what ways can you maximize transparency of the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The primary source of information, for the product, comes from the Product Backlog and the items in the Product Backlog are small enough to be done inside of a Sprint but big enough to show progress."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Backlog updates or changes require stakeholder approval."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Backlog is maintained using an online tool."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Backlog is a complete set of requirements for the product."},{key:"E",text:"Product Backlog items should be pre-assigned to the individual members and no larger than 8 Story Points or larger than one day."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The primary source of information, for the product, comes from the Product Backlog and the items in the Product Backlog are small enough to be done inside of a Sprint but big enough to show progress."},
  {id:34,question:"Non-functional requirements (i.e. performance, security, technical debt) are typically not visible to end users or stakeholders. How would you ensure these items are transparent?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Add them to the Hardening Sprints."},{key:"B",text:"Add them to the Product Backlog or the Definition of Done."},{key:"C",text:"Add them to a specific swimlane at the top of the Scrum Board."},{key:"D",text:"Assign them to an external team to take care of."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Non-functional requirements should be added to the Product Backlog or the Definition of Done to ensure transparency."},
  {id:35,question:"Product Backlog refinement is an ongoing process in which the Product Owner and the Developers collaborate on the details of the items in the Product Backlog. When should this activity occur?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"In between sequential Sprints (i.e. between Sprint n and Sprint n+1)"},{key:"B",text:"1 or 2 Sprints ahead or in the actual Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"In Sprint 0."},{key:"D",text:"During Sprint Retrospective."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Refining the Product Backlog and Product Backlog items will optimize the flow of value and help make the upcoming work 'ready' for the team to work on thus they will do this 1-2 preceding Sprints ahead."},
  {id:36,question:"True or False: Multiple teams working on the same product should have separate Product Owners.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"For a single product there is one Product Backlog. For a single Product Backlog there is one Product Owner."},
  {id:37,question:"Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory and one of the pillars that upholds its implementation is transparency. In what ways can you maximize transparency of the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Backlog is divided by future Sprints."},{key:"B",text:"Product Backlog items are estimated in Story Points."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Backlog is managed using Jira."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Backlog is ordered and available to all stakeholders."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Backlog is ordered and available to all stakeholders to maximize transparency."},
  {id:38,question:"Which statement is true about the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It supplements the requirements document."},{key:"B",text:"It is a complete project plan that the Scrum Team commits to completing."},{key:"C",text:"It is a living artifact that evolves as the product and the environment in which it will be used evolves."},{key:"D",text:"It should not have more than 6 months of work."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Changes in business requirements, market conditions, or technology may cause changes in the Product Backlog."},
  {id:39,question:"True or False: Multiple teams working on the same product should maintain separate Product Backlogs.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"For a single product there is one Product Backlog. For a single Product Backlog there is one Product Owner."},
  {id:40,question:"How is architecture and infrastructure handled?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"They are discussed and planned during Sprint spikes."},{key:"B",text:"They are done in Sprint 0."},{key:"C",text:"They are added to the Product Backlog or implemented along with functional development."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Architecture and infrastructure are added to the Product Backlog or implemented along with functional development."},
  {id:41,question:"Who is responsible for estimating the Product Backlog items?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers by themselves."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"The Technical Architect."},{key:"E",text:"The Developers after clarifying the requirements with the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"The ones doing the work are the best ones to create the estimations."},
  {id:42,question:"Which statement regarding the Product Backlog is FALSE?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It is an inventory of work to be done for the Product."},{key:"B",text:"Ordered based on value, priority, risk, and dependencies."},{key:"C",text:"It is a finalized list of requirements to be done for the Product."},{key:"D",text:"It is managed by the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Product Backlog is a living artifact that evolves and changes as more is learned."},
  {id:43,question:"How is the Product Backlog ordered?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Whatever the Product Owner decides is best."},{key:"B",text:"Highest priority items at the bottom and lowest priority items at the top."},{key:"C",text:"Items with the smallest Story Points are at the top and the biggest at the bottom."},{key:"D",text:"Items are ordered by function (i.e. design, frontend, backend, database)"},{key:"E",text:"Least risky are at the top and riskiest are at the bottom."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"For the Product Owner to succeed, the entire organization must respect his or her decisions."},
  {id:44,question:"True or False: Each Scrum Team must have a different Product Owner.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"For a single product there is one Product Backlog. For a single Product Backlog there is one Product Owner regardless of the number of Scrum Teams working from the same Product Backlog."},
  {id:45,question:"What impact does an evolving environment have on the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A new Product Backlog is created to meet the needs of the users."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Backlog is static as it is a commitment to the stakeholders."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Backlog is a living artifact that evolves as the product and the environment in which it will be used evolves."},{key:"D",text:"Identify a different market for the current Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Product Backlog is a living artifact that evolves and changes as more is learned."},
  {id:46,question:"When is ownership of individual items, in the Sprint Backlog, assigned to individual Developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Any time during Sprint Planning."},{key:"B",text:"Never. Even if individuals work on specific Sprint Backlog items, the Developers as a whole remain accountable for the Sprint Backlog in its entirety."},{key:"C",text:"During Daily Scrum."},{key:"D",text:"When the Scrum Master assigns it."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers are responsible for doing the work in the Sprint Backlog in order to satisfy the Sprint Goal."},
  {id:47,question:"The Sprint Backlog is owned by the:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Team."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is the set of Product Backlog items selected by the Developers and their plan for delivering the work."},
  {id:48,question:"The Sprint Backlog is the set of Product Backlog items selected for the Sprint, plus a plan for delivering the product Increment and realizing the Sprint Goal. When can the Developers add, remove or change the work needed to complete the Increment and meet the Sprint Goal?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"As soon as the Scrum Master identifies new work."},{key:"B",text:"As soon as the Product Owner identifies new work."},{key:"C",text:"Only at the Daily Scrum."},{key:"D",text:"As soon as they are identified."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a living artifact that evolves as more is learned."},
  {id:49,question:"What is time-boxing?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It refers to emphasizing achieving results by focusing on the needs of the Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"It refers to delivering maximum business value in a minimum time span."},{key:"C",text:"It refers to prioritizing creation of high value deliverables over lower value deliverables."},{key:"D",text:"It refers to fixing a certain amount of time for each process and activity in a Scrum project."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Time-boxing is allotting a fixed, maximum unit of time for an activity. It helps teams focus on the most important tasks at hand in order to achieve the objectives of the specified activity."},
  {id:50,question:"Which of the following does NOT reflect the values of Scrum or the Scrum theory?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers can ask the Product Owner for help if they need clarification or to optimize the work they are doing in the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers can collaborate with the Product Owner to adjust the amount of work in the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint Backlog emerges during the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint Backlog is a finalized plan that the Developers commit to completing by the end of the Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a living artifact that evolves as more is learned. Static plans do not allow room to adjust or change directions if needed."},
  {id:51,question:"What is the Sprint Backlog composed of?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Bug fixes"},{key:"B",text:"Use Cases"},{key:"C",text:"Tasks"},{key:"D",text:"User Stories"},{key:"E",text:"Any of the above"}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a forecast about what will be delivered in the Increment and meeting the Sprint Goal."},
  {id:52,question:"Which is the best description of the Sprint Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It is a finalized list of items that the Developers commit to completing by the end of the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Each task is assigned an owner."},{key:"C",text:"It is the Developers' plan for the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"User Stories are no bigger than 8 Story Points."},{key:"E",text:"It is ordered by the Scrum Master."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a plan by and for the Developers."},
  {id:53,question:"True or False: Done Increments must be shipped to end users at the end of each Sprint.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner decides when it is best to release Increments."},
  {id:54,question:"Why does Scrum require having a new Increment of working software done at the end of every Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"To ensure all selected items from Sprint Planning has been done."},{key:"B",text:"For the purpose of transparency."},{key:"C",text:"Because it is the Product Owner's commitment to management."},{key:"D",text:"In order to maximize utilization of the Developers."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Working software is the primary measure of progress. Failure to produce an Increment at the end of the Sprint will reduce transparency and is a lost opportunity to inspect and adapt the product."},
  {id:55,question:"True or False: Scrum requires having a new Increment of working software released to end users at the end of every Sprint.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner decides when it is best to release Increments."},
  {id:56,question:"Multiple Scrum Teams working on the same product should integrate their Increments every Sprint.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"False, multiple Scrum Teams will synchronize integrations at the Hardening Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"False, each Scrum Team is independent."},{key:"C",text:"True, but only if the work done has dependencies on other Scrum Teams."},{key:"D",text:"True, otherwise the Product Owner and Stakeholders may not be able to accurately inspect the work that was done in the Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"A way to reduce the risk of being blocked or blocking another team is to integrate as often as possible in order to address any issues early on."},
  {id:57,question:"Which of the following is a benefit of the agile process promoting early and frequent feedback?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The total number of defects found during the project is much higher than on traditional software development projects such as waterfall."},{key:"B",text:"There is less rework because customers see the product regularly."},{key:"C",text:"It is easy to determine the developer who introduces the most defects when integrating code."},{key:"D",text:"There is enough time to complete all features scheduled for the given iteration."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Having short feedback loops helps teams rapidly respond and adapt to changes."},
  {id:58,question:"When should the Product Owner release each Increment to the end users?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"At the end of each Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"When it makes the most sense."},{key:"C",text:"After Stakeholder approval."},{key:"D",text:"When all work, to make the Increment shippable, is done."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value of the product and the work done by the Developers thus will release the Increment based on when he/she thinks is best."},
  {id:59,question:"What must be delivered, by the Scrum Team, at the end of any Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A potentially shippable product Increment that is 'done.'"},{key:"B",text:"The architecture and infrastructure to start feature development in the next Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"A fully formulated project plan for the work to be done to the product."},{key:"D",text:"Enough Test Cases to follow for at least the next 2-3 Sprints."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Failure to produce an Increment results in reduced transparency and is a lost opportunity to inspect and adapt the product."},
  {id:60,question:"What is the best description of a product Increment?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A release plan for delivering features based on projections from the business."},{key:"B",text:"An MVP used to validate market fit."},{key:"C",text:"A Product Plan that defines projected work for all future Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"Completed functional requirements waiting for UAT."},{key:"E",text:"The sum of all the Product Backlog items completed during a Sprint that complement those delivered in previous iterations."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"The Increment is the sum of all the Product Backlog items completed during a Sprint that complement those delivered in previous iterations."},
  {id:61,question:"Which of the following is NOT a time-boxed Scrum event?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Daily Scrum"},{key:"B",text:"Grooming"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"D",text:"Sprint Review"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"There are 4 events defined in Scrum (Sprint Planning, Daily Scrum, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective). The Product Backlog Refinement meeting (formally known as Grooming) is an optional event."},
  {id:62,question:"Which of the following statements on Time-boxing is INCORRECT?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It proposes fixing a certain timeframe for each activity."},{key:"B",text:"It ensures that Scrum Team members do not take up too much or too little work for a particular period of time."},{key:"C",text:"It is a principle through which Scrum framework addresses the project constraint of 'time'."},{key:"D",text:"It ensures that there is detailed upfront planning before every Sprint begins."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Time-boxing helps everyone focus on the same problem at the same time. During the Sprint, the Sprint Backlog will emerge as more is discovered and learned."},
  {id:63,question:"What is the Product Owner's role regarding the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner is responsible for creating the Definition of Done and may receive feedback from the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Team is responsible for creating the Definition of Done and may receive feedback from the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Team is responsible for creating the Definition of Done and may receive feedback from the Product Owner."},
  {id:64,question:"Under what circumstances would a Sprint be cancelled?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When the forecasted workload becomes unachievable."},{key:"B",text:"When the Product Owner is absent too often."},{key:"C",text:"When the Developers are unclear on what to do on the remaining work."},{key:"D",text:"When the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"A Sprint would be cancelled if the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete. This might occur if the company changes direction or if market or technology conditions change."},
  {id:65,question:"At the end of a Sprint, one of the items that is in progress does not meet the Definition of Done. What should happen the item?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Modify the Definition of Done so that the item can be added to the Increment."},{key:"B",text:"Add the completed work of the item to the Increment and create a separate Product Backlog item to make it 'done' in the next Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Do not include the item in the Increment, put it back in the Product Backlog, and let the Product Owner decide what to do with it."},{key:"D",text:"Extend the Sprint until item is 'done' and can be added to the Increment."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Product Backlog items are either 'done' or 'not done.' This helps with transparency, reduces complexity and allows for improved empiricism."},
  {id:66,question:"Why should the Product Owner care that the Developers comply to the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"To ensure that the Developers are completing their assigned tasks."},{key:"B",text:"So, they know who to contact if they need to clarify requirements."},{key:"C",text:"To have complete transparency and a common understanding of the 'done' work at the end of each Sprint. It can also help the team manage the maintenance costs and ownership costs."},{key:"D",text:"To know what skills are needed to make an item 'done' and who should be added to the team."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The quality of the product can impact the cost of ownership and sustainability of the product."},
  {id:67,question:"When is the development of a Product Backlog item considered finished?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When the Sprint time-box ends."},{key:"B",text:"When all tests have been passed."},{key:"C",text:"When there is no more work remaining to make the item potentially shippable."},{key:"D",text:"When all of the tasks are completed."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"When there is no more work remaining to make the item potentially shippable."},
  {id:68,question:"Which of the following is not a time-boxed Scrum event?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Daily Scrum"},{key:"B",text:"Daily Standup"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"D",text:"Sprint Review"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Daily Scrum is exclusively created for the Scrum Framework and has a clearly defined owner, time-box, and purpose. The Daily Standup can vary depending on the context that it is being used."},
  {id:69,question:"Which is NOT a true statement about the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It increases transparency."},{key:"B",text:"It provides a shared understanding of what it means when work is complete."},{key:"C",text:"It guides the Developers on what must be satisfied before the Scrum Master can close the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"It provides guidance on how many Product Backlog items the Developers can select for a Sprint."},{key:"E",text:"It guides the Developers in forecasting how many Product Backlog items they can do for a Sprint."},{key:"F",text:"It defines what it takes for an Increment to be ready for release."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master does not close the Sprint. The Definition of Done guides the Developers on what must be satisfied for an item to be considered complete."},
  {id:70,question:"Of the following activities, which is the best way to promote transparency of an Increment?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sending a daily status report to the stakeholders."},{key:"B",text:"Estimate the work needed to complete the items in hours rather than days."},{key:"C",text:"Log any technical debt incurred during development on a separate but transparent list."},{key:"D",text:"Doing the work that is necessary to meet the current Definition of Done."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Doing the work that is necessary to meet the current Definition of Done promotes transparency of an Increment."},
  {id:71,question:"As Scrum Teams mature, what is expected to happen?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Retrospectives will be less painful."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master becomes optional."},{key:"C",text:"Their Definition of Done will expand to include more stringent criteria for higher quality."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint time-boxes will be shortened because the productivity is higher."},{key:"E",text:"Team membership will change in order to promote knowledge sharing."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Their Definition of Done will expand to include more stringent criteria for higher quality."},
  {id:72,question:"Which of the following pairs, related to Tuckman's Model of Group Dynamics, is INCORRECTLY matched?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Storming: Team tries to accomplish work"},{key:"B",text:"Forming: Team is mature with experience"},{key:"C",text:"Norming: Team begins to sort out internal differences"},{key:"D",text:"Performing: Team's efficiency is at its optimal level"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Forming is the first stage of group development where new people begin working together. During this stage, the team's performance will typically be lower than in later stages as the group starts figuring out how to best work together."},
  {id:73,question:"Who defines the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The development organization (or the Scrum Team if none is available from the development organization)"},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner as he/she is responsible for maximizing the value of the work done by the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master as he/she is responsibility for managing the process."},{key:"D",text:"The company as it responsible for providing the environment and support the Scrum Team needs."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The ones doing the work are the best ones to define the level of quality of the work and what it means to be done."},
  {id:74,question:"When Developers from multiple Scrum Teams are working on the same product, how should the Definition of Done be created?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Developers from each Scrum Team creates its own and ensures all other Teams understand the differences."},{key:"B",text:"Developers from each Scrum Team will create and adhere to their own."},{key:"C",text:"They must follow a single Definition of Done."},{key:"D",text:"Developers from all Scrum Teams must have a Definition of Done that makes their combined work potentially releasable."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The importance is the teams' ability to produce shippable Increments and having transparency on what 'done' means."},
  {id:75,question:"How much time should be spent refining the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"As much as the Scrum Team agrees is necessary to create enough ready Product Backlog Items."},{key:"B",text:"As much as the Product Owner deems necessary to create enough ready Product Backlog Items."},{key:"C",text:"Up to 10% of the capacity of the Developers in a typical Sprint, but as much as 90% in early Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"No more than 1 day per week for the Developers."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Team decides how and when refinement is done. Refinement usually consumes no more than 10% of the capacity of the Developers."},
  {id:76,question:"Which of the following events has the shortest time-box in a four-week Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Retrospective"},{key:"B",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Review"},{key:"D",text:"Product Backlog Refinement"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Sprint Planning: 8 hours, Sprint Review: 4 hours, Sprint Retrospective: 3 hours for a four-week Sprint."},
  {id:77,question:"Which role is responsible for understanding the requirements of the project and creating the deliverables?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Team Leader"},{key:"B",text:"The Developers"},{key:"C",text:"Scrum Master"},{key:"D",text:"Product Owner"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers consists of professionals who do the work of delivering a potentially releasable Increment of 'Done' product at the end of each Sprint."},
  {id:78,question:"What is the Scrum Master's role during the Daily Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask each Developer what he/she did yesterday, will do today, and any impediments."},{key:"B",text:"Update the Scrum board."},{key:"C",text:"Assign tasks to each team member."},{key:"D",text:"Ensure the Developers understand and enact the Daily Scrum to maximize value."},{key:"E",text:"All answers apply."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Scrum Master ensures that the Developers have the Daily Scrum, but the Developers are responsible for conducting the Daily Scrum."},
  {id:79,question:"Which of the following activities is NOT usually Time-boxed?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Daily Scrum"},{key:"B",text:"Refining the Product Backlog"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"D",text:"Sprint Review"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Team will decide how and when refinement is done. Refinement usually consumes no more than 10% of the capacity of the Developers."},
  {id:80,question:"An eight-hour Sprint Planning is the maximum time-box for Sprints that are ... long.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Four weeks"},{key:"B",text:"Three weeks"},{key:"C",text:"One week"},{key:"D",text:"Two weeks"},{key:"E",text:"Any of the above."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"Sprint Planning has a maximum time-box of 8 hours for one-month Sprints and usually shorter for shorter Sprints. The time-box for Sprint Planning is limited to 8 hours regardless of the length of the Sprint."}
];
const psm1Test2Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Which of the following is NOT an advantage of using Scrum to deliver projects?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It makes projects adaptable and open to incorporating change."},{key:"B",text:"It minimizes non-essential work and leads to higher efficiency levels."},{key:"C",text:"It leads to greater levels of motivation among employees."},{key:"D",text:"It ensures that all requirements are delivered at the end of the project."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Scrum cannot guarantee all requirements are delivered as the complex domain represents 'unknown unknowns'."},
  {id:2,question:"Which of the following is a valid service from the Scrum Master to the Product Owner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Helping the Product Owner find techniques for managing the Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Act as a proxy when the Product Owner is not available to the team."},{key:"C",text:"Helping the Product Owner order the Product Backlog items in order to maximize value."},{key:"D",text:"Act as the middleman between the Product Owner and the Development Team."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master helps find techniques for effective Product Backlog management."},
  {id:3,question:"Which of the following statements about the Scrum framework is TRUE?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Focuses on detailed upfront project planning."},{key:"B",text:"Allows teams to take ownership of the work."},{key:"C",text:"Enables delegation of authority from one level to another."},{key:"D",text:"Emphasizes individual accountability rather than group accountability."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum Teams are self-managing and cross-functional."},
  {id:4,question:"Which of the following statements best describes a Scrum Team?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A Scrum Team must be between 3-9 members."},{key:"B",text:"A Scrum Team should be in place before the project is initiated."},{key:"C",text:"A Scrum Team delivers products iteratively and incrementally."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master determines when to extend or reduce the Sprint length."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Scrum Teams deliver products iteratively and incrementally, maximizing opportunities for feedback."},
  {id:5,question:"The Agile Manifesto states that we value individuals and interactions _____ processes and tools.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"over"},{key:"B",text:"less than"},{key:"C",text:"as much as"},{key:"D",text:"in place of"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Agile Manifesto values Individuals and interactions over processes and tools."},
  {id:6,question:"What is the purpose of the Sprint Review?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"To track the Scrum Team's productivity throughout the development process."},{key:"B",text:"To update management of project status and team performance."},{key:"C",text:"It is a collaboration between the Scrum Team and stakeholders to inspect the Increment and adapt the Product Backlog if needed."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"A Sprint Review is held to inspect the Increment and adapt the Product Backlog if needed."},
  {id:7,question:"Which concept is the basis of the business justification aspect in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Risk-driven delivery"},{key:"B",text:"Value-driven delivery"},{key:"C",text:"Time-driven delivery"},{key:"D",text:"Change-driven delivery"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value of the product."},
  {id:8,question:"Every Sprint cycle begins with a _____________ meeting.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Release Planning"},{key:"B",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"C",text:"Retrospective"},{key:"D",text:"Project Vision"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The work to be performed in the Sprint is planned at the Sprint Planning."},
  {id:9,question:"How long can a Sprint be if a team takes four-hours in Sprint Planning?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Four weeks"},{key:"B",text:"Three weeks"},{key:"C",text:"One week"},{key:"D",text:"Two weeks"},{key:"E",text:"Any of the above."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"Sprint Planning has a maximum of 8 hours for one-month Sprints. A 4-hour Sprint Planning can work for any Sprint length."},
  {id:10,question:"When does the Sprint end?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When all Sprint Backlog items meet the definition of Done."},{key:"B",text:"When the time-box expires."},{key:"C",text:"When the Scrum Master says it's done."},{key:"D",text:"When there is no more work to be done."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Sprints have consistent durations. A new Sprint starts immediately after the previous Sprint."},
  {id:11,question:"What is management's role in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"To provide the necessary environment and support needed by providing insights and resources that help the Scrum Teams continue moving forward."},{key:"B",text:"Identifying and removing people that are performing poorly."},{key:"C",text:"Monitoring skill levels of the Developers."},{key:"D",text:"Monitoring the Scrum Team's velocity."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Getting support from the business side helps facilitate the changes that foster empiricism."},
  {id:12,question:"What would likely happen if management only changed terminology to fit Scrum without proper understanding?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Very little change will happen as the vocabulary is specifically defined for implementing Scrum."},{key:"B",text:"The organization may not realize the real benefits of Scrum as there would be no real change."},{key:"C",text:"Organizations may feel less stressed as the behaviors would remain familiar."},{key:"D",text:"All answers apply."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Understanding the differences between traditional methods and Scrum will help move teams in the right direction."},
  {id:13,question:"Flexibility in Scrum is NOT achieved through which of the following?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Iterative product development"},{key:"B",text:"Customer value-based prioritization"},{key:"C",text:"Time-boxing"},{key:"D",text:"High velocity"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Having a high velocity does not always translate into business value."},
  {id:14,question:"Which statement best describes Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A clearly defined methodology that defines the software development process."},{key:"B",text:"A manual for defining best practices for software development."},{key:"C",text:"A clearly defined and predictable process that follows the principles of Computer Science."},{key:"D",text:"A framework to address complex products in complex environments."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Frameworks allow those closest to the problem the flexibility to creatively deliver products."},
  {id:15,question:"True or False: In order to start the first Sprint, Scrum only requires a Product Owner with enough ideas, Developers to execute, and a Scrum Master to guide the process.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"A PO with enough ideas, Developers to execute, and an SM is the minimum requirements."},
  {id:16,question:"Scrum is based on which of the following?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Defined process."},{key:"B",text:"Complex process."},{key:"C",text:"Empiricism."},{key:"D",text:"Hybrid model."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Scrum asserts that knowledge comes from experience and making decisions based on what is known."},
  {id:17,question:"True or False: Stakeholders are only allowed to meet with the Scrum Team at Sprint Review.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Stakeholders can engage with the Scrum Team during Refinement, Sprint Planning or during the Sprint."},
  {id:18,question:"Which item should NOT be raised during a retrospective meeting?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There should be more emphasis on unit testing in the future."},{key:"B",text:"The build process is manual and takes too long."},{key:"C",text:"John, the tester, is struggling to find defects. The Scrum Master requests test training for this resource."},{key:"D",text:"Automated regression test suites are taking too long to run."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is making an assumption. Their role is to facilitate conversations for the team to decide."},
  {id:19,question:"Which Scrum Value impacts trust?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Respect"},{key:"B",text:"Courage"},{key:"C",text:"Commitment"},{key:"D",text:"Openness"},{key:"E",text:"Focus"},{key:"F",text:"All of the above"}],correctAnswers:["F"],explanation:"Without trust, team members will have difficulties acting in ways that reflect the Scrum values."},
  {id:20,question:"Doing your best and helping other Scrum Team members demonstrates which of the following?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Value of Commitment"},{key:"B",text:"Increased Revenue"},{key:"C",text:"Increased Profit"},{key:"D",text:"Maximizing utilization"},{key:"E",text:"High Performance"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"People personally commit to achieving the goals of the Scrum Team by doing their best and helping others."},
  {id:21,question:"Peter, a Project Manager, has raised concerns about your Scrum Team's productivity. Which is the best way to respond?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Share the Product Backlog, the projections towards the release dates and ensure that Peter has access."},{key:"B",text:"Show the Profit & Loss (P&L) report."},{key:"C",text:"Share the current impediments."},{key:"D",text:"Share the last stakeholder status report prepared by the Scrum Master."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Transparency will help manage stakeholder expectations and allow teams to effectively adapt."},
  {id:22,question:"The three pillars of empirical process control consist of:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Planning, Inspection, Adaptation"},{key:"B",text:"Inspection, Transparency, Adaptation"},{key:"C",text:"Planning, Demonstration, Retrospective"},{key:"D",text:"Respect for People, Kaizen, Eliminating Waste"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"These 3 pillars uphold every implementation of the empirical process control."},
  {id:23,question:"What does a trendline projection through a release burn-down chart indicate?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When all work will be completed so the Scrum Team can start work on a new Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"When the project will be over if the Product Owner removes work equal to any new work added."},{key:"C",text:"When work remaining is projected to be completed if nothing changes on the Product Backlog or the Scrum Team."},{key:"D",text:"The evolution of the return of investment on the project."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The trendline is based on the team's average velocity and projects completion based on current state."},
  {id:24,question:"What is a good way for a Scrum Team to ensure that security concerns are addressed and transparent?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Add Security Sprints to resolve security concerns when needed."},{key:"B",text:"Have the Scrum Team create Product Backlog items for each concern and/or add security concerns to the Definition of Done."},{key:"C",text:"Create a separate backlog for security items."},{key:"D",text:"Delegate the work to an external team."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Backlog and the Definition of Done are artifacts that promote transparency."},
  {id:25,question:"True or False: Technical Debt can lead to false assumptions about the current state of the system.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"A team can have an artificially high velocity by taking shortcuts or introducing technical debt."},
  {id:26,question:"True or False: When technical debt occurs, the system will become more unstable as development progresses.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Technical debt will compound and have a negative effect on the team's ability to deliver value if neglected."},
  {id:27,question:"Who can change the Sprint Backlog in the middle of the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Only the Scrum Master"},{key:"B",text:"Only the Developers"},{key:"C",text:"Only the Product Owner"},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Team"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Only the Developers can change its Sprint Backlog during a Sprint."},
  {id:28,question:"At the eighth Sprint Review, stakeholders are upset that the product is not what they expected. What may have led to this?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master has not been reporting on progress. The Product Owner has not been managing tasks effectively."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master has not ensured transparency. The Product Owner has not made stakeholders aware of progress. The stakeholders have not been attending Sprint Reviews."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master has not been attending the Daily Standup. The Product Owner has not been using the Gantt chart correctly."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum requires significant aspects of the process to be visible to those responsible for the outcome."},
  {id:29,question:"Select the correct Scrum Team members defined in Scrum.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Developers, Scrum Master, Product Owner"},{key:"B",text:"Engineers, Business Analyst, Product Owner"},{key:"C",text:"Stakeholders, Scrum Master, Project Manager, Product Owner"},{key:"D",text:"Product Manager, Business Analyst, Developers, Stakeholders"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Framework only recognizes Developers, Scrum Master, Product Owner."},
  {id:30,question:"True or False: Scrum has a role called Project Manager.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Framework consists of a Scrum Master, a Product Owner and Developers."},
  {id:31,question:"A Scrum Team has been working on the same product for 12 Sprints. What would be the immediate impact if two new Scrum Teams are added?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Its productivity is likely to decrease."},{key:"B",text:"Its productivity is likely to increase."},{key:"C",text:"Its productivity is likely to stay the same."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The original team would need time to assist and support the new Scrum Teams."},
  {id:32,question:"What would be the main benefits of self-managing?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Increased rule compliance, self-accountability, commitment."},{key:"B",text:"Increased rule compliance, self-accountability, output."},{key:"C",text:"Increased capacity, accuracy of estimates, output."},{key:"D",text:"Increased creativity, self-accountability, commitment."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Self-managed teams allow teams to creatively solve difficult problems, be accountable, and commit to each other."},
  {id:33,question:"True or False: A Scrum Team must have a Product Owner and Scrum Master.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"False. A Scrum Master is only necessary when requested or needed."},{key:"B",text:"True. Each must be a full-time member on the Scrum Team."},{key:"C",text:"True. Their participation and availability will impact the outcomes produced by the Scrum Team."},{key:"D",text:"False. If a Product Owner is unavailable, he/she can be replaced by a Business Analyst."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"How much time they spend with each team will directly impact effectiveness."},
  {id:34,question:"In what ways does the Scrum Master keep the Developers working at their highest level of productivity?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"By removing impediments that hinder the Developers and facilitating their decisions."},{key:"B",text:"By helping the Developers with user acceptance tests and tracking defects."},{key:"C",text:"By ensuring each member takes turns speaking at the Daily Scrum."},{key:"D",text:"By keeping the Scrum board and burn-down chart updated daily."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master removes impediments and facilitates Scrum events as requested or needed."},
  {id:35,question:"Which statement is true about the Scrum Master role?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master assigns tasks to the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master helps those outside the Scrum Team understand which interactions are helpful and teaches the team to keep events within the time-box."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master is responsible for updating the Scrum board."},{key:"D",text:"At the Sprint Review, the Scrum Master demonstrates the completed Increment."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is responsible for coaching the Scrum Team and the organization."},
  {id:36,question:"Flexibility on Scrum projects is achieved through which of the following?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Specialized teams."},{key:"B",text:"Detailed upfront planning."},{key:"C",text:"Value-based Prioritization."},{key:"D",text:"Non-iterative delivery."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Sprint Goal provides guidance. The Sprint Backlog emerges during the Sprint as Developers learn more."},
  {id:37,question:"A Scrum Team with remote Developers spends extra time setting up meetings. How should the Scrum Master handle this?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Allow the Developers to self-manage and decide for itself what to do."},{key:"B",text:"Setup the meeting and tell the Developers how it will be done."},{key:"C",text:"Ask the Developers to alternate responsibilities for setting up the meeting."},{key:"D",text:"Inform management and ask them to solve it."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"As a self-managed team, they will decide for themselves how to best manage communication."},
  {id:38,question:"Which statement is correct when the Developers are working in the middle of the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Sprint Backlog would be frozen."},{key:"B",text:"No user acceptance tests will be conducted until the end of the Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"The scope may be clarified as more is learned."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The scope may be clarified or re-negotiated with the Product Owner."},
  {id:39,question:"A Developer has notified the Scrum Master of a potential data security risk. What action should the Scrum Master take?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Notify the test team."},{key:"B",text:"Add a Product Backlog item to address the security issue."},{key:"C",text:"Ask the Developer to share the issue with the team as soon as possible."},{key:"D",text:"Wait until the Sprint Retrospective to add security to the Definition of Done."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"It is best to coach the Developers to collaborate on issues regardless of severity."},
  {id:40,question:"A Scrum Master's list of open impediments is growing. Which would be the LEAST helpful technique?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Consulting with the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"Prioritizing the list and working on them in order."},{key:"C",text:"Arranging a triage meeting with all project managers."},{key:"D",text:"Alerting management to the impediments and their impact."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Scrum does not have project managers and arranging a triage meeting would not help."},
  {id:41,question:"Your organization has formed a new Scrum Team. In what ways would help the team start?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ensure Scrum Team members have compatible personalities, have tech leads clarify expectations, and propose a performance rewards system."},{key:"B",text:"Have team members introduce their background experience, ask the Product Owner to discuss the product, and ensure the team understands the need for a Definition of Done."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum Teams should understand the goals and history of the product and what 'done' means."},
  {id:42,question:"What guideline should the Scrum Master provide if the Product Owner asks how estimations should be made?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Estimates must be made in Story Points."},{key:"B",text:"Estimates must be in relative units."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers are responsible for estimating the size of the work."},{key:"D",text:"Estimates are made by the Product Owner."},{key:"E",text:"Estimates must follow the Fibonacci Sequence."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The people who will perform the work are the best ones to estimate the size of the work."},
  {id:43,question:"The Developers discover they don't have the tools to make each Product Backlog item done. What should the Scrum Master do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Stop the Sprint and have the Developers work on the infrastructure before continuing."},{key:"B",text:"Encourage the Product Owner to accept partially done Increments."},{key:"C",text:"Coach the Developers to improve their skills, tools and infrastructure over time and establish a Definition of Done that is actually possible."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master coaches the team in self-managing and cross-functionality."},
  {id:44,question:"The Developers have suggested to move the Daily Scrum to every other day. What is the most appropriate action?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Learn why the Developers want this, coach them on why the Daily Scrum is important and work with them to improve the outcome."},{key:"B",text:"Support the Developers' self-managing decision."},{key:"C",text:"Have the Developers vote on which days the Daily Scrum should occur."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is responsible for promoting and supporting Scrum as defined in the Scrum Guide."},
  {id:45,question:"Which event is conducted at the end of a Sprint to analyze process improvement opportunities?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Review"},{key:"B",text:"Sprint Retrospective"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"D",text:"Daily Scrum"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Retrospective is an opportunity for the Scrum Team to inspect itself and create a plan for improvements."},
  {id:46,question:"What action can the Scrum Master take to ensure communication between Developers and Product Owner is effective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ensure all communication goes through the Scrum Master first."},{key:"B",text:"Teach the Product Owner to talk in terms of technology."},{key:"C",text:"Observe the communications between them and facilitate discussions if needed or by request."},{key:"D",text:"Translate the technologies used by the Developers for the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"One of the primary responsibilities of a Scrum Master is the ability to facilitate."},
  {id:47,question:"How should a Scrum Master coordinate work when more than one Scrum Team is working on one product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Teach them that it's their responsibility to coordinate with the other teams to create a shippable product Increment."},{key:"B",text:"Identify and manage the dependencies between Scrum Teams."},{key:"C",text:"Have the Product Owner work with tech leads to parse the Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"Merge the teams and work from a single Sprint Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Self-managed teams decide how best to work together to produce a shippable Increment."},
  {id:48,question:"What would be typical Scrum Master activities during the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Monitor the progress of the Developers and assigning tasks."},{key:"B",text:"Remove impediments and facilitating inspection and adaptation opportunities as requested or needed."},{key:"C",text:"Avoiding conflicts and escalating to line managers if conflicts occur."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Master removes impediments and facilitates inspection and adaptation opportunities."},
  {id:49,question:"True or False: The Scrum Master is responsible for the process in which Scrum is adopted and enacted.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is responsible for managing the boundaries that Scrum provides."},
  {id:50,question:"You observe that the Product Owner is not effectively collaborating with the Developers. What actions would you take?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Send the Product Owner to training."},{key:"B",text:"Nominate a proxy Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"Act as the go-between."},{key:"D",text:"Coach the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"A Scrum Master coaches those inside and outside the team on the values of Scrum."},
  {id:51,question:"True or False: A Scrum Master teaches that progress in Scrum comes from inspecting an Increment at the Sprint Review.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Working software is the primary measure of progress."},
  {id:52,question:"What is sustainable pace?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The pace at which the Scrum Team can work and sustain comfortably for an indefinite period of time."},{key:"B",text:"The pace at which the Scrum Team converts User Stories into deliverables."},{key:"C",text:"The pace at which the Scrum Team releases project deliverables."},{key:"D",text:"The pace at which the Scrum Team can work and sustain comfortably in a set of Sprints leading to a release."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Agile processes promote sustainable development. The pace should be maintained indefinitely."},
  {id:53,question:"Which statement best describes collaboration?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"This principle describes how time is considered a limiting constraint in Scrum."},{key:"B",text:"This principle focuses on today's workers, who deliver greater value when encouraged to self-manage."},{key:"C",text:"This principle focuses on awareness, articulation, and appropriation. It advocates project management as a shared value-creation process."},{key:"D",text:"This principle highlights the focus of Scrum to deliver maximum business value."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Teams collaborate and interoperate with team members and stakeholders to maximize opportunities of success."},
  {id:54,question:"What is the most appropriate action if the Product Owner is having difficulties managing the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Have the Developers order the work instead."},{key:"B",text:"Have the Product Owner order items based on size."},{key:"C",text:"Offer the Product Owner help in understanding that the goal is to maximize the flow of value."},{key:"D",text:"Delegate the work to the Assistant Product Owner."},{key:"E",text:"Delay the Sprint for the Product Owner to have enough time to prioritize."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Product Owner's primary concern is the flow of value reflected in the ordering of the Product Backlog."},
  {id:55,question:"What is a Product Owner responsibility that he/she might delegate?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Writing User Stories"},{key:"B",text:"Ordering the Product Backlog"},{key:"C",text:"Representing stakeholders to the Scrum team"},{key:"D",text:"Attending the Sprint Review"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers may help order the Product Backlog as they know about technical limitations and dependencies."},
  {id:56,question:"What action should a Scrum Master take if the Developers decide that Retrospectives are no longer necessary?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Start facilitating more productive and useful Retrospectives."},{key:"B",text:"Suggest reducing the frequency of Retrospectives."},{key:"C",text:"Extend the Sprint time-box in order to fit the Retrospectives."},{key:"D",text:"Comply with the team's decision."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master should facilitate more productive and useful Retrospectives."},
  {id:57,question:"Which stakeholder is the most important for the Product Owner to satisfy?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The company founder"},{key:"B",text:"The board of directors"},{key:"C",text:"The Head of Product"},{key:"D",text:"The Product's users"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The highest priority is to satisfy the end users."},
  {id:58,question:"What would you strive for if five new Scrum Teams were to work on one product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There should be five Product Owners, one for each Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"The product has one Product Backlog and one Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"There should be five Product Backlogs and one Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"There should be five Product Backlogs and five Product Owners."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"For a single product there is one Product Backlog and one Product Owner."},
  {id:59,question:"Customer satisfaction should be measured:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Annually"},{key:"B",text:"Quarterly"},{key:"C",text:"Daily"},{key:"D",text:"Frequently"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Frequent enough to ensure the team is building the right thing at the right time."},
  {id:60,question:"A client is complaining about poor performance of the product. As a Scrum Master, how can you help the Product Owner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Coach the Product Owner on effective ways to communicate this concern to the Developers and encourage adding the performance issue to the Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Tell the Product Owner performance is defined by the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"Note the issue for the next Sprint Retrospective."},{key:"D",text:"Notify the team responsible for system performance."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Coach the Product Owner on effective communication and encourage adding the issue to the Product Backlog."},
  {id:61,question:"Why is it important that there is only one Product Owner per product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master knows who will be his back-up, it saves time and money, and Developers know who to request tasks from."},{key:"B",text:"It is clear who is accountable for the success of the product, Developers know who determines priorities, and it avoids barriers to effective communication."},{key:"C",text:"It isn't important as multiple Product Owners can easily share a single Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"One Product Owner provides clear accountability, priority decisions, and effective communication."},
  {id:62,question:"True or False: The Product Owner's primary concern is the flow of value reflected in the ordering of the Product Backlog.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner is the value maximizer. This is done through the ordering of the Product Backlog."},
  {id:63,question:"Which of these tools is mandatory for the Product Owner to use?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Release burnup chart."},{key:"B",text:"Burndown chart."},{key:"C",text:"Version control."},{key:"D",text:"Project Gantt chart."},{key:"E",text:"None of the above."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"The Product Owner can use any tool that helps make the best decisions possible."},
  {id:64,question:"Why does the agile manifesto de-emphasize extensive documentation early in the project?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Software must be working before documentation can be written."},{key:"B",text:"Not enough requirements are known to write documentation."},{key:"C",text:"Rapidly changing requirements would make the documentation outdated."},{key:"D",text:"Documentation can only be written after testing."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Agile welcomes changing requirements. Extensive early documentation would become outdated."},
  {id:65,question:"During Sprint Planning, Developers couldn't forecast a Sprint Backlog but created a Sprint Goal. Which action would you support?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Postpone the Sprint for the Product Owner to refine the Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Extend Sprint Planning until Developers can forecast enough items."},{key:"C",text:"Forecast the most likely items to meet the goal and discuss in the Retrospective why this happened."},{key:"D",text:"Request assistance from the technical architect."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Forecast the most likely items and discuss in the Retrospective why this happened and how to improve."},
  {id:66,question:"A new Product Owner is unsure about responsibilities. Which activity would be most helpful?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Writing User Stories."},{key:"B",text:"Interacting with stakeholders and ensuring the most valuable functionality is always produced first."},{key:"C",text:"Describing features as Use Cases."},{key:"D",text:"Ensuring work is completed within scope and time."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner should interact with stakeholders and ensure the most valuable functionality is produced first."},
  {id:67,question:"How should a Scrum Master divide a group of 100 Developers into multiple Scrum Teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Create Scrum Teams based on functional layer."},{key:"B",text:"Have the resource manager assign people to teams."},{key:"C",text:"Ask the developers to divide themselves into teams."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"A good first question is 'How will we make sure all teams have the right amount of expertise?'"},
  {id:68,question:"Which is the best description of a Product Owner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Requirements developer."},{key:"B",text:"Value optimizer."},{key:"C",text:"Team leader."},{key:"D",text:"Go-between between the Developers and stakeholders."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner is the value optimizer, responsible for maximizing the value of the product."},
  {id:69,question:"Several developers notify you that their teams will need full-time help of an external technical specialist. What key concerns should you consider?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Having enough work for all the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The benefit of Developers solving the problem themselves and the ability to produce integrated Increments."},{key:"C",text:"Maintaining a consistent velocity."},{key:"D",text:"Hiring additional resources to fill the void in skillset."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Consider the benefit of self-solving and the ability to produce integrated Increments."},
  {id:70,question:"Who is responsible for ensuring the Product Backlog items are understood to the level needed?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Business Analyst."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Owner is accountable for managing the Product Backlog."},
  {id:71,question:"Which action is appropriate for a Scrum Master at the Daily Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Making sure each member has an opportunity to say what they did, will do, and any impediments."},{key:"B",text:"Leading the Daily Scrum."},{key:"C",text:"Teaching the Developers to keep the Daily Scrum time-boxed to 15 minutes or less."},{key:"D",text:"Updating the Scrum board."},{key:"E",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master teaches the team to keep the Daily Scrum within the time-box."},
  {id:72,question:"What activities would a Product Owner do during an active Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Engage with the stakeholders and answer questions from the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"Prioritize the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Participate at the Daily Scrum."},{key:"D",text:"Update the burndown chart."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner engages with stakeholders and answers questions from the Developers during the Sprint."},
  {id:73,question:"Who on a Scrum Team would know the most about progress toward a business objective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"B",text:"The Release Manager"},{key:"C",text:"The Developers"},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner knows the most about progress toward business objectives."},
  {id:74,question:"Peter estimated velocity of 21 but after 3 Sprints, the team has velocity of 15 and can't create shippable increments. What is the best way to proceed?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Add more team members to increase capacity."},{key:"B",text:"Coach the team on improving their estimations."},{key:"C",text:"Extend the Sprint to complete the Sprint Backlog items."},{key:"D",text:"Inform Peter the projected completion date is not correct. The Developers would estimate work to produce a shippable Increment first. Based on empirical data, Peter can adjust and decide how to continue."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Inform Peter that projections are not correct and let Peter adjust based on empirical data."},
  {id:75,question:"Which of the following are true about the Product Owner role?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Can be shared between multiple people. Is the same as a Project Manager. Is played by a committee."},{key:"B",text:"Is one person. Can be influenced by a committee. Is accountable for ordering the Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner is one person who can be influenced by a committee and is accountable for ordering the Product Backlog."},
  {id:76,question:"Who manages the progress of work during a Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master"},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"C",text:"The Team Lead"},{key:"D",text:"The Developers"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Developers are self-managing and decide how to manage their own progress."},
  {id:77,question:"True or False: A Product Owner is essentially the same thing as a traditional Project Manager.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner is not the same as a traditional Project Manager."},
  {id:78,question:"What should Developers do if asked by someone outside the team to add an important item to a Sprint in progress?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Add the item to the bottom of the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Replace an item of equal size."},{key:"C",text:"Add the item to the top of the next Sprint Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"Inform the Product Owner so he/she can work with the person."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Allow the Product Owner to decide what to do as he/she is responsible for the flow of value."},
  {id:79,question:"Which Scrum Team member is responsible for engaging with stakeholders?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The team lead"},{key:"B",text:"The business analyst"},{key:"C",text:"The project manager"},{key:"D",text:"The Developers"},{key:"E",text:"The Product Owner"}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for engaging with stakeholders."},
  {id:80,question:"How much work must Developers do to a Product Backlog item selected for a Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"An equal amount of time on analysis, design, programming, testing and documentation."},{key:"B",text:"As much as the Product Owner has been informed will be done in conformance with the Definition of Done."},{key:"C",text:"All development work and at least some testing."},{key:"D",text:"As much as can fit into the Sprint. Any remaining work will be moved to a subsequent Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"As much as the Product Owner has been informed will be done in conformance with the Definition of Done."}
];
const psm1Test3Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Which statement best describes the responsibility of the Product Owner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Optimizing the value of the work to be done by the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"Managing the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"Ensuring that the work meets the commitments to the stakeholders."},{key:"D",text:"Acting as the go-between for the stakeholders."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner is accountable for the flow of value from the work that the Developers do."},
  {id:2,question:"The Developers on the Scrum Team should have all the skills and competencies needed to:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Turn the Product Backlog items they select into a potentially releasable product increment of functionality."},{key:"B",text:"Do all of the development work in order to handoff to the testers in the subsequent Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Complete the project within the estimate as committed to the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Developers should have all the skills needed to turn Product Backlog items into a potentially releasable product increment."},
  {id:3,question:"You have joined a new Scrum Team as the Scrum Master. Up until now, the Product Owner has not been attending Sprint Retrospectives. The Developers have a fear that they will become 'too negative' with the Product Owner present. As a Scrum Master, what should you do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Speak to the Product Owner and see what they think. Do what they suggest is best."},{key:"B",text:"Facilitate a discussion in the Scrum Team and allow them to decide what is best to do."},{key:"C",text:"Respect the Developers' wishes."},{key:"D",text:"Explore further why the Developers fear the presence of the Product Owner. Work with the Scrum Team to find a safe way to introduce the Product Owner to the Sprint Retrospective to enable greater transparency."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Sprint Retrospective is an opportunity for the Scrum Team to inspect itself and create a plan for improvements to be enacted during the next Sprint."},
  {id:4,question:"How often should Scrum Teams change its developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Frequently in order to share knowledge."},{key:"B",text:"As needed, while taking into account a short-term reduction in productivity."},{key:"C",text:"Never, as it conflicts with the Scrum process."},{key:"D",text:"As needed, as long as it doesn't impact productivity."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"It is not mandatory that the same team stay together, although it must be understood that any changes to the team will impact how they work together."},
  {id:5,question:"What are the Developers responsible for?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Writing User Stories and ordering the Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Reporting productivity and selecting the Sprint time-box."},{key:"C",text:"Organizing the work required to meet the Sprint Goal and resolving conflicts between developers."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Developers are responsible for organizing the work required to meet the Sprint Goal."},
  {id:6,question:"According to Scrum theory, how should a group of 50 developers be divided into multiple Scrum Teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Allow the team leads to divide and select teams."},{key:"B",text:"Understanding the product, the product vision and the Scrum framework, the group self-organizes into teams."},{key:"C",text:"Create a skills matrix, identify role levels, and years of experience to assign people to teams."},{key:"D",text:"The teams will rotate members every Sprint to spread knowledge."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The group self-organizes into teams based on understanding the product, vision, and Scrum framework."},
  {id:7,question:"What is the recommended size for a Scrum Team?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"10 or fewer"},{key:"B",text:"Minimal 5"},{key:"C",text:"7 plus or minus 2"},{key:"D",text:"3 to 9"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The recommended size for a Scrum Team is 10 or fewer."},
  {id:8,question:"Who should be present to review and adjust the selected Sprint work if the Developers determine that they will not be able to finish the complete forecast?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The stakeholders and Scrum Master."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner and the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers and Project Manager."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master, the Business Analyst and the Developers."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner and the Developers should be present to review and adjust the selected Sprint work."},
  {id:9,question:"What Scrum Team structure is best suited to produce integrated increments?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers in the Scrum Team have the combined abilities to develop functionality from beginning to end throughout all technical layers."},{key:"B",text:"Each Scrum Team specializes in one technical layer of the system (e.g. GUI, database, middle tier, interfaces)."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Cross-functional teams with combined abilities to develop functionality end-to-end are best suited to produce integrated increments."},
  {id:10,question:"Who determines how to do the work during the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"B",text:"The Technical Architects."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers."},{key:"D",text:"The Team Leads."},{key:"E",text:"The engineering director."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Developers determine how to do the work during the Sprint."},
  {id:11,question:"What should the Developers do if they don't understand a functional requirement?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Request a specialist to be added to the Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"Move the item to a future Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Complete as much as possible and add the remaining work as a new Product Backlog item."},{key:"D",text:"Work with the Product Owner to determine what is possible and acceptable."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Developers should work with the Product Owner to determine what is possible and acceptable."},
  {id:12,question:"What should the Developers do if they realize they had selected too much work after having started the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Modify the definition of Done to ensure all Product Backlog items can be done by the end of the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Work with the Product Owner to remove some work or Product Backlog items as soon as possible."},{key:"C",text:"Add additional team members to handle the extra work."},{key:"D",text:"Continue working and update the Product Owner at the Sprint Review."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a living artifact that evolves and changes as more is learned or discovered."},
  {id:13,question:"Who can change the Sprint Backlog during the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers"},{key:"B",text:"No one"},{key:"C",text:"The Developers and the Product Owner together"},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Only the Developers can change its Sprint Backlog during a Sprint."},
  {id:14,question:"What should the Developers do with non-functional requirements?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ensure they are addressed in every Increment."},{key:"B",text:"Assign them to the technical leads on the team."},{key:"C",text:"They will be addressed in the Integration Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"Add them to a separate non-functional requirements list."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Non-functional requirements should be worked on alongside functional development."},
  {id:15,question:"What would be the responsibilities of self-managing Developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Update stakeholders on the daily progress and keep the burn-down chart updated."},{key:"B",text:"Selecting Product Backlog items for the Sprint and doing the work planned in the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Writing User Stories and reordering the Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"Deciding on the value of the product features and value estimations."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"It's the responsibility of the Developers to size the amount of work for Product Backlog items and to select the appropriate number of items for each Sprint."},
  {id:16,question:"Scrum promotes self-management. Which of these statements would NOT support self-management?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers deciding how work is done in a Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Removing the need for documentation."},{key:"C",text:"Being a lightweight framework."},{key:"D",text:"Removing hierarchies."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"By removing documentation you would reduce sustainability of the product. The Development Team's responsibility is to find the right balance."},
  {id:17,question:"How should multiple Scrum Teams, working from the same Product Backlog, select the Product Backlog items their teams plan to work on?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner will present the work and the Developers will select the items each Scrum Teams will work on."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner creates separate Product Backlogs for each Scrum Team."},{key:"C",text:"Each Scrum Team would select an equal number of items."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner assigns the work to each team."},{key:"E",text:"The Scrum Team with the highest productivity will select the items first."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The ones doing the work are the best ones to decide what they can do and how to do it."},
  {id:18,question:"What would be good ways of creating Scrum Teams that would support the Scrum values?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Project Managers will allocate individuals to specific teams."},{key:"B",text:"Bring all the people or existing teams together and let them propose how to organize into the new structure and self-organize into Scrum Teams."},{key:"C",text:"The operations manager determines the new team structures and assignments."},{key:"D",text:"Direct managers personally re-assign current reports to new teams."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The ones that will be doing the work are the best ones to decide on what Scrum Team structures work best."},
  {id:19,question:"True of False: Every Scrum Team should have the competencies and skills needed to deliver a Done Increment in a Sprint.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Scrum Teams are self-managed and cross-functional."},
  {id:20,question:"How is the Product Backlog ordered?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Items at the top are smaller than the items at the bottom."},{key:"B",text:"Items at the top have lower risk than the items at the bottom."},{key:"C",text:"Items at the top have higher return on investment than the items at the bottom."},{key:"D",text:"Items at the top are more important than the items at the bottom."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for ordering the items in the Product Backlog to best achieve goals and missions."},
  {id:21,question:"Who is responsible for determining when it is most appropriate to update the Sprint Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"B",text:"The Developers"},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Team"},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers are responsible for tracking the remaining work of the Sprint."},
  {id:22,question:"True or False: Cross-functional teams are specialized for working on specific system components (e.g. design, database, backend, frontend).",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Cross-functional teams have all the skills and competencies needed to deliver end-to-end work."},
  {id:23,question:"The Scrum Guide defines an effective Scrum Team to be cross-functional, where all the skills needed to build a product exists within the team. While starting Scrum, what would be the advantages of keeping the existing component teams (e.g. design, database, backend, frontend)?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Component teams would have all the needed skills needed to focus on their specific technical layer."},{key:"B",text:"Component teams generally have all the skills needed to deliver shippable Increments that add business value."},{key:"C",text:"Because their productivity is already predictable, they can deliver shippable Increments more quickly than a newly formed team."},{key:"D",text:"Because they have been working together for some time, there will be less initial disruption than a newly formed team. As they begin working, they will discover what works best and how to move towards cross-functional teams."},{key:"E",text:"There is less communication overhead than working in feature teams."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Gradually transitioning into cross-functional teams could be less disruptive than abruptly forming new teams."},
  {id:24,question:"Currently, your engineering department is organized in siloed teams that specialize by function (for example, design, front-end, back-end, database, and testing). What would you consider when moving away from component teams towards feature teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"You cannot begin Scrum without have feature teams. It is easier to measure and compare performance between feature teams. Feature teams should have an equal number of team members."},{key:"B",text:"Members within feature teams require compatible personalities. Feature teams should have a mix of junior and senior members. Tasks are completed more quickly than component teams."},{key:"C",text:"Moving from component teams to feature teams could reduce productivity in the initial stages. Feature teams have less communication complexity. Getting the support from the business side makes the transition easier."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The initial phase of forming a new team could cause short-term disruption as they need time to discover how to best work together."},
  {id:25,question:"Part of the team's Definition of Done requires creating or updating technical documentation in order to maintain the product and/or features in the future. The team's technical writer will be on vacation during the Sprint. What should you do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Encourage the technical writers from other teams to form a specialized team to organize and plan the work for multiple teams."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers will write it as they are still responsible for creating the documentation to make the Increment done in conformance with their Definition of Done."},{key:"C",text:"Wait until the technical writer returns before continuing with related items."},{key:"D",text:"Complete all development work first while adding technical documentation to the Product Backlog to be done in a subsequent Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"All Product Backlog items selected for the Sprint are owned by the Developers as a whole."},
  {id:26,question:"A cross-functional Scrum Team is defined as:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Cross-skilled individuals who are able to do all the work necessary to create value by the end of the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"A team of engineers, testers, business analysts, technical architects and functional managers."},{key:"C",text:"A group of full-stack developers shared across multiple teams."},{key:"D",text:"A team of skilled developers that can effectively multi-task on multiple Product Backlog items at the same time."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The objective of the Sprint is to produce value at the end of each Sprint so that the team can effectively inspect and adapt accordingly."},
  {id:27,question:"Who is responsible for managing the tasks of the Developers during the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Project Manager."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"D",text:"The Developers."},{key:"E",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Developers are responsible for managing and tracking the progress of their work during a Sprint."},
  {id:28,question:"Who must ensure that the work done for a Product Backlog item conforms to the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The test team."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Team."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"E",text:"The Developers."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"The Developers are accountable for instilling quality by adhering to a Definition of Done."},
  {id:29,question:"Kevin is a senior developer that has recently joined an existing Scrum Team. The existing team members are unable to get along with Kevin and conclude that he is not a culture fit. If necessary, who is responsible for removing the new team member, and why?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master because he/she is responsible for removing Impediments."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers are responsible because it is an internal localized issue, and may request help from the Scrum Master."},{key:"C",text:"The HR department, as they are responsible for the hiring process."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner because he/she is responsible for managing the team."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers are responsible for addressing internal conflicts and may request help from the Scrum Master if needed."},
  {id:30,question:"The Sprint length should be:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Short enough to keep the business risk acceptable to the Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"Short enough to be able to synchronize the development work with other business events."},{key:"C",text:"No more than one month."},{key:"D",text:"All of these answers are correct."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"All of these answers are correct regarding Sprint length."},
  {id:31,question:"What is iterative development?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It refers to using more than one product development cycle to develop the final project deliverables through the learning from the previous development cycles."},{key:"B",text:"It refers to developing the final project deliverables in one product development cycle."},{key:"C",text:"It refers to developing project deliverables using automated processes."},{key:"D",text:"It refers to developing project outputs through detailed upfront planning with emphasis on fixing scope, quality and other project aspects."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Scrum employs an iterative, incremental approach to optimize predictability and control risk."},
  {id:32,question:"When does a new Sprint begin?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Immediately after the next Sprint Planning."},{key:"B",text:"Immediately after the end of the previous Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"It depends on the Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"Every Monday."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"A new Sprint begins immediately after the end of the previous Sprint."},
  {id:33,question:"What might be a valid reason for abnormally cancelling a Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When the Developers discover it cannot meet their Sprint commitments."},{key:"B",text:"When the work becomes too difficult for the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"When the sales department discovers features that add more value than the current work being done."},{key:"D",text:"When the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"A Sprint would be cancelled if the Sprint Goal becomes obsolete."},
  {id:34,question:"Which of the following is NOT a benefit of using Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ensures that the highest value requirements of the customer are satisfied first as it works on the principle of value-based prioritization."},{key:"B",text:"Leads to a high trust work environment ensuring low friction among employees as it promotes transparency and collaboration."},{key:"C",text:"Leads to an innovative and creative work environment as it creates an environment of introspection, learning and adaptation."},{key:"D",text:"Ensures that products are developed over an agreed period of time as it emphasizes detailed planning at the beginning of the project."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory and does not emphasize detailed upfront planning."},
  {id:35,question:"When does a Sprint end?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When there is no work remaining in the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"When the time-box expires."},{key:"C",text:"It depends on the Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"Immediately after the conclusion of the Sprint Review."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"A Sprint ends when the time-box expires."},
  {id:36,question:"What must the Scrum Team do during the first Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Create a potentially shippable product Increment that includes at least one piece of functionality."},{key:"B",text:"Analyze and estimate the requirements for the subsequent Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"Create a project plan in order to map functional development to Sprint dates."},{key:"D",text:"Only design and develop the architecture and infrastructure."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Sprints promote iterative and incremental development."},
  {id:37,question:"True or False: An objective of a Sprint is to produce a potentially releasable product Increment.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Sprints promote iterative and incremental development."},
  {id:38,question:"What Product Owner activities occur between the end of the current Sprint and the beginning of the next Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Product Backlog refinement."},{key:"B",text:"Updating stakeholders on project progress."},{key:"C",text:"There are no such activities. When the current Sprint ends, the new Sprint begins."},{key:"D",text:"Participate as a team member at the Sprint Retrospective."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"When the current Sprint ends, the new Sprint begins immediately."},
  {id:39,question:"What factors are best considered when defining the Sprint length?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"How often team membership changes and the size of the Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"Having consistent Sprint length across all Scrum Teams."},{key:"C",text:"The level of expertise over the technology to be used, ability to release an Increment to the end users, and the risk of being disconnected from the stakeholders."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Sprint length should consider technology expertise, ability to release, and stakeholder connection risk."},
  {id:40,question:"True or False: Multiple Scrum Teams working from the same Product Backlog must have the same Sprint start dates.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Multiple Scrum Teams could have the same Sprint start dates but it is not mandatory."},
  {id:41,question:"The Scrum Team gathers for the Sprint Planning meeting. The Product Owner has some stories but the team finds that the stories do not provide enough information to make a forecast. The next immediate step is:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master cancels the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers proceed with starting with whatever is known."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers make it transparent that they cannot make a forecast with insufficient information and negotiates with the Product Owner on refining the stories to a ready state."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Team discusses the root cause in the Retrospective."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"When the PBIs are presented during Sprint Planning, they are discussed and clarified to the level needed."},
  {id:42,question:"Which of the following are feedback loops in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Daily Scrum, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective"},{key:"B",text:"Daily Standup, Sprint Review, and Sprint Retrospective"},{key:"C",text:"Release Planning, Daily Scrum, and Sprint Review"},{key:"D",text:"Grooming, Daily Status, and Sprint Review"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Daily Scrum is exclusive to Scrum with explicitly defined ownership, time-box, and purpose."},
  {id:43,question:"Who is ultimately accountable for the order of the items in the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Project Manager"},{key:"B",text:"The Developers"},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master"},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"E",text:"The Scrum Team"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value of the product through ordering of the Product Backlog."},
  {id:44,question:"The Developers can cancel the Sprint:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When the availability of the Product Owner is less than expected."},{key:"B",text:"When the requirements for the work to be done becomes unclear or not understood."},{key:"C",text:"It can't. Only the Product Owner can cancel Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"When the Sprint Backlog is determined to be unachievable."},{key:"E",text:"When too many impediments occur."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Only the Product Owner can cancel Sprints."},
  {id:45,question:"A new developer joins the Scrum Team taking the total number to 10 people. As a Scrum Master, what should you do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Instruct the Developers to split into 2 teams, they should decide the appropriate sizes."},{key:"B",text:"Raise the increased team size as a potential impediment and help the Developers decide what to do about it."},{key:"C",text:"Instruct the developers to split into 2 teams with 5 Developers in each Scrum Team."},{key:"D",text:"Do nothing, the Developers must fix its own issues."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"As a Scrum Master, you should ensure that the Developers are aware of the impact the change may have."},
  {id:46,question:"You are the Product Owner on a new Scrum project in your organization. Which of the following statements do NOT hold true for your project?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The customer is not yet clear on what the end product will be like."},{key:"B",text:"The project ensures effective and timely incorporation of the feedback received."},{key:"C",text:"The project will create predetermined deliverables at scheduled points of a plan."},{key:"D",text:"The processes and tools can be tuned and adjusted according to the changing business requirements."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory and employs an iterative, incremental approach."},
  {id:47,question:"Which of the following is a benefit of using Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It enables detailed planning at the beginning of the project hence ensures that all the risks are identified and mitigated."},{key:"B",text:"It provides complete control over the project to the Product Owner as he is responsible for all the product development activities in a Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"It is based on the principle value-based prioritization thus ensures that highest value is provided in the shortest period possible."},{key:"D",text:"It is based on the principle of managing by stages thus ensures that all the expected benefits are realized at the end of the project."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Scrum is a framework for delivering products of the highest possible value through an iterative, incremental approach."},
  {id:48,question:"Which role in Scrum is responsible for achieving maximum business value through the project?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Product Owner"},{key:"B",text:"Scrum Master"},{key:"C",text:"Scrum Team"},{key:"D",text:"The CEO"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value of the product resulting from work of the Developers."},
  {id:49,question:"The Head of Product has asked the Developers to add a new feature to the current Sprint. What is the appropriate response from the Developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Add the item to the top of the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Replace an item in the Sprint Backlog of equivalent size."},{key:"C",text:"Start work on it immediately and continue with the remaining items after it has been completed."},{key:"D",text:"Notify the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value. No one can force the Developers to work from a different set of requirements."},
  {id:50,question:"Which of the following best defines collaboration?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It refers to individual Scrum Team members being aware of each other's work."},{key:"B",text:"It refers to the Scrum Team working together and interfacing with the stakeholders to create and validate the deliverables of the project to meet the stated goals."},{key:"C",text:"It refers to achieving results by focusing on the needs of the Scrum Team."},{key:"D",text:"It refers to proposes fixing a certain amount of time for each process and activity in a Scrum project."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"They collaborate and interoperate with team members and stakeholders in order to maximize opportunities of success."},
  {id:51,question:"Luke has been appointed the Product Owner for building the infrastructure for the proposed monorail system for the city of Lowenham. In his capacity as the Product Owner, which of the following would NOT help Luke ensure that the project deliverables are delivered in an iterative manner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"By ensuring that Epics are developed in the Initiate phase, and are not altered anytime in the later processes."},{key:"B",text:"By ensuring that each complex Produce Backlog Item is broken down through progressive elaboration during later processes."},{key:"C",text:"By focusing on value and its continuous delivery within each Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"By ensuring that the Scrum Team understands the Product Backlog Items in the Sprint Backlog to the level needed."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory and employs an iterative, incremental approach."},
  {id:52,question:"The Developers decide to adopt a #noestimates policy. The CIO and COO require all projects and work to be estimated in days/hours. They blame you, the Scrum Master, for the absence of this information. As a Scrum Master, what should you do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Discuss and understand the need for estimates from the CIO and COO, and the reasons for the Developers adopting #noestimates. Help the CIO and COO understand the potential waste in estimation and the opportunities for increased value delivery that will be possible."},{key:"B",text:"Support the CIO and COO and instruct the Developers to abandon #noestimates."},{key:"C",text:"Discuss and understand the need for estimates from the CIO and COO, and the reasons for the Developers adopting #noestimates. Facilitate a discussion. Help them find the best possible solution under the circumstances."},{key:"D",text:"Support the decision of the Developers which was reached via self-management."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is responsible for promoting and supporting Scrum and helping everyone understand Scrum theory, practices, rules, and values."},
  {id:53,question:"Scrum framework is best suited for which of the following projects?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Projects with fixed scope and timelines."},{key:"B",text:"Projects with changing requirements."},{key:"C",text:"Projects with stable requirements."},{key:"D",text:"Projects with defined roles and responsibilities."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum is founded on empirical process control theory. It is a framework for addressing complex adaptive problems."},
  {id:54,question:"How much work must be done to each Sprint Backlog item in a Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Analyze, design, implement, test, document and approval."},{key:"B",text:"All the work needed to deliver a 'Done' increment."},{key:"C",text:"All development tasks."},{key:"D",text:"All the work that has been defined during Sprint Planning."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"At the end of a Sprint, the new Increment must be 'Done,' which means it must be in useable condition and meet the Definition of Done."},
  {id:55,question:"Which of the following is NOT an advantage of delivering projects using Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Scrum ensures an open work environment through information radiators such as Scrumboard."},{key:"B",text:"Scrum ensures faster resolution to issues through collaboration and colocation of team members."},{key:"C",text:"Scrum ensures a customer-oriented framework through collaborative approach and emphasis on business value."},{key:"D",text:"Scrum ensures better coordination among teams through an hierarchical organization structure which delegates authority for all the project aspects from higher level to the lower."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Scrum Teams are self-managing and cross-functional. Self-managing teams choose how best to accomplish their work."},
  {id:56,question:"What could be a reason for a Product Owner to delay the start of a new Sprint after the conclusion of the previous Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The QA team has not finished testing the previous Increment before declaring it ready to ship."},{key:"B",text:"The stakeholders were disappointed with the Increment produced in the previous Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"There is no acceptable reason. A new Sprint starts immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner needs additional time to identify the next initiatives."},{key:"E",text:"There's not enough work in the Product Backlog to work on in the upcoming Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"There is no acceptable reason. A new Sprint starts immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint."},
  {id:57,question:"Which of the following is required in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Retrospective."},{key:"B",text:"All Developers answering the 3 questions at the Daily Scrum."},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Burndown Chart."},{key:"D",text:"User Stories."},{key:"E",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Sprint Retrospective is required in Scrum."},
  {id:58,question:"How much time is allowed between the conclusion of the current Sprint and the start of the next Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Maximum of 1 day for Sprints that are time-boxed to 2 weeks."},{key:"B",text:"None. A new Sprint starts immediately following the conclusion of the previous Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Enough time for the last Increment to finish testing."},{key:"D",text:"Enough time for the Product Owner to prepare the Product Backlog for Sprint Planning."},{key:"E",text:"All of the above are allowed."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"None. A new Sprint starts immediately following the conclusion of the previous Sprint."},
  {id:59,question:"What are typical Product Owner activities during Sprint 0?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Creating a project plan based on the defined timeline."},{key:"B",text:"Ensuring there is enough work to do for at least 3 Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"Creating User Stories based on the requirements document."},{key:"D",text:"Allocating enough resources before starting Sprint 1."},{key:"E",text:"There is no such thing as Sprint 0."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"There is no special Sprints. All Sprints are structured to produce potentially shippable product Increments."},
  {id:60,question:"Which role in Scrum plays the role of a facilitator and ensures that the Scrum Team is provided with an environment conducive to maximizing opportunities of success?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The CEO"},{key:"B",text:"Scrum Team"},{key:"C",text:"Scrum Master"},{key:"D",text:"Product Owner"}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is a servant-leader for the Scrum Team and helps everyone find ways to maximize value."},
  {id:61,question:"Which of the following are time-boxed events in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"B",text:"Daily Scrum"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Review"},{key:"D",text:"Sprint Retrospective"},{key:"E",text:"All of the above"}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"All of these events are time-boxed in Scrum."},
  {id:62,question:"During the Sprint, the Developers realize they might not be able to finish all of the items in the Sprint Backlog. What should happen?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Add additional developers to the Scrum Team until they are able to meet their commitment."},{key:"B",text:"Continue Sprinting until the work is complete and redefine a new Sprint time-box based on the results of the current Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint length holds and the Developers continuously learn what is actually possible to do within the time-box."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"At the end of the Sprint time-box, Product Backlog items are either 'done' or 'not done.' This helps with transparency."},
  {id:63,question:"Which statement is correct about the length of the Sprints?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"All Sprints must be 1 month or less and it is optimal to have a consistent Sprint length."},{key:"B",text:"The Sprint length is dependent on the development effort forecasted (number of items selected) during Sprint Planning."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint length is calculated by aggregating the time required to design, code and test."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint Length is defined by the Scrum Master."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"All Sprints must be 1 month or less and it is optimal to have a consistent Sprint length."},
  {id:64,question:"Who can prematurely cancel a Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers"},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"C",text:"The Stakeholders"},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Only the Product Owner can determine when items being worked on is obsolete."},
  {id:65,question:"How should a Scrum Master respond if the Product Owner plans the first Sprint to only focus on setting up the infrastructure and architecture in order to work on business functionality in a subsequent Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Help the Product Owner understand the value of including business functionality into every Sprint, regardless of how small and explain to him/her that the best architecture and infrastructure emerge alongside the development of the functionality."},{key:"B",text:"Support the Product Owner's decision as he/she is accountable for maximizing the value of the work that the Scrum Team does."},{key:"C",text:"Explain that one Sprint may be too short to finish the architecture and he should pre-allocate subsequent Sprints just in case."},{key:"D",text:"Add at least one technical architect to the Scrum Team to ensure the architecture can be completed in the first Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Each Increment should include business value, no matter how small. The architectures, requirements, and designs will emerge during development."},
  {id:66,question:"In what ways do time-boxes help promote the Scrum principle of self-management?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Time-boxes help everyone focus on the same problem at the same time and encourage the people who are closest to the problem to create the best possible result in the time allotted, give the current context."},{key:"B",text:"Time-boxes protect the team from interruptions so that they can spend more time coding. It reduces the number of meetings and time spent in meetings."},{key:"C",text:"Time-boxes help the team commit to completing the scope of work within the time limit. It helps stakeholders define when the work needs to be released."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Time-boxes help everyone focus on the same problem and encourage people closest to the problem to create the best result."},
  {id:67,question:"The Scrum Team has just closed their first Sprint. When should their second Sprint begin?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When the Scrum Team declares they are ready."},{key:"B",text:"After Sprint Planning for the second Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"After User Acceptance Testing is completed on the previous Increment."},{key:"D",text:"Immediately."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Starting a new Sprint immediately after the conclusion of the previous Sprint reduces complexity through consistency."},
  {id:68,question:"Scrum Teams are cross-functional, with all of the skills as a team necessary to:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Deliver a potentially releasable product Increment."},{key:"B",text:"Do all of the development work, except for design as the Designer is external to the team."},{key:"C",text:"Complete the project on time, on budget and within the defined scope."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Scrum Teams are cross-functional, with all the skills as a team necessary to create value."},
  {id:69,question:"What is the Product Owner involvement in crafting the Sprint Goal?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner should come to the Sprint Planning with a clearly defined Sprint Goal."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner orders the Product Backlog according to business objectives. During the Sprint Planning, the Developers select items from the Product Backlog and work with the Product Owner to craft the Sprint Goal."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers are responsible for crafting the Sprint Goal based on the principle of self-management. The Product Owner must respect the Developers' decision."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner is responsible for crafting the Sprint Goal as he/she is accountable for maximizing the value of the work the Developers do."},{key:"E",text:"The stakeholders are responsible for crafting the Sprint Goal in collaboration with the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers select items and work with the Product Owner to craft the Sprint Goal."},
  {id:70,question:"What output from Sprint Planning provides guidance and overarching direction on why the Developers are building the Increment?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Sprint Burndown chart"},{key:"B",text:"The Sprint Goal"},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint Backlog"},{key:"D",text:"The task list"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Goal gives the Developers some flexibility regarding functionality implemented within the Sprint."},
  {id:71,question:"Which statement best describes the Sprint Backlog in an active Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Some Sprint Backlog items would be replaced with items from the Product Backlog, if the priorities change."},{key:"B",text:"The scope may be re-negotiated as more is learned."},{key:"C",text:"Some Sprint Backlog items would be moved back to the Product Backlog to be completed in future Sprints."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a living artifact and the scope may be clarified and re-negotiated as more is learned."},
  {id:72,question:"Which role in Scrum includes the customers, users, and sponsors, who frequently interact with the Scrum Team?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Vendor"},{key:"B",text:"Chief Product Owner"},{key:"C",text:"Scrum Guidance Body"},{key:"D",text:"Stakeholders"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"A Stakeholder is a person external to the Scrum Team with a specific interest in and knowledge of a product."},
  {id:73,question:"What is the correct time-box for the Sprint Planning event?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"4 hours for a monthly Sprint"},{key:"B",text:"8 hours for a monthly Sprint"},{key:"C",text:"After the Sprint Backlog is finalized"},{key:"D",text:"Every two weeks"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Sprint Planning is time-boxed to a maximum of 8 hours for a monthly Sprint. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter."},
  {id:74,question:"Before the end of Sprint Planning, the Developers realize that they have planned too much work for the upcoming Sprint. ie The planned Sprint Backlog is greater than their projected capacity. What could the Developers do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Work overtime to complete the commitment of work within the Sprint time-box."},{key:"B",text:"Redo the Sprint Planning in order to have a more accurate estimation."},{key:"C",text:"Work with the Product Owner to remove or change the selected Product Backlog items, or make sure he/she is aware, continue Sprinting, and monitor the progress."},{key:"D",text:"Delegate some of the work to another Scrum Team that has spare capacity."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is the team's forecasted plan. It is a living artifact that adapts during execution."},
  {id:75,question:"What topics would be discussed during Sprint Planning?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"How to maximize team member utilization."},{key:"B",text:"What to do and who will do which tasks."},{key:"C",text:"User feedback and the impact on the Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"How to improve the development process."},{key:"E",text:"Why is this Sprint valuable, what can be done in the Increment, and how to deliver the work."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"Sprint Planning addresses: Why is this Sprint valuable, what can be done, and how will the work be delivered."},
  {id:76,question:"When is the Sprint Goal crafted?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"During Sprint Planning."},{key:"B",text:"During Product Backlog Grooming."},{key:"C",text:"A Sprint Goal is optional."},{key:"D",text:"Before the Sprint Planning."},{key:"E",text:"During the implementation of the work."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Sprint Goal is an objective that will be met through the implementation of the Product Backlog."},
  {id:77,question:"What value does the Sprint Goal provide to the Developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Goals provide guidance just in case the Product Backlog items are not clear to a Developer."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers are more focused with a common yet specific goal."},{key:"C",text:"A Sprint Goal ensures the Developers complete all committed Sprint Backlog items."},{key:"D",text:"A Sprint Goal guarantees value is being produced."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Goal provides guidance and helps the Developers focus with a common yet specific goal."},
  {id:78,question:"Relationships between the Product Owner and the Developers has been tense for many Sprints. The Product Owner has lost trust and respect for the Developers as they consistently fail to achieve the Sprint Goal to her satisfaction by the end of each Sprint. The Developers blame the Product Owner for increasing scope each Sprint making the Sprint Goal unachievable. As a Scrum Master, what should you do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Talk to the Product Owner and tell them not to increase scope mid Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Speak to the line managers of the various Developers about their lack of productivity and ask them to take corrective action."},{key:"C",text:"Discuss the situation with the Scrum Team. Help them find improved ways to clarify and set a more realistic Sprint Goal."},{key:"D",text:"Take no action. Allow the Developers to self-manage to address the issue."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master helps everyone understand Scrum theory and helps the Scrum Team maximize value."},
  {id:79,question:"What are the minimum requirements to make the Sprint Backlog 'ready', during the Sprint Planning?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Enough so that the Developers can make a forecast for the Sprint and start the first few days."},{key:"B",text:"Enough to satisfy the Product Owner and stakeholders."},{key:"C",text:"Enough to keep all Developers busy."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint Backlog must be fully formulated to occupy the Developers for the entirety of the Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a living artifact that evolves as more is learned."},
  {id:80,question:"True or False: Using Scrum ensures that all resources on a project will be fully utilized in the most efficient way.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum focuses on the outcome rather than the process that produces the output. The focus is on delivering highest possible value."}
];
const psm1Test4Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"True or False: Agility is nothing more than the ability to rapidly respond to change.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Agility is the ability to quickly adjust and adapt to different situations. The Agile Manifesto defines the principles for agility in software development and Scrum is just a framework a team can use for incremental and iterative development so they can adapt quickly to changes. A team does not need to apply any specific framework in order to be agile as long as they have the ability to change when needed."},
  {id:2,question:"True or False: When something about Scrum becomes too challenging for the Product Owner, he/she can delegate some responsibilities to the Scrum Master.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"It is NOT acceptable for the Product Owner to attempt to proxy or outsource his/her duties to the Scrum Master. The Product Owner will work in concert with the Scrum Master to utilize Scrum correctly and advantageously and try to never been seen as an assistant or proxy PO. When something about Scrum frustrates a Product Owner, he/she should consult the Scrum Master for ways to implement the Scrum framework in a way that is effective."},
  {id:3,question:"True or False: \"Done\" can include meeting the Product Backlog item's acceptance criteria.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Product Backlog items often include test descriptions that will prove its completeness when \"Done\"."},
  {id:4,question:"True or False: Inviting stakeholders to the Sprint Retrospectives ensures that the discussions are aligned with the project's objectives.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Retrospective is for the Scrum Team to inspect their internal process and find ways to improve effectiveness."},
  {id:5,question:"True or False: Multiple Scrum Teams working on the same product will also pull work from the same Product Backlog.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"One product will have one Product Backlog regardless of how many teams are creating the product."},
  {id:6,question:"True or False: The output of Sprint Planning is the Sprint Backlog as well as a Sprint Goal.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The objective of Sprint Planning is to define a target and overarching direction for the Development Team and a plan for how to achieve the goal."},
  {id:7,question:"True or False: A Sprint is considered successful when an Increment is released to production.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The heart of Scrum is a Sprint, a time-box of one month or less during which a \"Done\", useable, and potentially releasable product Increment is created. The increment must be in useable condition regardless of whether the Product Owner decides to release it."},
  {id:8,question:"True or False: A high performing Scrum Team will have frequent Release Sprints.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"There is no special Sprints. All Sprints are structured to produce potentially shippable product Increments."},
  {id:9,question:"True or False: The Daily Scrum is owned and run by the Developers.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Anyone can \"attend\" the Daily Scrum but only the Developers are allowed to \"participate\". If the Product Owner or Scrum Master are actively working on items in the Sprint Backlog, they also participate as Developers. The Scrum Master can facilitate as requested or needed."},
  {id:10,question:"True or False: All work that the Developers plan to deliver in a Sprint originates from the Product Backlog.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"During Sprint Planning, the Scrum Team discusses is \"What can be done this Sprint.\" The items under discussion comes from the Product Backlog. The Product Backlog is the single source of truth that lists all features, functions, requirements, enhancements, and fixes that constitute the changes to be made to the product in future releases."},
  {id:11,question:"True or False: During Sprint Planning, the Developers must select enough Product Backlog items to satisfy the stakeholders.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers select the Product Backlog items in agreement with the Product Owner."},
  {id:12,question:"True or False: The Product Backlog must be fully formulated and complete before starting the first Sprint.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Backlog is a living artifact that evolves and changes as more is learned."},
  {id:13,question:"True or False: The Scrum Master manages the process within the Scrum Framework.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is a management role but for the process rather than for the people."},
  {id:14,question:"True or False: The Developers are responsible for conducting the Daily Scrum.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Anyone can \"attend\" the Daily Scrum but only the Developers are allowed to \"participate\". If the Product Owner or Scrum Master are actively working on items in the Sprint Backlog, they participate as Developers. The Scrum Master can facilitate as requested or needed."},
  {id:15,question:"True or False: Product Backlog items can include test descriptions that will prove its completeness when \"Done\".",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Product Backlog items often include test descriptions that will prove its completeness when \"Done\". The idea is for the item to describe the expected changes after an item is done."},
  {id:16,question:"True or False: During Sprint Planning, the Product Owner ensures the Developers commit to the Product Backlog items that were promised to the stakeholders.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Owner's responsibility is ordering the Product Backlog to maximize the flow of value."},
  {id:17,question:"True or False: A key concern when multiple Scrum Teams are working for the same Product Backlog is minimizing dependencies between teams.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Minimizing dependencies reduces complexity and enhances agility."},
  {id:18,question:"True or False: The Scrum Master is no longer needed when teams are able to self-manage.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Master continues to serve the team even when they become self-managing."},
  {id:19,question:"True or False: The Sprint Goal is defined before the Sprint Backlog is forecasted.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"During Sprint Planning, the Scrum Team will craft a Sprint Goal based on the forecast. In other words after deciding what can be done, the Scrum Team will formulate a Sprint Goal."},
  {id:20,question:"True or False: The Product Owner and Scrum Master should not be one of the Developers.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"It's OK for one person to have more than one role on a Scrum Team. If the Product Owner or Scrum Master are actively working on items in the Sprint Backlog, they participate as Developers."},
  {id:21,question:"Which two of the following are true about Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Scrum is a methodology for managing complex projects."},{key:"B",text:"Scrum is like traditional processes but with Sprints and related artifacts."},{key:"C",text:"Scrum is a framework for developing and maintaining complex products."},{key:"D",text:"Scrum is based on empirical process control theory."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Scrum is a framework, not a methodology or body of knowledge. Scrum is empirical, rather than theoretical. Scrum is more about product outcomes rather than project management."},
  {id:22,question:"A company has four Products. Which two of the following are acceptable ways of forming Scrum Teams?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There should be one Product Owner for each product."},{key:"B",text:"There can be a single Product Owner for all products."},{key:"C",text:"There should be a single Product Owner for all products."},{key:"D",text:"There can be one Product Owner for each product."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"When there's one product, there is one Product Owner, even if the product is large. However, when there are multiple products, there can be a full-time Product Owner for each product or one Product Owner for all products sharing his/her time between products."},
  {id:23,question:"Which statements are correct about Product Backlog refinement?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It should be done right before the Sprint Planning."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master should facilitate it."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Team decides when it occurs and how much time is needed."},{key:"D",text:"Multiple teams may participate."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"If multiple teams are working on the project, they will participate in the refinement as well. Refinement can take any amount of time as long as it is helpful and does not distract from the current goals."},
  {id:24,question:"Which of the following are optional in Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Increment."},{key:"B",text:"Definition of Done."},{key:"C",text:"Cumulative flows."},{key:"D",text:"Burn-down charts."},{key:"E",text:"Sprint Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Various processes, techniques and methods can be employed within the framework. Various practices exist to forecast progress, like burn-downs, burn-ups, or cumulative flows. While proven useful, these do not replace the importance of empiricism."},
  {id:25,question:"Which of the following describes the Definition of Done?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Helps increase velocity."},{key:"B",text:"Increases transparency."},{key:"C",text:"Ensures everything is documented."},{key:"D",text:"Helps ensure the Increment is releasable."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Definition of Done increases transparency because everyone knows what it means by \"Done\". It includes everything required for creating something usable by the end users (potentially releasable)."},
  {id:26,question:"When should the Product Backlog items be refined?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Before the Sprint in which the item will be worked on."},{key:"B",text:"The business analysts do it before handing them off to the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"During the Sprint that the items are being worked on."},{key:"D",text:"In Sprint 0."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Product Backlog refinement is an ongoing activity. As the Developers work during the Sprint, they keep the Sprint Goal in mind and may refine items as needed."},
  {id:27,question:"When can the items in the Product Backlog be refined?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"In one or two preceding Sprints."},{key:"B",text:"In the time between the end of the previous Sprint and before the start of the next."},{key:"C",text:"During the Sprint, if they have not been refined in the previous Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"In Sprint 0."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Product Backlog refinement is a continuous activity. It's preferred to have items refined before Sprint Planning; however, it's OK to need more refinement during development."},
  {id:28,question:"Which 4 activities are the Developers responsible for?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sizing Product Backlog items."},{key:"B",text:"Breaking down epics into small user stories."},{key:"C",text:"Designing architecture and infrastructure."},{key:"D",text:"Making technical decisions."},{key:"E",text:"Volunteering for tasks."},{key:"F",text:"Writing user stories."},{key:"G",text:"Prioritizing the Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["A","C","D","E"],explanation:"Designing the software is part of development. They are self-managed and make technical decisions and volunteer for tasks. Sizing items is the responsibility of the developers because they are the people who will be developing and delivering the item."},
  {id:29,question:"What does it mean to say a Product Backlog item is \"Done\"?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The item is ready for functional testing by the Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"The item creates a software that is potentially usable by the end user."},{key:"C",text:"No work left based on the Definition of Done."},{key:"D",text:"The item can be a part of a potentially releasable piece of software."},{key:"E",text:"All tasks identified for the item are done."},{key:"F",text:"The item is ready for user acceptance testing."},{key:"G",text:"The item has all the quality requirements defined by the Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D"],explanation:"Items are \"Done\" when they are complete based on the definition of \"Done\". In that case, they would have the potential of creating a releasable/shippable Increment that is usable by the end user."},
  {id:30,question:"What are the benefits of having tests in the Definition of Done?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Increments can be more complete."},{key:"B",text:"It can help Increments become potentially shippable."},{key:"C",text:"Increased transparency of the Increments."},{key:"D",text:"Reporting would be easier for the project manager."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C"],explanation:"Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified. The Definition of Done creates transparency by providing everyone a shared understanding of what work was completed."},
  {id:31,question:"Which of the following is NOT mandatory for applying Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Velocity."},{key:"B",text:"Having potentially releasable Increments."},{key:"C",text:"Release planning."},{key:"D",text:"Measuring Sprint progress."},{key:"E",text:"A Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Having a release plan is usually required but it's not part of the framework. Velocity calculation is also helpful but is not part of the framework. The Scrum framework is purposefully incomplete, only defining the parts required to implement Scrum theory."},
  {id:32,question:"Who supports the Scrum Master in removing impediments?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The customer."},{key:"B",text:"The senior management."},{key:"C",text:"The Director of Engineering."},{key:"D",text:"Anyone on the Scrum Team."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"The Developers can help the Scrum Master. Some impediments are rooted in external causes and that's why the Scrum Master might need to have the management's support. The Product Owner can also support the Scrum Master by managing stakeholder expectations."},
  {id:33,question:"An organization has decided to change from their traditional process to using Scrum. What will likely occur if they only replace their current terminology with Scrum terminology?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It can make management feel less anxious about the change."},{key:"B",text:"Changes might not be understood and the benefits will be lost."},{key:"C",text:"They will be able to adopt Scrum faster this way."},{key:"D",text:"The change might not be obvious and very little change will actually occur."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","D"],explanation:"Each element of the framework serves a specific purpose. Changing the core design or ideas of Scrum, leaving out elements, or not following the rules of Scrum, covers up problems and limits the benefits of Scrum."},
  {id:34,question:"Which two statements best describe technical debt?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When measured properly, the Product Owner can estimate when the product is ready for release."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers should not start working on a new item unless they remove all existing technical debt."},{key:"C",text:"It creates uncertainty, because when more code is added, more problems will occur and the development slows down."},{key:"D",text:"It creates false assumptions about the current state of the system; e.g. it might not be really releasable."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Technical debt is the consequence of poor system design. If it keeps increasing, development will become harder and slow down the progress and create problems for future releases."},
  {id:35,question:"A company has three separate Products. What are the two acceptable ways of forming the Scrum Teams?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There can be one Product Owner for each product."},{key:"B",text:"There must be one Product Owner for each product."},{key:"C",text:"There can be a single Product Owner for all products."},{key:"D",text:"There must be a single Product Owner for all products."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"When there are multiple Products, there are two options: Have a Product Owner for each of them or have one Product Owner for all of them."},
  {id:36,question:"Which two of the following are the most important considerations when forming multiple Scrum Teams?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Having proper size in each team."},{key:"B",text:"Having an effective mixture of skills in each team to avoid dependencies."},{key:"C",text:"Having a mixture of senior and junior developers in each team."},{key:"D",text:"Having enough skills for a single technical layer designated to the each team."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Scrum Teams are cross-functional, meaning the members have all the skills necessary to create value each Sprint. It is small enough to remain nimble and large enough to complete significant work."},
  {id:37,question:"How much refinement should be done to items at the top of the Product Backlog?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"All the tasks required for completing it have been identified."},{key:"B",text:"Enough that it can be \"Done\" within the time-box of a Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"In a way that it's clear enough for the Developers to understand."},{key:"D",text:"Enough to know which Developer will be assigned to it."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Items at the top of the Product Backlog should be small enough to fit in one Sprint. They should also be clear and detailed enough to be understood."},
  {id:38,question:"Which statements are correct about a Sprint Backlog item that was not finished by the end of the Sprint?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It will be moved back to the Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"It won't be included in the Increment at the Sprint Review."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint will be extended until the item is done."},{key:"D",text:"It will be demonstrated to the stakeholders and released if approved."},{key:"E",text:"It will be completed in the next Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Work cannot be considered part of an Increment unless it meets the Definition of Done. When something is not 'done', it will be moved back to the Product Backlog."},
  {id:39,question:"Which of the following are ways for the stakeholders to interact with the Developers?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Attending the Sprint Retrospective."},{key:"B",text:"Via the Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"Participating at the Sprint Review."},{key:"D",text:"Through the Scrum Master."},{key:"E",text:"Giving feedback at the Daily Scrums."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"The Scrum Master helps stakeholders understand which interactions are helpful and which are not. Stakeholders interact with the Scrum Team if it can add value and helps the team towards the goals."},
  {id:40,question:"Who is in the Scrum Team?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers."},{key:"C",text:"A Project Manager."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"E",text:"Team leader(s)."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","D"],explanation:"The Scrum Team consists of a Product Owner, the Developers, and a Scrum Master."},
  {id:41,question:"Which of the following is LEAST accurate about the first Sprint?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A complete Product Backlog is created."},{key:"B",text:"A piece of working software is created."},{key:"C",text:"A releasable Increment is delivered."},{key:"D",text:"The complete system architecture is designed."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"All Sprints have the same purpose of delivering value by meeting a Sprint Goal through the delivery of a potentially releasable Increment."},
  {id:42,question:"Which statements are most accurate about the Sprint Retrospective?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It occurs immediately before the Sprint Review."},{key:"B",text:"It's an opportunity for inspection and adaptation."},{key:"C",text:"It's time-boxed to three hours for a one-month Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"It's the only time improvements are planned for the Scrum Team."},{key:"E",text:"The Product Owner doesn't have to attend the event."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"The Sprint Retrospective concludes the Sprint and helps the Scrum Team identify helpful changes to improve effectiveness. It is time-boxed to a maximum of three hours for a one-month Sprint."},
  {id:43,question:"Which three of the following are the Developers accountable for?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Create a plan for the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Sizing Product Backlog items."},{key:"C",text:"Pulling Product Backlog items for the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Ensuring the Product Backlog is ordered properly."},{key:"E",text:"Reporting progress to the stakeholders."},{key:"F",text:"Creating and adding User Stories to the Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C"],explanation:"Because the Developers are the ones doing the work, they would be the best ones to decide on how to make the work done, estimating how much effort is needed, and how much work they can possibly do."},
  {id:44,question:"Product Backlog refinement is the act of ... to the items in the Product Backlog.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"adding description, size and order"},{key:"B",text:"including story points"},{key:"C",text:"assigning ownership"},{key:"D",text:"assigning Sprint numbers"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Product Backlog refinement is the act of breaking down and further defining Product Backlog items into smaller more precise items. This is an ongoing activity by the Scrum Team."},
  {id:45,question:"When's a new Increment of working software must be available?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Every 3 Sprints"},{key:"B",text:"When the Product Owner asks for it"},{key:"C",text:"At the end of each Sprint"},{key:"D",text:"Before each planned release"},{key:"E",text:"Whenever the user acceptance testing is done"}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"An Increment of \"Done\" working software, which is potentially releasable, is produced at the end of each Sprint."},
  {id:46,question:"Who should know the most about the overall project performance?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master"},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Team"},{key:"D",text:"The project manager"},{key:"E",text:"The Developers"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for the flow of value therefore he/she will be the one to know the most about the overall performance of the project."},
  {id:47,question:"How complete should the Sprint Backlog be at the end of the Sprint Planning meeting?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Complete enough to show work for the first few days of the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"It depends on the preference of the Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint Backlog must be fully devised by the end of the Sprint Planning."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Sometimes, not all tasks are able to be identified in the Sprint Planning. There should be enough to start. In a complex environment, it's difficult to know everything upfront."},
  {id:48,question:"Which of the following is responsible for formulating the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers create the Definition of Done because they are the ones doing the work."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master creates the Definition of Done because he/she ensures transparency."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Team creates a Definition of Done appropriate for the product."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner creates the Definition of Done because he/she is responsible for maximizing product value."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"If the Definition of Done is not an organizational standard, the Scrum Team must create a Definition of Done appropriate for the product."},
  {id:49,question:"What happens if the entire Product Backlog is not fully clear before the Sprint Planning?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Nothing; the Sprint would be planned anyway."},{key:"B",text:"The Sprint would be cancelled, and will start as soon as enough items at the top of the Product Backlog are ready."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint Planning would be delayed, until enough refinement is done to the items at the top of the Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint Planning would be extended, to have the items refined before adding them to the Sprint Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"We prefer to have \"ready\" items at the top of the Product Backlog before Sprint Planning. However, nothing stops our flow of Sprints. The \"unready\" items would be selected and refined during the Sprint."},
  {id:50,question:"Which Scrum event is opportune for discussing process improvements?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Sprint Retrospective."},{key:"B",text:"The Daily Scrum."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint Planning."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint Review."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Scrum provides a process which should be continuously improved by way of the Sprint Retrospectives."},
  {id:51,question:"The number of developers has increased from 7 to 14. The Developers are complaining that there are too many people at the Daily Scrum and that it is impossible to keep it within 15 minutes. As a Scrum Master, what would be the most appropriate response?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Increase the time-box of Daily Scrums to 30 minutes."},{key:"B",text:"Help the team understand the benefits of smaller team sizes and let them self-organize into separate Scrum Teams."},{key:"C",text:"Take ownership of the Daily Scrum to ensure it ends within 15 minutes."},{key:"D",text:"End the Daily Scrums at 15 minutes and ensure as many developers contribute as possible within the time-box."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Team is small enough to remain nimble and large enough to complete significant work, typically 10 or fewer people. If Scrum Teams become too large, they should consider reorganizing into multiple cohesive Scrum Teams."},
  {id:52,question:"A Product Owner, with an extensive Product Backlog, wants to add detailed acceptance criteria for each item before starting development. What's the best response from the Scrum Master?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It's a good idea, as long as the acceptance criteria are not too detailed."},{key:"B",text:"It's a good idea, as long as there's a similar set of acceptance criteria for all items."},{key:"C",text:"This is not necessary as items can be discussed and refined throughout the development of the product."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Scrum employs an iterative, incremental approach to optimize predictability and to control risk. Lean thinking reduces waste and focuses on the essentials."},
  {id:53,question:"When do developers prepare the tools and infrastructure for the development?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Throughout the project."},{key:"B",text:"Before the first Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"In Sprint zero."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"It is difficult to prepare all of the infrastructure and tools upfront because needs of a product in a complex environment is not fully known. The infrastructure and tools are prepared throughout the development effort."},
  {id:54,question:"Which of the following is not improved by using time-boxed Sprints?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Technical debt."},{key:"B",text:"Prioritization of all aspects of work."},{key:"C",text:"Establishing work-in-progress limit."},{key:"D",text:"Demonstrating incremental progress."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Technical debt is any shortcoming in the solution. Refactoring is a common way of reducing technical debt. Time-boxing, however, doesn't help with technical debt."},
  {id:55,question:"What happens to incomplete Product Backlog items when the Sprint time-box ends?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"They would be moved back to the Product Backlog with the original estimation."},{key:"B",text:"They would be moved to the next Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"They would be re-estimated and moved back to the Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"The Developers continue working on the items and the Sprint is extended until all items are 'done'."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The items should be re-estimated because they have been worked on and the effort may have changed. Items not done are moved back to the Product Backlog for the Product Owner to reorder."},
  {id:56,question:"If there are 21 developers available for a Scrum project, how should they be divided into teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master will decide."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner will decide."},{key:"C",text:"The resource management department decides."},{key:"D",text:"Have the developers decide."},{key:"E",text:"They should be divided equally into 3 Scrum Teams."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Scrum Teams are cross-functional with all necessary skills. Because the developers will be executing the work, it is best that they decide how to balance their skills and competencies across teams."},
  {id:57,question:"Which of the following is the single source of requirements for all changes planned to be made to the product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Increment."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint Retrospective."},{key:"E",text:"The Sprint Review."},{key:"F",text:"The Business Model Canvas."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Everything we might want to apply to the product, including changes, are reflected in the Product Backlog. This reduces complexity and increases transparency."},
  {id:58,question:"When is a Sprint Backlog item considered complete?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When all of its sub-tasks are complete."},{key:"B",text:"When the Sprint is over."},{key:"C",text:"When the item meets the Definition of Done."},{key:"D",text:"When the user acceptance tests are done."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"When the item is complete based on the Definition of Done, it creates an Increment of working software which is potentially releasable."},
  {id:59,question:"Who's responsible for Gantt Charts in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"No one."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers."},{key:"D",text:"The project manager."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Scrum does not prescribe specific processes, techniques and methods. Various practices exist to forecast progress, but these do not replace the importance of empiricism."},
  {id:60,question:"Who ensures that the Developers are working on the most important tasks during the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"B",text:"The project manager."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers themselves."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Because the Developers are the ones doing the work they are the best ones to decide who does what, when, and how in order to meet the Sprint Goal."},
  {id:61,question:"If the customer asks a developer to add a new feature to the current Sprint, how should the developer respond?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask the Product Owner to work with the customer."},{key:"B",text:"Add the item to the bottom of the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Reject the request."},{key:"D",text:"Add the item to the Product Backlog."},{key:"E",text:"Swap the item with one of the items in the Sprint Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner is accountable for maximizing the value of the product. The entire organization must respect the Product Owner's decisions."},
  {id:62,question:"The Product Owner has doubts about the quality of the Definition of Done. What should he/she do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Adjust the Definition of Done immediately."},{key:"B",text:"Adjust the Definition of Done after the end of the Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Ask the QA department to investigate the issue."},{key:"D",text:"Bring it up at upcoming Sprint Retrospective."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Scrum Team is responsible for the Definition of Done rather than the Product Owner alone. If the Product Owner doubts the quality, he/she can discuss it with the team at the next Sprint Retrospective."},
  {id:63,question:"Who is responsible for monitoring the work in the Sprint Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Team"},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master"},{key:"C",text:"The Developers"},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner"}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a plan by and for the Developers. It is a highly visible, real-time picture of the work that the Developers plan to accomplish during the Sprint."},
  {id:64,question:"Which statement best describes the Sprint Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Each of its items has been estimated in story points."},{key:"B",text:"It's the Developers' plan for the Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"It's defined by the Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"Each item is assigned ownership to a developer."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is created during Sprint Planning and includes items selected from the Product Backlog (pulled by the Developers) and tasks created by decomposing the items."},
  {id:65,question:"How long does the Sprint Planning take in a project with three-week Sprints?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Maximum 6 hours."},{key:"B",text:"Maximum 3 hours."},{key:"C",text:"No more than 8 hours for a one-month Sprint but typically shorter for shorter Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"Maximum 4 hours."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Sprint Planning is 8 hours for a one-month Sprint and usually shorter for shorter Sprints. It is up to the Scrum Team to decide on optimal time-boxes as long as they do not exceed the maximum limit."},
  {id:66,question:"Which statement is correct about Product Backlog refinement?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It usually consumes no more than 20% of the capacity of the Scrum Team."},{key:"B",text:"It is an ongoing activity of the Scrum Team and is refined as needed."},{key:"C",text:"It must not consume more than 10% of the capacity of the Development Team."},{key:"D",text:"It usually consumes no more than 10% of the capacity of the Scrum Team."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Product Backlog refinement is an ongoing activity to add details. It is up to the Scrum Team decide when it is needed and how much time is needed within the boundaries of Scrum."},
  {id:67,question:"Which Scrum artifact will have ordered items?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Sprint Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"None."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"The Increment."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Product Backlog consists of items that have description, order, and size."},
  {id:68,question:"When is a Sprint cancelled?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When a key developer cannot work for awhile."},{key:"B",text:"When the Sprint Goal doesn't make sense anymore."},{key:"C",text:"When all Sprint Backlog items cannot be finished within the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"When the Definition of Done is met."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Sprints can be cancelled by the Product Owner when it doesn't make sense to continue pursuing the Sprint Goal rendering the work obsolete."},
  {id:69,question:"Which is NOT a main responsibility of the Developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Volunteering for tasks."},{key:"B",text:"Creating tasks."},{key:"C",text:"Measuring and understanding progress towards the Sprint Goal."},{key:"D",text:"Breaking down the items in the Product Backlog into smaller items"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for managing the Product Backlog and its content. This can include breaking down large Product Backlog items. The Developers can help if needed."},
  {id:70,question:"Which of the following accountabilities is NOT described in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Accountabilities of a Product Manager."},{key:"B",text:"Accountabilities of a Scrum Master."},{key:"C",text:"Accountabilities of the Developers."},{key:"D",text:"Accountabilities of a Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Scrum defines three specific accountabilities within the Scrum Team: the Developers, the Product Owner, and the Scrum Master."},
  {id:71,question:"Which statement best describes the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Everything that would make the output potentially releasable"},{key:"B",text:"Anything that the Product Owner finds necessary"},{key:"C",text:"Passing the QA and having all the required documents"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Definition of Done helps us understand when everything is done on a Product Backlog item and is part of the Increment."},
  {id:72,question:"Which of the following is a valid service from the Scrum Master to the Product Owner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Helping the Product Owner find techniques for managing the Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Act as a proxy when the Product Owner is not available to the team."},{key:"C",text:"Helping the Product Owner order the Product Backlog items in order to maximize value."},{key:"D",text:"Act as the middleman between the Product Owner and the Developers, as requested or required."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master serves the Product Owner by helping find techniques for effective Product Goal definition and Product Backlog management. These are mainly focused on coaching/training."},
  {id:73,question:"Which role is the equivalent of project manager in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"B",text:"The team leader(s)"},{key:"C",text:"None"},{key:"D",text:"The Developers"},{key:"E",text:"The Scrum Master"}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The project management activities are distributed across the Scrum Team."},
  {id:74,question:"When does inspection occur?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Whenever the Product Owner finds it necessary."},{key:"B",text:"Frequently, but not so often that gets in the way of work."},{key:"C",text:"All the time."},{key:"D",text:"At the Sprint Review."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"All Scrum events are opportunities for inspection and adaptation. Inspection makes adaptation possible. However, like anything else in Agile, we just like to have \"enough\" of it."},
  {id:75,question:"Which artifact contains the plan for realizing the Sprint Goal?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"None, Scrum does not use plans."},{key:"B",text:"The Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"The Gantt Chart."},{key:"E",text:"The requirements document."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is the set of items selected from the Product Backlog and a number of tasks required for developing them and realizing the Sprint Goal."},
  {id:76,question:"What happens to the Product Backlog when the end users' environment and needs change in the middle of the project?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There's no effect. If the changes are extreme, the project should be cancelled and a new one started with a new Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"It evolves to reflect the changes."},{key:"C",text:"It will be archived, and a new Product Backlog would replace it."},{key:"D",text:"The requirement specification document should change accordingly, followed by the Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Product Backlog is a dynamic concept that is never made static. It always changes to reflect feedback from the customer, end users, market and their environment."},
  {id:77,question:"Which of the following is the LEAST productive way for the Scrum Master to improve the Developers' communications with the Product Owner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Act as a go-between for them."},{key:"B",text:"Teach them how to effectively communicate."},{key:"C",text:"Monitor their communication performance."},{key:"D",text:"Suggest effective communication tools and techniques to the Scrum Team."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Acting as a go-between weakens the team and blocks self-management. The Scrum Master is supposed to teach and coach."},
  {id:78,question:"When does integrating a solution occur?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Before releasing the Increment."},{key:"B",text:"At the end of the Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"At anytime during the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"At the end of the project."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Integration is part of the development of each item and a step towards making work done. Agile approaches benefit from continuous integration to make the output potentially releasable."},
  {id:79,question:"Who is responsible for managing the Developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Team leader"},{key:"B",text:"Developers"},{key:"C",text:"Product Owner"},{key:"D",text:"Scrum Master"},{key:"E",text:"Scrum Team"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The ones doing the work will self-manage and internally decide who does what, when, and how."},
  {id:80,question:"The Sprint Backlog makes visible all of the work the ... identifies as necessary to meet the Sprint Goal.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Developers"},{key:"B",text:"Scrum Team"},{key:"C",text:"Product Owner"},{key:"D",text:"Scrum Master"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"This is up to the Developers to identify how to accomplish the goal. These are the tasks the Developers believe are needed to make the work items done."}
];
const psm1Test5Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Who monitors the remaining work in the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"The Project Manager."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for measuring the progress of the project and tracking the remaining work in the Product Backlog. The Developers are responsible for measuring the progress of the Sprint and tracking the remaining work in the Sprint Backlog."},
  
  {id:2,question:"Which item is NOT an attribute of a Product Backlog Item?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Size"},{key:"B",text:"Description"},{key:"C",text:"Order"},{key:"D",text:"Owner"}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Each Product Backlog Item has a description, a business value used for ordering and an estimated size for the amount of effort."},
  
  {id:3,question:"What practice works best to synchronize multiple teams working on the same product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Having a single Daily Scrum for all teams."},{key:"B",text:"Having multiple Sprint Planning sessions for each Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Integrating a weekly status report across all teams."},{key:"D",text:"Helping the teams decide what works best."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Scrum Framework is flexible enough to support multiple teams working on the same product without needing to modify or change the structure or components as defined in the Scrum Guide. If multiple teams are working on the same product, they can decide how best to synchronize within the boundaries of Scrum and still be effective."},
  
  {id:4,question:"What type of process control is Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Agile"},{key:"B",text:"Adaptive"},{key:"C",text:"Empirical"},{key:"D",text:"Modern"}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Scrum is empirical; based on the real-world experiences. It asserts that knowledge comes from experience and making decisions based on what is known. In order to do so, Scrum employs an iterative, incremental approach to optimize predictability and control risk."},
  
  {id:5,question:"What's the vertical axis in a typical burn-down chart?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The amount of work or remaining work."},{key:"B",text:"The progress."},{key:"C",text:"The technical debt."},{key:"D",text:"The performance of the team."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The horizontal axis is time, the vertical axis is the remaining amount of work and the trend line shows the forecasted finish date if the Product Backlog and the team capacity stay the same."},
  
  {id:6,question:"Who assigns tasks to the Developers?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"C",text:"The project manager."},{key:"D",text:"The Developers themselves."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Developers take responsibility for the tasks themselves and the they ensure that the work is done properly. Remember that they are self-managing. When items are 'Done', the Product Owner can check the items but this is focused on the item rather than individuals; all developers are accountable for meeting the Sprint Goal and creating a shippable Increment."},
  
  {id:7,question:"Only the Product Owner has the authority to cancel a Sprint. However, the Developers is trying to convince the Product Owner that the Sprint should be cancelled. What's the most appropriate response from the Scrum Master?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It is OK."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master should stop this, because the Developers do not have the authority to influence Sprint cancellation."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master should encourage the Product Owner to discuss it with the stakeholders first."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master should make the final decision."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Only the Product Owner can cancel a Sprint and the final decision belongs to him/her. However, this decision can be influenced by the stakeholders, customers, Developers or Scrum Master."},
  
  {id:8,question:"How can a Scrum Master help multiple teams keep their output aligned in a single product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Teach the Product Owner to collaborate with lead developers on aligning the effort."},{key:"B",text:"Teach them that it's their responsibility to work with the other teams to align their outputs and integrated their work into a single Increment."},{key:"C",text:"Collect Sprint Backlog tasks of all teams, make them consistent, and return them to team to work on."},{key:"D",text:"Visit each Daily Scrum and ensure that activities are aligned across all teams."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Because the Developers are the ones doing the work, they are the best ones to decide how to integrate their work to deliver a shippable Increment."},
  
  {id:9,question:"What is the benefit of having the Daily Scrum held at the same time and same place each day?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Because it makes it easier to reserve the space."},{key:"B",text:"Because the Product Owner may require it."},{key:"C",text:"To reduce complexity and increase simplicity."},{key:"D",text:"To make it easier for the Scrum Master to manage performance."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"It is wasteful to spend effort everyday with logistics of the Daily Scrum when the event itself is only 15 minutes. Having the event at the same time and place everyday takes less planning, involves less thinking and provides a consistent feedback loop."},
  
  {id:10,question:"How should the Scrum Team deal with non-functional requirements?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Incorporate them into every Increment."},{key:"B",text:"Incorporate them immediately prior to releasing."},{key:"C",text:"Incorporate them in the hardening Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Incorporate them in the integration Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Non-functional requirements are usually part of the Definition of Done and should be considered for every Product Backlog item thus every Increment. Sometimes, non-functional requirements will address a very particular part of the software can be added as separate items in the Product Backlog. All Sprints have the same objective. There's no Sprint zero, hardening Sprint, release Sprint, integration Sprint, etc."},
  
  {id:11,question:"Which of the following is the most appropriate action from the Scrum Master in response to a Product Owner who has problems ordering the Product Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask the Developers to help the Product Owner understand the dependencies among items to be used in ordering the items."},{key:"B",text:"Help the Product Owner find techniques for ordering the items."},{key:"C",text:"Extend the Sprint so that the Product Owner has more time ordering items."},{key:"D",text:"Delegate the responsibility of ordering Product Backlog items to the Business Analyst."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Master serves the Product Owner in several ways, including helping find techniques for effective Product Backlog management."},
  
  {id:12,question:"When should Increments be released?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"When the Increment is free of defects."},{key:"B",text:"When it makes sense."},{key:"C",text:"After each Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"When the Increment is shippable."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Work cannot be considered part of an Increment unless it meets the Definition of Done. All Increments would be in a potentially releasable (shippable) state but it is not mandated when they are released. Releasing will depend on the context and at discretion of the Product Owner."},
  
  {id:13,question:"An Increment will consist of which of the following?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"New features in a usable state that are additive to those delivered in the previous Sprints."},{key:"B",text:"A user interface layout design for the software."},{key:"C",text:"A UML diagram that describes the functionalities of future Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"A decomposition of Product Backlog items into tasks that will be used in the future Sprints."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"An Increment is a concrete stepping stone toward the Product Goal. Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. In order to provide value, the Increment must be usable."},
  
  {id:14,question:"Which of the following is a prerequisite before Sprint Planning can begin?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Having the Product Backlog items clearly described and assigned to developers."},{key:"B",text:"Having the items at the top of the Product Backlog small enough to fit in one Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Having the full Product requirements detailed, approved, and reflected in the Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"None."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"We prefer to have 'ready' items at the top of the Product Backlog before Sprint Planning, which is done through Product Backlog refinement. However, nothing stops the flow of Sprints. For example, we do not delay the Sprint because the items are not ready. In such cases, the 'unready' items would be selected for the Sprint and refined during the Sprint. 'Ready' items are defined as items that are clear, understood, and small enough to fit into one Sprint."},
  
  {id:15,question:"Which of the following best describes the first Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It is reserved for creating the project plan."},{key:"B",text:"It is for defining the product vision."},{key:"C",text:"It is dedicated to architecture and infrastructure."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Team creates and delivers a shippable piece of functionality."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"There's no difference between the first Sprint and the next ones. The main purpose of each Sprint is to meet the Sprint Goal through the delivery of a shippable Increment."},
  
  {id:16,question:"Which of the following refers to the average amount of work done per Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Capacity"},{key:"B",text:"Velocity"},{key:"C",text:"Burn-down rate"},{key:"D",text:"Performance"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Velocity is the amount of work (ie 'points' or 'story points') done per Sprint. For example, 200 story points per Sprint."},
  
  {id:17,question:"Which statement is LEAST accurate about the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It's created by the Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"There can be more than one Definition of Done when multiple teams are working on the same product."},{key:"C",text:"It may be defined by the development organization."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Definition of Done can be prepared in the development organization and used in all projects as a minimum. If additional content is required for the definition or it's not prepared in the organization level, the Scrum Team would be responsible for preparing it. The Definition of Done can evolve during the project as more is learned. It's also dependent on the project and its environment. Multiple teams can share a single Definition of Done OR have different Definitions of Done, as long as they are compatible and capable of creating an integrated Increment at the end of the Sprint."},
  
  {id:18,question:"Who owns the Sprint Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Team."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Developers own the Sprint Backlog and the Product Owner owns the Product Backlog."},
  
  {id:19,question:"Who updates the work remaining in the Sprint Backlog during the Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Team."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible for measuring the progress of the overall product and managing the work in the Product Backlog. The Developers are responsible for measuring the progress of the Sprint and tracking the remaining work in the Sprint Backlog."},
  
  {id:20,question:"All of the following are inputs to the Sprint Planning meeting, EXCEPT:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Sprint Goal."},{key:"B",text:"The Previous Increment."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"Velocity."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Sprint Goal is created during the Sprint Planning. The rest are the existing information we use as an input for planning the Sprint."},
  
  {id:21,question:"If it's not possible to complete the Sprint Backlog, who would try to resolve it?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Scrum Master."},{key:"C",text:"The Developers and the Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"E",text:"The Project Manager."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"It's OK of the Sprint Backlog is not complete until the end of the Sprint. However, Scrum Teams should try to meet the Sprint Goal. When the Developers find out they are unable to complete the Sprint Backlog items they will inform the Product Owner for help and the two roles together will adjust the work (tasks), or reorder the times to maximize the chance of meeting the Sprint Backlog."},
  
  {id:22,question:"Teams A and B work on two different projects. Team A has 8 members, and a velocity of 600. Team B has 6 members, and a velocity of 500. Which team has a higher performance?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Team B."},{key:"B",text:"Team A."},{key:"C",text:"It depends."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The provided information is not enough. Velocity is defined locally and it's not beneficial to compare one team's velocity with the other."},
  
  {id:23,question:"Which of the following is least likely to be used by a Scrum Team?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Large screen, planning poker cards."},{key:"B",text:"Wiki, online forum."},{key:"C",text:"WBS, Gantt Chart."},{key:"D",text:"Digital camera, task board."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"WBS and Gantt Charts are used in traditional projects because they are focused on an upfront understanding of the scope of the project. The scope of Agile projects evolve during the project."},
  
  {id:24,question:"What is velocity?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Average lines of code created per Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Average amount of work done per Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Average man-hours spent per Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Average number of items done per Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Velocity is the amount of work (sometimes called 'points' or 'story points') done per Sprint. For example, 200 story points per Sprint."},
  
  {id:25,question:"A baselined Product Backlog is called:",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Release plan."},{key:"B",text:"Product Backlog is not baselined in Scrum."},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"Product vision."},{key:"E",text:"'Ready' Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"'Baselining' is a term used in traditional environments for referring to a finalized upfront plan that would be followed in the future and used for evaluating the actual performance. There's no upfront planning and no baselines in Scrum."},
  
  {id:26,question:"A four-hour Sprint Planning is the time-box for Sprints that are ... long.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Four weeks."},{key:"B",text:"Three weeks."},{key:"C",text:"One week."},{key:"D",text:"Two weeks."},{key:"E",text:"Any of the above."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"Sprint Planning is time-boxed to a maximum of eight hours for a one-month Sprint. Besides the Daily Scrum, Scrum does not prescribe specific time-boxes for events for Sprints less than one-month. For shorter Sprints, the event is usually shorter. The keyword here is usually. Shorter Sprints can take up to 8 hours to plan but if a large proportion of the Sprint time-box is spent in planning then the team might be having issues and need to evaluate how the planning is done."},
  
  {id:27,question:"Which of the following does NOT apply to/suit Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Fixed requirements."},{key:"B",text:"Based on empirical process control."},{key:"C",text:"Simple and lightweight."},{key:"D",text:"Framework used to address complex products."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Agility is all about depending on adaptation, instead of predictive (static, upfront) planning."},
  
  {id:28,question:"What's the maximum duration of Sprint Planning when the Product Backlog is not clear?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"As much as needed"},{key:"B",text:"8 hours"},{key:"C",text:"6 hours"},{key:"D",text:"12 hours"},{key:"E",text:"4 hours"},{key:"F",text:"2 hours"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The maximum duration of Sprint Planning for a one month Sprint (which is the longest allowed Sprint) is 8 hours. This is not dependent on any other factor such as the state of the Product Backlog."},
  
  {id:29,question:"The Product Owner is using burn-up charts instead of burn-down charts. What would be your response as the Scrum Master?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There's nothing wrong with it."},{key:"B",text:"Burn-up charts are used in traditional methods, and should be replaced by burn-down charts."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Burn-down charts are very common for tracking and representing progress, but they are not mandatory and the Product Owner can use other tools/techniques as well."},
  
  {id:30,question:"Which of the following events is the most important opportunity for capturing lessons learned?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Retrospective"},{key:"B",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Review"},{key:"D",text:"Daily Scrum"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Lessons learned are always captured but the main purpose of Sprint Retrospective is capturing and planning for lessons learned."},
  
  {id:31,question:"Which of the following is a benefit of working inside time-boxes?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It helps to limit work-in-progress."},{key:"B",text:"It ensures that all planned items will be finished."},{key:"C",text:"It increases the Scrum Team's velocity."},{key:"D",text:"It helps the Product Owner know which attribute of the 'Iron Triangle' to adjust."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"When working inside time-boxes, it's better to limit work-in-progress and get items done before going to the next ones; otherwise chances would be high that the team ends up with many in-progress items and rather than 'done' items at the end of the Sprint. Limiting work-in-progress is a lean concept that helps to manage waste."},
  
  {id:32,question:"There are 6 teams working on the same product. How many Product Owners are needed?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"One."},{key:"B",text:"Six."},{key:"C",text:"The team should decide."},{key:"D",text:"Depends on the complexity of the product."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"For a single product there is only one Product Backlog and one Product Owner to manage the Product Backlog regardless of how many Scrum Teams are working on the product."},
  
  {id:33,question:"Which of the following is not a pillar of Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Transparency"},{key:"B",text:"Inspection"},{key:"C",text:"Empiricism"},{key:"D",text:"Adaptation"}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The three pillars of Scrum are adaptation, inspection and transparency. Scrum is based on empiricism but it's not one of the pillars."},
  
  {id:34,question:"Self-managing Developers are characterized by their ability to ...",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Make local decisions."},{key:"B",text:"Decide on which features will be added to the product."},{key:"C",text:"Decide on the project vision."},{key:"D",text:"Make project-based decisions."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Team is focused on creating Increments during Sprints and are self-managing to find out how to best accomplish it. Higher-level decisions for the project might be done by the Product Owner or other stakeholders."},
  
  {id:35,question:"Which statement is least accurate about the Definition of Done?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It may evolve during the project."},{key:"B",text:"It's created by the Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"It may vary depending on the project."},{key:"D",text:"It may be defined by the development organization."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Definition of Done can be prepared in the development organization and used in all projects as a minimum. If additional content is required for the definition or it's not prepared in the organization level, the Scrum Team would be responsible for preparing it. The Definition of Done can evolve during the project as more is learned. It's also dependent on the project and its environment."},
  
  {id:36,question:"Which of the following is a responsibility of team leaders when multiple teams are working on the same product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Acting as middle men between the Product Owner and the developers."},{key:"B",text:"There's no team leaders in Scrum."},{key:"C",text:"Help the Product Owner with release planning."},{key:"D",text:"Making assignments."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"There are only three accountabilities in Scrum and other roles or titles are not recognized: the Product Owner, the Scrum Master, the Developers."},
  
  {id:37,question:"When multiple teams are working on the same product, who should make sure that their outputs can be integrated into one Increment?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers."},{key:"B",text:"The Developers and the Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"It's up to the Developers to figure out and ensure that their outputs will create an integrated Increment that is potentially releasable."},
  
  {id:38,question:"How is management external to the Scrum team involved in the Daily Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Product Owner represents their opinions."},{key:"B",text:"There's no such involvement."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master represents them."},{key:"D",text:"Management can be present at the meeting and open it with their updates or opinions."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Development Team self-manages and is the only management required at the Daily Scrum."},
  
  {id:39,question:"What should the Product Owner do during Sprint zero?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Prepare the Product Backlog for the next few Sprints."},{key:"B",text:"Communicate with the customer and understand the requirements."},{key:"C",text:"There's no such thing as Sprint zero."},{key:"D",text:"Prepare the Product Backlog for the whole project."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"There's no such thing as Sprint zero. The first Sprint is called Sprint 1 and it's exactly the same as other Sprints: creates an Increment. The infrastructure, tools and requirements are prepared gradually throughout the project."},
  
  {id:40,question:"Which of the following is a way of decreasing technical debt?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Hiring an external auditor."},{key:"B",text:"Improving the Definition of Done."},{key:"C",text:"Having hardening Sprints."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"There's usually room for improving the Definition of Done. A good definition will let less technical debt pass on to the next Sprints. Technical debt is minor shortcomings in the code that makes it less than 'good enough' and therefore creates risks in the future. It usually decreases velocity in the future (because the team has to fix the shortcomings) and as some of the debt might remain in the final product, the maintenance cost will increase as well. Another Agile way of reducing technical debt is continuous refactoring."},
  
  {id:41,question:"Which of the following events has the shortest max time-box in a four-week Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Retrospective"},{key:"B",text:"Sprint Planning"},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Review"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"These are the maximum durations defined for a one-month Sprint: Sprint Planning: 8 hours, Sprint Review: 4 hours, Sprint Retrospective: 3 hours. For shorter Sprints, the events are usually shorter."},
  
  {id:42,question:"Which of the following is a responsibility of a project manager in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There's no project manager in Scrum"},{key:"B",text:"Making high-level decisions"},{key:"C",text:"Authorizing the Sprints"},{key:"D",text:"Planning releases"},{key:"E",text:"Preparing the project plan and Gantt Charts"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"There are only three accountabilities defined in Scrum: the Product Owner, the Scrum Master and the Developers."},
  
  {id:43,question:"What's the optimal length of a Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Short enough to minimize risk"},{key:"B",text:"One week"},{key:"C",text:"Two weeks"},{key:"D",text:"One month"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"We prefer shorter Sprints as long as value can be produced. Shorter Sprints help to manage business risk."},
  
  {id:44,question:"What does a Product Owner do at the Sprint Retrospective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Capture questions and answers from the Developers."},{key:"B",text:"Participate as a member of the Scrum Team."},{key:"C",text:"Prioritize the outputs of the meeting."},{key:"D",text:"Summarize and report the results to the senior management."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The whole Scrum Team should participate in the Sprint Retrospective to find an improvement to be applied immediately or in the next Sprint; including the Product Owner."},
  
  {id:45,question:"Which statement best describes the Sprint Backlog?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Developers can replace items in the Sprint Backlog with items from the Product Backlog, if they cannot complete an item."},{key:"B",text:"The scope may be re-negotiated as more is learned."},{key:"C",text:"Sprint Backlog items that cannot be completed in the current Sprint is automatically added to the Sprint Backlog for the next Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"The Sprint time-box is extended if not all Sprint Backlog items are done."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a living artifact that changes as work is being done and more is learned. The scope may be clarified and re-negotiated in order for the team to achieve the Sprint Goal."},
  
  {id:46,question:"What should happen to the 'Done' Product Backlog items if the Sprint is cancelled?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"They should be moved back to the Product Backlog, and would be taken care of in the future Sprints."},{key:"B",text:"They should be moved to the next Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"They will be reviewed, and if they are potentially releasable, the Product Owner typically accepts them."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Product Owner is accountable for maximizing the value of the work the Developers do. If the Increment is potentially shippable then the Product Owner accepts it as so. The Product Owner can then decide whether or not to release."},
  
  {id:47,question:"How much of the Sprint Backlog should be defined during the Sprint Planning event?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Just enough, so the Developers can forecast what they can do and to start the first several days of the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Just enough for the Scrum Master to be able to assign tasks to the Developers."},{key:"C",text:"Just enough to understand design and architecture."},{key:"D",text:"All of the potential work."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog includes the items selected from the Product Backlog and the tasks created by decomposing the items. The items are planned in the Sprint Planning but not all tasks need to be created; just enough for the first few days of development. The rest of the tasks will emerge and be added during the Sprint."},
  
  {id:48,question:"Which of the following is not allowed in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Refactoring"},{key:"B",text:"Hardening Sprints"},{key:"C",text:"Velocity tracking"},{key:"D",text:"Release planning"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Hardening Sprints are not allowed because the subject of hardening should be continuously address throughout normal Sprints. All Sprints are the same in Scrum. Other options are not described in the framework but can be practices used in Scrum projects."},
  
  {id:49,question:"When multiple Scrum teams are working on the same product, should all of their outputs be integrated every Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Yes"},{key:"B",text:"No"},{key:"C",text:"Yes, only if there are dependencies among them"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"At the end of each Sprint a Scrum Team produces a potentially shippable product increment. So if multiple Scrum Teams are working on the same product, they should be integrating their outputs in order to help ensure the 'done' work is potentially shippable. Merging their work every Sprint will help the teams identify any integration issues and ensure the increment is potentially releasable."},
  
  {id:50,question:"What role does a tester have in Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Verifying the programmers output."},{key:"B",text:"Writing test cases."},{key:"C",text:"Incorporate the test driven development practices."},{key:"D",text:"Finding defects."},{key:"E",text:"There is no tester 'role' in Scrum."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"Scrum only describes accountabilities for the Product Owner, the Scrum Master and the Developers. Developers are the people in the Scrum Team that are committed to creating any aspect of a usable Increment each Sprint. Anyone actively working on items in the Sprint Backlog are considered as Developers regardless of individual titles."},
  
  {id:51,question:"Which of the following best describes transparency?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The whole process should be visible to everyone."},{key:"B",text:"The process should be visible, and understood by key stakeholders."},{key:"C",text:"The whole process should be visible to stakeholders."},{key:"D",text:"Significant aspects of the process must be visible to those responsible for the outcome."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Transparency is about visibility and doesn't contain understanding; even though we better try our best to create the right understanding too but that's another story. The 'whole process' might be too much for some stakeholders; 'significant aspects' is enough, as we treat most things in Agile environments."},
  
  {id:52,question:"The Product Owner doesn't spend enough time on the project. Which of the following options is the best response from the Scrum Master?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Nominate a proxy Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"Teach the Product Owner why it's important for her/him to spend enough time on the project."},{key:"C",text:"Bring up the issue in the Sprint Retrospective."},{key:"D",text:"Send the Product Owner to a proper training."},{key:"E",text:"Inform the Product Owner's functional manager."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Master is responsible to coach team members in a proactive way and help them do the right thing."},
  
  {id:53,question:"Which statement is correct when multiple Scrum Teams are working on the same product?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There can be multiple Product Backlogs divided into different application areas."},{key:"B",text:"All Scrum Teams share a single Product Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Each Scrum Team will have separate Product Backlogs and a single master Product Backlog to map the PBIs across the teams."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"For a product there is only one Product Backlog and one Product Owner to manage the Product Backlog regardless of how many Scrum Teams are working on the product."},
  
  {id:54,question:"The Developers cannot deliver the Increment because they don't understand a functional requirement. What should they do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Partially complete the work."},{key:"B",text:"Move the work to the next Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Consult with a specialist to solve the problem within the remaining duration of the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Collaborate with the Product Owner to help solve the problem."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Product Owner is responsible to make all items clear and understood. If the problem wasn't solved, then there's no option other than leaving it to go back to the Product Backlog at the end of the Sprint and be done later. Work cannot be considered part of an Increment unless it meets the Definition of Done."},
  
  {id:55,question:"Who creates the Sprint Goal?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master"},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner"},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Team"},{key:"D",text:"The Development Team"}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"All Scrum Team members together compose the Sprint Goal during the Sprint Planning."},
  
  {id:56,question:"True or False: The Product Owner can ask anyone on the Scrum Team to order the Product Backlog items instead of him/her.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner can delegate his/her responsibilities to others but he/she stays accountable."},
  
  {id:57,question:"True or False: When multiple Scrum Teams are working on the same product, each team should have their own Definition of Done.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"All teams can use the same Definition of Done but if required they can have different definitions as long as they are compatible and capable of creating integrated Increments. The answer to this question would have been 'true' instead of 'false' if there was a 'may' instead of 'should'."},
  
  {id:58,question:"True or False: The Product Owner can delegate some of his/her responsibilities to the Developers.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Product Owner can delegate his/her responsibilities to the others but he/she stays accountable."},
  
  {id:59,question:"True or False: Scrum should be tailored for the project.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Unlike methodologies, the Scrum 'framework' is not tailored because it's already limited to the essentials. Even the terms should not change let along adding or removing elements such as roles and events. However, you need to add many practices and techniques to the framework. The Scrum Master ensures that the team's process stays within the framework."},
  
  {id:60,question:"True or False: Our velocity was 250 at the end of the 6th Sprint. It has become 275 at the end of the 11th Sprint. Therefore, we're creating more value now as compared to the past.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Velocity and value have no direct relationship."},
  
  {id:61,question:"True or False: Only the Scrum Team is allowed to attend the Sprint Planning.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Team may also invite other people to attend Sprint Planning to provide advice."},
  
  {id:62,question:"True or False: There should be frequent integration Sprints to integrate the work of the Developers.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"There's no integration Sprint in Scrum. All Sprints are the same and create increments. Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. In order to provide value, the Increment must be usable."},
  
  {id:63,question:"True or False: It's required to use User Stories in Scrum.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"It is not mandatory to use User Stories in Scrum as it is a localized practice and is dependent on whether the Scrum Team deems the practice helpful or not."},
  
  {id:64,question:"True or False: It's better to have longer Sprints for projects with more risk.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Shorter Sprints provide shorter feedback loops and more opportunities to inspect and adapt. When addressing complex problems, increasing feedback loops will also increases risk."},
  
  {id:65,question:"True or False: The Developers are self-managing, therefore, can decide on the frequency of the Daily Scrum.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Team is self-managing and can make decisions but only within the borders set by Scrum. While implementing only parts of Scrum is possible, the result is not Scrum. Scrum exists only in its entirety and functions well as a container for other techniques, methodologies, and practices."},
  
  {id:66,question:"True or False: Scrum is a lightweight development methodology.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum is an empirical framework rather than a development methodology or process."},
  
  {id:67,question:"True or False: The Product Owner is accountable for both maximizing the value of the product and the value of the work done by the Developers.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The value of the work of the team is nothing but the value they create through the product. The Product Owner is responsible for maximizing the value the product delivers to the users and of the work of the Developers. How this is done may vary widely across organizations, Scrum Teams and individuals."},
  
  {id:68,question:"True or False: Time can be allocated between the end of one Sprint and before the start of the next Sprint for integration.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"An Increment is a concrete stepping stone toward the Product Goal. Each Increment is additive to all prior Increments and thoroughly verified, ensuring that all Increments work together. Work cannot be considered part of an Increment unless it meets the Definition of Done."},
  
  {id:69,question:"True or False: Using time-boxed Sprints helps to limit work-in-progress.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"When working inside time-boxes, it's better to limit work-in-progress and get items done before going to the next ones; otherwise, chances would be high that the team ends up with many in-progress items and not enough 'Done' items at the end of the Sprint. Limiting work-in-progress is a lean concept that avoids waste."},
  
  {id:70,question:"True or False: The Product Owner should invite stakeholders to the Sprint Retrospective.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Team invites the stakeholders to the Sprint Review meeting and can invite stakeholders to the Sprint Planning if necessary. The Sprint Retrospective is an internal event for the Scrum Team."},
  
  {id:71,question:"True or False: Anyone can attend the Daily Scrum, but only the Developers participate.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Developers are accountable for adapting their plan each day toward the Sprint Goal."},
  
  {id:72,question:"True or False: The Product Backlog is baselined at the beginning of the project.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"We don't baseline any artifact in Scrum. The Product Backlog is dynamic and never complete."},
  
  {id:73,question:"True or False: The Scrum Master is a management role.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Agile Embraces Horizontal Management. The Scrum Master is responsible for: Managing impediments, eliminating waste. Managing the process. Managing the team's health. Managing the boundaries of self-organization. Managing the culture."},
  
  {id:74,question:"True or False: The Developers are free to change their engineering practices whenever they need.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Developers are self-managing; they decide how best to handle their work and this decision can evolve during the project as more is learned about the needs. This is about how best to make the work done and doesn't have to be constrained by the Sprints. The elements that shouldn't be changed during the Sprint are those required for keeping them focused on the goals."},
  
  {id:75,question:"True or False: Each Sprint Backlog item is assigned ownership to individual Developers.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Items and tasks in the Sprint Backlog are not owned by any specific person; ownership and accountability is shared. Tasks can be assigned to one developer or a pair of developers but they don't own the task; they are just responsible for doing the work but the Developers as a whole remain accountable."},
  
  {id:76,question:"True or False: Each Developer should be cross-functional.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Scrum Team as a whole is cross-functional, which means the sum of all skills and competencies within the team. It does not necessarily mean that we need to have cross-functional individuals. Each individual can specialize in one or more technical layers or aspects of the project as long as the team as a whole is cross-functional (having all the expertise required to get the job done, with minimal or no need for external resources)."},
  
  {id:77,question:"True or False: The Scrum Master shouldn't allow the Developers start developing without having the tasks identified and assigned.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"There are two problems in this statement: The Scrum Master doesn't manage the team and cannot forbid team members from doing something and cannot order them to do certain things. The Developers identify the tasks and work on them gradually throughout the Sprint. Upfront planning limits team agility."},
  
  {id:78,question:"True or False: Scrum mandates the use of burn-down charts.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Teams can use burn-down charts but they are not mandatory."},
  
  {id:79,question:"True or False: Each new Sprint starts immediately after the previous Sprint.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Nothing happens between two Sprints; the next one starts immediately after the conclusion of the previous."},
  
  {id:80,question:"True or False: The Sprint Review is the only time when stakeholder feedback is captured.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Sprint Review is probably the most important opportunity for capturing feedback but adaptation is not limited to that. The Product Owner is constantly in contact with the stakeholders to identify new Product Backlog items or to refine them."}
];
const psm2Super1Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Which three activities describe what a Scrum Master manages as reflected by the Scrum Guide?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Managing the Product Backlog items and work in the Sprint Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Managing the process in which Scrum is applied."},{key:"C",text:"The way Scrum is understood and enacted within the organization."},{key:"D",text:"Removing organizational impediments that limits the team's progress."},{key:"E",text:"Managing the capacity and utilization of each Development Team member."},{key:"F",text:"Reporting on the performance of the Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D"],explanation:"SM manages Scrum process, understanding, and removes impediments."},
  {id:2,question:"What should you keep in mind when transitioning from component teams to cross-functional teams?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Easier to compare performance between teams."},{key:"B",text:"Newly formed teams need time to stabilize."},{key:"C",text:"People from different layers need time to work together."},{key:"D",text:"Postpone Scrum until teams are reorganized."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Teams need time to stabilize and people need time to work together."},
  {id:3,question:"Paul estimated 9 Sprints but velocity is 40 instead of 50 and integration tests aren't complete. What is the most effective way to recover?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Dev Team informs Paul progress is not correct, Increment not releasable, suggest doing past work first and re-estimate remaining work."},{key:"B",text:"Strive for 90% done and defer undone work."},{key:"C",text:"SM manages Sprint Backlog and assigns work."},{key:"D",text:"SM sets work aside for release Sprints."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Be transparent about true state and re-estimate before proceeding."},
  {id:4,question:"The Development Team reports daily work to the Product Owner at Daily Scrum. What should the Scrum Master do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask PO to stop attending."},{key:"B",text:"Allow PO to participate."},{key:"C",text:"Facilitate to avoid conflicts."},{key:"D",text:"Coach on purpose of events and let them figure out."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Coach on the purpose of Scrum events and let the team self-organize."},
  {id:5,question:"The team decided to remove regression testing from DoD. What two actions are most appropriate for Steven?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Reject the decision."},{key:"B",text:"Ask what problem they're solving and impact on transparency and quality."},{key:"C",text:"Accept as mutual agreement."},{key:"D",text:"Ask if they can still produce potentially shippable increments."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Ask about the problem and if shippable increments are still possible."},
  {id:6,question:"After 8 Sprints, sponsors are upset. What factors may have led to this?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"SM hasn't ensured transparency."},{key:"B",text:"Scope changes not tracked."},{key:"C",text:"Sponsors not using Sprint Reviews."},{key:"D",text:"Stakeholders not using Daily Scrum."},{key:"E",text:"Project plan followed stringently."},{key:"F",text:"PO not engaging with sponsors."}],correctAnswers:["A","C","F"],explanation:"Lack of transparency, sponsor engagement, and PO communication."},
  {id:7,question:"Three teams need Dan, a database specialist, full time. What should Steven do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Manage Sprint Backlogs for even utilization."},{key:"B",text:"Facilitate discussion with all teams and help implement their solution."},{key:"C",text:"Assign Dan to most urgent tasks first."},{key:"D",text:"Ask Dan to hire additional specialists."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Facilitate discussion and help teams self-organize."},
  {id:8,question:"Steven is SM for three new teams building one product. What two things should he first advise?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"One Product Owner accountable for maximizing value."},{key:"B",text:"Three Product Owners."},{key:"C",text:"One Product Backlog for all work."},{key:"D",text:"Each team has own Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"One PO and one Product Backlog for a single product."},
  {id:9,question:"The team suggests Daily Scrum every other day. What would be three key concerns?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"PO can't inspect utilization."},{key:"B",text:"Impediments raised and resolved more slowly."},{key:"C",text:"Less info shared, Sprint plan inaccurate."},{key:"D",text:"Fewer opportunities to inspect and adapt Sprint Backlog."},{key:"E",text:"SM can't update burndown."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D"],explanation:"Slower impediment resolution, less transparency, fewer adaptation opportunities."},
  {id:10,question:"Steven talks to five teams about integrating Increments. What would he encourage?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Each team delivers at end of Sprint, new items to integrate in next Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Wait for infrastructure before starting Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"Each team delivers in own code branch."},{key:"D",text:"All teams agree on mutual DoD for potentially shippable Increment including all previous Increments."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Shared DoD for integrated, potentially shippable Increments."},
  {id:11,question:"What is the best way to create Development Teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"PO creates skills matrix."},{key:"B",text:"Provide boundaries and allow self-organization."},{key:"C",text:"Leadership allocates by skills and experience."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Allow teams to self-organize within provided boundaries."},
  {id:12,question:"When multiple Scrum Teams work from the same Product Backlog, they must still work in conformance with the Scrum Guide.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"False"},{key:"B",text:"True"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum Guide applies regardless of number of teams."},
  {id:13,question:"How would budgeting and financial forecasting be performed in Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Budgeting not necessary."},{key:"B",text:"Fixed budgets not allowed."},{key:"C",text:"Frequently inspect outcomes to understand value per investment."},{key:"D",text:"Single release funded with several Sprints producing shippable increments."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Inspect outcomes frequently and fund releases across multiple Sprints."},
  {id:14,question:"Which three activities would be acceptable for Steven to help the organization adopt Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Schedule formal trainings."},{key:"B",text:"Require all teams start Scrum immediately."},{key:"C",text:"Extend Retrospectives for training."},{key:"D",text:"Educate stakeholders and clients."},{key:"E",text:"Arrange 1:1 coaching sessions."},{key:"F",text:"Penalize team members."}],correctAnswers:["A","D","E"],explanation:"Train, educate, and coach."},
  {id:15,question:"A team with velocity 55 will have a second team added. What's the impact on the original team?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Velocity not affected."},{key:"B",text:"Velocity likely to drop."},{key:"C",text:"Velocity likely to rise."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Supporting new team temporarily reduces velocity."},
  {id:16,question:"What two boundaries in Scrum guide effective self-organization?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Functional teams with handoff phases."},{key:"B",text:"Creating potentially shippable Increment each Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Mix of skills and experience."},{key:"D",text:"Timeboxing events for inspection and adaptation."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Shippable Increments and timeboxing guide self-organization."},
  {id:17,question:"Peter gives recognition to individuals during Daily Scrum. What two valid actions for Steven?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Coach Peter on burndown chart."},{key:"B",text:"Talk to Peter about behavior impact and suggest stopping attendance."},{key:"C",text:"Coach team on Daily Scrum purpose."},{key:"D",text:"Nothing, Steven is optional."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Address behavior impact and coach on Daily Scrum purpose."},
  {id:18,question:"Team requests hardening Sprint. What three scenarios likely occurred?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Scrum customized suitably."},{key:"B",text:"Difficulty releasing during Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"DoD not adhered to."},{key:"D",text:"Hardening Sprints supported."},{key:"E",text:"DoD weak causing technical debt."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","E"],explanation:"Hardening indicates DoD issues or integration difficulties."},
  {id:19,question:"What three statements best describe the purpose of Definition of Done?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Checklist to monitor progress."},{key:"B",text:"Guidance when forecasting Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Helps defer pending work."},{key:"D",text:"Creates transparency of 'done' state at Sprint Review."},{key:"E",text:"Helps decide when Sprint can end."},{key:"F",text:"Guidance on remaining work for shippable Increment."}],correctAnswers:["B","D","F"],explanation:"DoD guides forecasting, creates transparency, and shows remaining work."},
  {id:20,question:"What can the value of openness affect?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Collaboration efforts."},{key:"B",text:"Product quality."},{key:"C",text:"Team happiness."},{key:"D",text:"Time to market."},{key:"E",text:"Stakeholder trust."},{key:"F",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["F"],explanation:"Openness affects all of these."},
  {id:21,question:"A senior engineer uses too much time at Daily Scrum. What are the best 2 actions?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Speak privately and coach on Daily Scrum purpose."},{key:"B",text:"Use a token to limit speaking."},{key:"C",text:"Contact direct manager."},{key:"D",text:"Timebox each person to 2 minutes."},{key:"E",text:"Coach team to find solution and take ownership."}],correctAnswers:["A","E"],explanation:"Coach privately and help team own the solution."},
  {id:22,question:"What two items best describe what 'done' means?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ready for UAT."},{key:"B",text:"Ready for integration testing."},{key:"C",text:"All work as defined in DoD."},{key:"D",text:"Potentially releasable to end users."},{key:"E",text:"Within current skills and expertise."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Done means conforming to DoD and potentially releasable."},
  {id:23,question:"Conflict arises about what work makes an item 'done'. What is the best action?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"End discussion and make decision."},{key:"B",text:"Bring PO to decide."},{key:"C",text:"Interpret DoD for team."},{key:"D",text:"Facilitate session to resolve conflict and refine DoD."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Facilitate conflict resolution and refine DoD together."},
  {id:24,question:"A Dev Team member isn't attending Daily Scrum. The team says it's OK. What should Steven do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Run Daily Scrum and require attendance."},{key:"B",text:"Talk privately and say be a team player."},{key:"C",text:"It's the team's responsibility to decide."},{key:"D",text:"Ask team what value results from all attending and risks of non-attendance."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Ask team about value and risks to help them decide."},
  {id:25,question:"PO and Dev Team relationship has suffered due to changes. What should Steven do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Address in Sprint Retrospective and discuss why changes occur."},{key:"B",text:"Explain PO is accountable for value flow."},{key:"C",text:"Organize team building session."},{key:"D",text:"Ensure stable velocity by rejecting changes."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Address in Retrospective to understand why changes occur."},
  {id:26,question:"Team members complain about Chris questioning design decisions. What are two good ways to address this?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Tell members Chris' opinions should be respected."},{key:"B",text:"Facilitate session to resolve with full team."},{key:"C",text:"Observe if raised at Retrospective."},{key:"D",text:"Tell Chris to be a team player."},{key:"E",text:"Organize team building."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Facilitate team discussions and observe at Retrospective."},
  {id:27,question:"A PBI doesn't meet DoD at Sprint end. What two things should happen?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Include if acceptable at Sprint Review."},{key:"B",text:"Estimate remaining work and add to Product Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Don't include in Increment."},{key:"D",text:"Split and add completed work to current Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Don't include incomplete items. Return to Product Backlog."},
  {id:28,question:"Requirement changes in other components slowed your team. The program manager is upset. What could you do to help the Product Owner?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Remove items forecasted beyond expected date."},{key:"B",text:"Add additional developers."},{key:"C",text:"Work with program manager on ordering and value to redefine delivery date."},{key:"D",text:"Shorten Sprints."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Work with program manager on ordering and value for realistic expectations."},
  {id:29,question:"Three teams need Nicole full time. Which three acceptable solutions would Steven consider?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Combine teams for Sprints needing Nicole."},{key:"B",text:"People volunteer to take on Nicole's work."},{key:"C",text:"Ask Nicole to hire additional people."},{key:"D",text:"Create team with Nicole for her domain."},{key:"E",text:"Reorder Product Backlog so Nicole serves one team."},{key:"F",text:"Investigate scaling techniques or frameworks."}],correctAnswers:["B","E","F"],explanation:"Volunteer to learn, reorder PB, or investigate scaling."},
  {id:30,question:"PO is surprised about technical debt at fifth Sprint Retrospective. What factors may have led to this?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Not used Retrospectives effectively."},{key:"B",text:"Not enough attention to technical quality."},{key:"C",text:"No conversations about technical debt."},{key:"D",text:"SM hasn't ensured transparency."},{key:"E",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"All factors contributed to technical debt accumulation."}
];

const psm2Super2Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Which two scenarios would best represent a self-organizing Development Team?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Development Team members are strictly focused on the work within their functional role and always handing off the work to other roles in a timely matter."},{key:"B",text:"The Development Team invites external people to the Sprint Planning to help them create a complete and detailed Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Development Team members collaboratively select and re-plan their work throughout the Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Management works with the Scrum Master to optimize the Development Team's progress during the Sprint."},{key:"E",text:"The Development Team creates its own Sprint Backlog, reflecting all work that is part of the Definition of Done."}],correctAnswers:["C","E"],explanation:"Self-organizing teams collaboratively select and re-plan their work and create their own Sprint Backlog."},
  {id:2,question:"Steven is a Scrum Master of a Development Team that has members working in different cities and timezones. The Development Team proposes to only hold the Daily Scrum on Mondays. Which two responses would be most appropriate from Steven?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Acknowledge and support their decision."},{key:"B",text:"Ensure that there is an overall consensus by having the Development Team members vote."},{key:"C",text:"Coach the team on why having a Daily Scrum everyday is an important opportunity to update the Sprint plan and how it helps the team self-organize work toward achieving the Sprint Goal."},{key:"D",text:"Help the Development Team understand that lowering the frequency of communication will only increase the feeling of disconnect between the team members."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"The Scrum Master should coach on the value of daily frequency and help understand the risks of reduced communication."},
  {id:3,question:"At the halfway point of the Sprint, the Product Owner comes to Steven telling him that he is concerned the Development Team will not be able to complete the entire Sprint Backlog by the end of the Sprint. What should Steven do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Motivate the Development Team to meet their commitment to the Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"Add more people to the Development Team to meet the Product Owner's expectations."},{key:"C",text:"Advise the Product Owner that the Development Team owns the Sprint Backlog and it is up to them to meet their commitments."},{key:"D",text:"Coach the Product Owner that with complex software development, you cannot promise the entire scope that was forecast during Sprint Planning. As more is learned during the Sprint, work may emerge that affects the Sprint Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"The Sprint Backlog is a forecast. In complex development, unknowns may emerge as more is learned."},
  {id:4,question:"Scrum addresses which of the following four risks in software development?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The skills and working relationships of the people on the teams."},{key:"B",text:"The definition of incentive and bonus strategies by HR for all team members."},{key:"C",text:"The clear definitions of stages and gateways in the overall governance model."},{key:"D",text:"The timescale of the planned work."},{key:"E",text:"The complexity and unpredictability of the requirements."},{key:"F",text:"The stability and complexity of the technology."}],correctAnswers:["A","D","E","F"],explanation:"Scrum addresses risks related to people, timescale, requirements complexity, and technology stability."},
  {id:5,question:"After several Sprints, a key stakeholder starts using the product. The stakeholder is surprised by the slow performance and complains to the Product Owner. What is the best action for a Scrum Master to take?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Encourage the Product Owner to bring the performance concerns to the Development Team and work with them on how to improve performance, and ultimately have stronger Definition of Done."},{key:"B",text:"Explain to the Product Owner that it's up to the Development Team to decide on acceptable performance standards as they own the Definition of Done."},{key:"C",text:"Wait until the next Sprint Retrospective as it is the most opportune time to modify the Definition of Done."},{key:"D",text:"Bring the concern to the testers in the Development Team and ask them to include performance testing."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The Scrum Master should encourage the PO to work with the Development Team to improve performance and strengthen the DoD."},
  {id:6,question:"During the Sprint Review, the Product Owner decides to release the current Increment to production. The stakeholders suggest temporarily delaying the next Sprint to respond to user feedback. The Product Owner prefers to continue. What would be two acceptable outcomes?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Continue with the Sprints and include the customer feedback in the Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Continue with the Sprints but shorten the Sprint time-boxes to allow for shorter feedback loops."},{key:"C",text:"Delay the next Sprint to allow the Development Team to work on new customer feedback."},{key:"D",text:"Continue with the Sprints but allow the Sprint Goal within the Sprint to change according to the customer feedback."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"A new Sprint starts immediately after the previous Sprint. Feedback goes to the Product Backlog or Sprints can be shortened."},
  {id:7,question:"At the Sprint Planning, the Development Team is not able to forecast the number of Product Backlog items due to unclear requirements. The Product Owner was able to clearly define the business objective. Which two actions would you support?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Allow the Development Team members as much time as needed to review the Product Backlog items and reconvene when they are confident enough to make a forecast."},{key:"B",text:"The Development Team forecasts the most likely Product Backlog items to meet the business objective and create a Sprint Backlog. Once the time-box is over, they start implementation and continue to analyze during the Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"If all agree they can extend the Sprint Planning until the Development Team can forecast enough Product Backlog items."},{key:"D",text:"They discuss in the upcoming Sprint Retrospective why this happened and what changes will make it less likely to occur again."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Events are time-boxed. The team should forecast best guess items and discuss improvements in the Retrospective."},
  {id:8,question:"What would be the best way for Steven to determine if the Product Owner is interacting enough with the Development Team during a Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"See whether the Product Owner has provided enough information at the Sprint Planning to make his/her presence optional during the Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Check whether the Increment presented at the Sprint Review meets the Product Owner's expectations."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner must always be present with the Development Team. Unavailability of the Product Owner is prohibited in Scrum."},{key:"D",text:"Check whether the Product Owner is actively engaged at the Daily Scrums."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Increment meeting the PO's expectations indicates sufficient interaction during the Sprint."},
  {id:9,question:"In what two ways is velocity and technical debt related?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A Development Team can artificially increase velocity by allowing technical debt to be incurred."},{key:"B",text:"Adding estimates to technical debt will allow the Development Team to maintain constant velocity therefore ensuring predictability."},{key:"C",text:"As the Development Team is working on new Product Backlog items, they may unexpectedly run into technical debt that will result the team's velocity dropping."},{key:"D",text:"They are not related because technical debt is non-functional and velocity is calculated based on end user functionality."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Technical debt can artificially inflate velocity or cause unexpected drops when encountered."},
  {id:10,question:"A new Product Owner has joined an existing Scrum Team. The Development Team has grown to have a good understanding of the product. The Product Owner is unsure about his responsibilities. What would be two acceptable ways of helping the Product Owner?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Inform the Product Owner that the Daily Scrum allows the Development Team to adapt to changes in scope without delay."},{key:"B",text:"Advise the Product Owner to rely on the Development Team and the stakeholders to formulate the Product Backlog. By asking questions and working with them the Product Owner will quickly be up to speed."},{key:"C",text:"Tell the Product Owner to make sure there are no ambiguities in the items on the Product Backlog when handed over to the Development Team."},{key:"D",text:"Advise the Product Owner to start building a good relationship with the stakeholders. The Product Owner is also expected to invite the right stakeholders to the Sprint Review meeting."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"The PO should build relationships with stakeholders and leverage the team's knowledge."},
  {id:11,question:"A new member has just joined an existing Development Team. During the Sprint, the individual has been trying to share his ideas but is continuously ignored by the rest of the Development Team. Which three Scrum Values has the Development Team been neglecting?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Courage"},{key:"B",text:"Focus"},{key:"C",text:"Transparency"},{key:"D",text:"Respect"},{key:"E",text:"Openness"},{key:"F",text:"Commitment"}],correctAnswers:["A","D","E"],explanation:"The team is neglecting Courage (to speak up), Respect (for the person), and Openness (to new ideas). Transparency is a pillar, not a value."},
  {id:12,question:"Which two behaviors would reflect Servant Leadership in a Scrum Master?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Coaching the Development Team, the Product Owner and the organization on how to work empirically."},{key:"B",text:"Staying away from internal Development Team interactions, maximizing their autonomy and freedom."},{key:"C",text:"Resolving every impediment for the Development Team."},{key:"D",text:"Facilitating Scrum Events as requested or needed."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Servant Leadership includes coaching on empiricism and facilitating events, not resolving every impediment."},
  {id:13,question:"Collaboration issues and technical dependencies between multiple Scrum Teams working on the same product can be fully resolved by using the correct version control tools.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"False"},{key:"B",text:"True"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Tools alone cannot fully resolve collaboration issues and dependencies. People and processes matter more."},
  {id:14,question:"Which two statements are the most accurate in regards to scaling Scrum for large projects requiring multiple Scrum Teams?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"A well-structured Product Backlog can minimize dependencies and increase focus for each team."},{key:"B",text:"Customizing the core Scrum framework is necessary to be successful with Scrum at large scale."},{key:"C",text:"A person focusing on the Sprint Backlog of a single Scrum Team is often more productive than that same person working on multiple Scrum Teams at the same time."},{key:"D",text:"Team members must work full time on a single Scrum Team."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"A good Product Backlog minimizes dependencies and people are more productive when focused on one team."},
  {id:15,question:"You have a Scrum Team that has been working together for over a year. The Development Team consists of 11 members who rarely collaborate. There are no Sprint Goals and most items in the Sprint Backlog are unrelated. What might explain why the Scrum Team is finding it difficult to craft Sprint Goals?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Sprints are too long."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner doesn't set objectives that he/she wants to achieve with upcoming Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"The Development Team is too big."},{key:"D",text:"The Product Owner is not empowered to make decisions about items in the Product Backlog nor how they are ordered."},{key:"E",text:"Scrum might not be the best framework for this team."}],correctAnswers:["B","D","E"],explanation:"Lack of Sprint Goals relates to PO not setting objectives, not being empowered, or Scrum not being suitable."},
  {id:16,question:"According to the Scrum Guide, where should the Daily Scrum be held?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"In the same location where the Development Team is seated."},{key:"B",text:"Wherever the Development Team decides is most suitable."},{key:"C",text:"In front of the Scrum board."},{key:"D",text:"Wherever the Scrum Master decides is best."},{key:"E",text:"In a room where management can attend."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"The Daily Scrum is held wherever the Development Team decides is most suitable."},
  {id:17,question:"During the Sprint Retrospective, the team is discussing the quality issues that prevented them from delivering a releasable Increment. The Development Team mentions they achieved high velocity. What are the best two responses for Steven?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Acknowledge the hard work but remind the Development Team that they need to improve to do even more in the next Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Facilitate a discussion on how to improve the quality to a level high enough for the Increment to be releasable, even if the measured velocity drops."},{key:"C",text:"Stress the value of working software over measured velocity."},{key:"D",text:"Agree and acknowledge the Development Team's hard work, so they will be motivated to do even more in the next Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Working software is more valuable than high velocity. Focus on improving quality for releasable Increments."},
  {id:18,question:"Adding more resources in Scrum will proportionally increase the value delivered.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"False"},{key:"B",text:"True"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Adding resources does not guarantee proportional increase in value in complex environments."},
  {id:19,question:"Steven has been invited to meet the IT and product management team. During the meeting the Product Owner asks how many Sprints will be needed to address the entire architecture and infrastructure before working on features. What are the two best responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"You confirm that architecture and infrastructure is needed before starting on business functionality but the estimated budget will be difficult to estimate."},{key:"B",text:"You coach the Product Owner and Development Team to add this work to Product Backlog to ensure transparency, have the Development Team estimate the work and do this in early Sprints while also creating some business functionality."},{key:"C",text:"You explain that it is more effective when architecture and infrastructure emerge alongside the development of business functionality."},{key:"D",text:"You explain that product management should not worry about technical solutions."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Architecture should emerge alongside business functionality and be added to the Product Backlog for transparency."},
  {id:20,question:"Steven's Daily Scrum requires more than 15 minutes and the team has suggested dividing into two teams. What would be the best response?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Agree - this is an appropriate solution to the problem."},{key:"B",text:"Agree - dividing the team into two is a good strategy to allow the teams to learn how to run Daily Scrums quickly."},{key:"C",text:"Unsure - dividing a team into two cannot be decided based on this information. You offer to observe."},{key:"D",text:"Disagree - as the root cause may not be that the team is too big."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"More information is needed before deciding to split the team. Offer to observe first."},
  {id:21,question:"An organization is using Scrum to build five new products. What would be the best two options for the number of Product Owners?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"There is one Product Owner for each product (so five in total). Each Product Owner may delegate, share and align work within their individual Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Enough Product Owners to delegate as much work needed to maximize utilization of all Development Team members."},{key:"C",text:"There is one Product Owner responsible for all five products. In order to scale his role, he/she can delegate some responsibilities to others but would still remain accountable."},{key:"D",text:"There is one Product Owner responsible for all five products. This person is not allowed to delegate any responsibilities."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"One PO per product or one PO for all who can delegate but remains accountable."},
  {id:22,question:"Your company has notified stakeholders that they will be delivering the first release within ten Sprints. On the seventh Sprint, the Scrum Team discovers they cannot include all features. The Product Owner believes removing items from the Definition of Done will accelerate development. What are the best two ways to explain the impact of technical debt?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Reducing the Definition of Done will introduce unknown errors as development progresses. The system can become more difficult to stabilize. Development will be slowed down in unpredictable ways."},{key:"B",text:"The amount of technical debt will need to be analyzed to allocate additional Sprints at the end of the project."},{key:"C",text:"As long as there is still technical debt, feature development for the next release cannot be started."},{key:"D",text:"Releasing upon a reduced Definition of Done creates false assumptions about the actual state of the system. This will create many interruptions during the next release."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Technical debt introduces unknown errors, makes stabilization harder, and creates false assumptions about system state."},
  {id:23,question:"Steven is a Scrum Master for three Scrum Teams building the same product. Management wants to standardize velocity to identify high performing teams. What would be the best two responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Velocity is the amount of business functionality that a Scrum Team creates in a Sprint. It is unique to that team and used as an input to Sprint Planning."},{key:"B",text:"Providing incentives based on velocity can increase the Scrum Team's motivation to produce more value."},{key:"C",text:"There is no direct relationship between velocity and value."},{key:"D",text:"Standardizing velocity across teams is a good way to understand which teams are producing the most value."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Velocity is unique to each team for Sprint Planning. There's no direct relationship between velocity and value."},
  {id:24,question:"Which approach would you recommend to ensure that the Product Backlog items discussed at Sprint Planning are well understood?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Having the Product Owner work with stakeholders between the end of the last Sprint and before beginning the next to prepare the Product Backlog items."},{key:"B",text:"Having the Development Team use some time during each Sprint to help the Product Owner analyze, estimate, and design items at the top of the Product Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Having a separate group of business analysts and functional testers analyzing high-ordered Product Backlog items before Sprint Planning."},{key:"D",text:"Having the business analysts in the Development Team create the upcoming Product Backlog items during a Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Product Backlog refinement involves the Development Team helping the PO analyze and estimate items during the Sprint."},
  {id:25,question:"During the Sprint Review of a scaled development effort, each Scrum Team should demonstrate its individual Increment in a separate branch of the code.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"True"},{key:"B",text:"False"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Multiple teams should integrate their work into a single Increment, not demonstrate separate branches."},
  {id:26,question:"What would be the best two ways to identify that a Development Team is self-organizing?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Development Team is able to resolve internal conflicts between members in order to continue working."},{key:"B",text:"Management is able to know which members are working on which items."},{key:"C",text:"Creativity thrives and new possibilities are explored."},{key:"D",text:"The Development Team members are cross-functional and knows what it needs to do to deliver all tasks committed to the Sprint Planning."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Self-organizing teams resolve internal conflicts and creativity thrives with new possibilities explored."},
  {id:27,question:"Select two ways in which Scrum uses time-boxing to promote self-organization?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Time-boxes helps everybody concentrate on the same problem at the same time."},{key:"B",text:"Time-boxes ensures that the Development Team commits to completing the items in the Sprint Backlog by the end of the Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Time-boxes can help teams plan how many additional Sprints is needed for User Acceptance testing."},{key:"D",text:"Time-boxes encourage the ones closest to the problem make the best possible decisions within the time-frame given the current situation."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Time-boxes help focus on the same problem and encourage those closest to the problem to make decisions."},
  {id:28,question:"Your organization requires all Increments to pass user acceptance testing (UAT) before release. Is it a good idea to postpone UAT until the end of the project?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It depends on the team's Definition of Done."},{key:"B",text:"No, because the state of the Product Increment won't be transparent and the feedback loop would be too long."},{key:"C",text:"Yes, because UAT is done in a hardening Sprint before the release Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Yes, because the Development Team is a self-organizing team and should not be disrupted during development."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Postponing UAT reduces transparency and creates too long a feedback loop."},
  {id:29,question:"During the Sprint Review, one of the stakeholders announces that due to market changes, funding might be reduced. Tensions rise and arguments break out. As a Scrum Master, what would be the best two actions?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Encourage the stakeholders and Product Owner to focus on delivering the highest value items for the next Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Inform everyone that the team needs to stay busy until the information is formally announced."},{key:"C",text:"Be objective and request for a short break for people to calm down."},{key:"D",text:"Defend the original budget and request the stakeholders to adhere to the original agreed funding."},{key:"E",text:"Avoid getting involved as it is the Product Owner's responsibility to manage stakeholder expectations."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Focus on highest value items and request a break to calm down and be objective."},
  {id:30,question:"The director of engineering asks Steven to increase his team's velocity by 15%. Which would be the best two responses for Steven?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"He informs the director of organizational impediments he is aware of that prevent the team from being more productive."},{key:"B",text:"He educates his director how it is part of a team's self-organization to improve velocity."},{key:"C",text:"He helps the director understand that it typically takes a few Sprints for a team to gradually increase velocity."},{key:"D",text:"He tells the director that this is not his responsibility in Scrum."},{key:"E",text:"He explains how a team uses velocity primarily to forecast work for the next Sprint, not to perfectly predict future productivity."}],correctAnswers:["A","E"],explanation:"Inform about impediments and explain velocity is for forecasting, not predicting future productivity."}
];

const psm2Super3Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Where should the Daily Scrum be held according to the Scrum Guide?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Around the Scrum board."},{key:"B",text:"In the coffee corner to confirm this is an informal gathering."},{key:"C",text:"Wherever the Development Team thinks is best."},{key:"D",text:"In the room that is reserved by the Scrum Master."},{key:"E",text:"In a room where management can listen in."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"The Daily Scrum is held wherever the Development Team thinks is best."},
  {id:2,question:"A new Product Owner comes in, unsure about his responsibilities. The Development Team has grown in functional and business insights over the past Sprints. What are two activities you would direct the new Product Owner towards?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Inform the Product Owner that the Daily Scrum allows the Development Team to adapt to changes in scope without delay."},{key:"B",text:"Advise the Product Owner to start building a good relationship with the stakeholders. The Product Owner is also expected to invite the best-placed stakeholders to the Sprint Review meeting."},{key:"C",text:"Tell the Product Owner to make sure that there are no ambiguities in the items on the Product Backlog when handed over to the Development Team."},{key:"D",text:"Advise the Product Owner to rely on the Development Team and the stakeholders to formulate the Product Backlog. By questioning them and working with them the Product Owner will quickly be most productive."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"The PO should build stakeholder relationships and leverage the team's knowledge to get up to speed."},
  {id:3,question:"Which two options describe how project budgeting and financial forecasting work in Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It is ideally revisited as frequently as each Sprint to ensure value is being delivered for the investment spent."},{key:"B",text:"Scrum does not align with traditional accounting practices. The financial department needs to be given a fixed cost per Sprint per team."},{key:"C",text:"Several Sprints may be funded as a single release, with the result of each Sprint being releasable software."},{key:"D",text:"The only funding is for the run cost of the Scrum Teams, so no budgeting process is needed."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Budgeting is revisited each Sprint and multiple Sprints can be funded as a single release."},
  {id:4,question:"The relationship between the Product Owner and the Development Team has degraded over time. The Development Team is angry with the Product Owner for changing requirements. The Product Owner is angry with the Development Team for changing requirements during implementation. What is the stance a Scrum Master takes?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask each person's functional manager to instruct their employees that they have to collaborate better."},{key:"B",text:"Take everyone to a 2-day off-site event to relax and re-align."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Master's role is to protect the Development Team. Ask for an external instance to mediate."},{key:"D",text:"Address why requirements change in the Sprint Retrospective. Ask the Development Team and the Product Owner to talk about why and consider the impact of the changes on value."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Address the issue in the Sprint Retrospective and facilitate discussion about why changes occur."},
  {id:5,question:"You are a Scrum Master entering an organization with component teams. You introduce feature teams. What are two things to consider when moving from component teams toward feature teams?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Feature teams will require time to become productive as people from the different layers become accustomed to working and delivering unified functionality together."},{key:"B",text:"Productivity, in terms of lines of code or story points, will probably suffer during the transition. Although even then delivery of business value is still likely to increase."},{key:"C",text:"With feature teams, it is easier to calculate and compare the productivity per team."},{key:"D",text:"You cannot do Scrum without feature teams. Don't continue adopting Scrum until teams are reorganized."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Feature teams need time to become productive and productivity may suffer initially, but value delivery increases."},
  {id:6,question:"A Development Team has members working from globally distributed locations. The team proposes doing a Daily Scrum only on Tuesdays. Which two are the most appropriate responses for the Scrum Master?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Have the developers vote to make sure there is overall consensus within the team."},{key:"B",text:"Acknowledge and support this self-organizing team's decision."},{key:"C",text:"Help the Development Team understand that lowering the frequency of communication will only increase the feeling of disconnect between the team members."},{key:"D",text:"Coach the team on why a daily frequency is important as an opportunity to update the Sprint plan and how it helps the team self-organize."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Coach on daily frequency importance and help understand risks of reduced communication."},
  {id:7,question:"One of the Development Team members is always missing the Daily Scrum. He feels that as long as he is doing his job well it doesn't matter whether he attends. The Development Team is not doing anything about it. How would you respond?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Teach the Development Team how to deal with this situation by attending the Daily Scrum."},{key:"B",text:"Ask the Development Team what value they will achieve by having the Daily Scrum with all team members present and what might go wrong if members don't attend."},{key:"C",text:"You do not intervene. The Development Team owns the Daily Scrum."},{key:"D",text:"Talk to the Development Team member who is missing Daily Scrum and ask him to be present without fail."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Ask the team about the value of having all members present and risks of non-attendance."},
  {id:8,question:"True or False: During the Sprint Review of a scaled development effort, every Scrum Team should demonstrate its individual Increment in a separate branch of the code.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"True"},{key:"B",text:"False"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Multiple teams should integrate their work into a single Increment, not demonstrate separate branches."},
  {id:9,question:"Scrum Master is a management position because the Scrum Master is accountable for which three management activities?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Managing the capacity and utilization of the developers."},{key:"B",text:"Reporting on the performance of a team."},{key:"C",text:"Managing the project plan and the project deliverables."},{key:"D",text:"Removing organizational impediments that limit the team's progress and productivity."},{key:"E",text:"Managing the Scrum process."},{key:"F",text:"The way Scrum is understood and enacted within the organization."}],correctAnswers:["D","E","F"],explanation:"The SM manages the Scrum process, how Scrum is understood, and removes organizational impediments."},
  {id:10,question:"What three conditions are most likely occurring if you are about to start a 'Quality Assurance and Release Readiness Sprint'?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The definition of 'Done' is not being met every Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"The definition of 'Done' is weak or incomplete, allowing technical debt to accumulate."},{key:"C",text:"The Development Team is finding it nearly impossible to have multiple releases in a Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"You are following Scrum and the concept of a Hardening Sprint."},{key:"E",text:"Scrum has been modified in an acceptable manner."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C"],explanation:"Hardening Sprints indicate DoD not being met, weak DoD, or difficulty with releases."},
  {id:11,question:"In the Sprint Review, one of the stakeholders highlights that funding may run out. An argument follows with raised voices. As a Scrum Master, what are your two best options?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It is the Product Owner's meeting, so do nothing."},{key:"B",text:"Encourage the stakeholders to focus on delivering the highest value items for the next Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Ask for a short break for people to calm down and be objective."},{key:"D",text:"Defend the budget, asking the stakeholders to support the funding."},{key:"E",text:"Argue that the team needs to be kept busy while the funding is confirmed."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Focus on highest value items and request a break to calm down."},
  {id:12,question:"A few members of the Scrum Team discuss work that is not being done. Some say it is part of the Definition of Done; others say it isn't. After angry discussion, someone starts making personal insults. What is the best action for the Scrum Master?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Take the people involved aside. Ask them to resolve the solution outside of the team."},{key:"B",text:"Conduct a session to help the entire team resolve the conflict, create a uniform Definition of Done, and become effective again. Remind the team that conflicting ideas are natural but making it personal doesn't help."},{key:"C",text:"Defuse the conflict. Take the Definition of Done and tell the Development Team members how to interpret it."},{key:"D",text:"End the discussion. Make the call whether the work is or is not part of the Definition of Done."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Facilitate conflict resolution to create a uniform DoD. Remind that conflicting ideas are natural but personal attacks don't help."},
  {id:13,question:"Five new Scrum Teams have been created to build one product. A few developers ask the Scrum Master who will coordinate the work between the different teams. What should the Scrum Master do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Teach them that it is their responsibility to form teams of people with the skills and knowledge to create an integrated Increment by the end of every Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Collect the Sprint tasks from the teams at the end of their Sprint Planning and merge into a consolidated plan."},{key:"C",text:"Visit the five teams each day to facilitate alignment and synchronization of their Sprint Backlogs."},{key:"D",text:"Advise the teams to reduce interdependence by working in separate branches."},{key:"E",text:"Teach the Product Owner to work with lead developers on ordering Product Backlog to avoid overlap."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Teach teams it's their responsibility to form with skills needed to create an integrated Increment."},
  {id:14,question:"At a Sprint Review meeting, the Chief Security Officer reminds everyone of important non-functional security requirements. What are two good ways the Development Team can handle these high security concerns?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The impact on past AND future work needs to be determined before new Sprints can start."},{key:"B",text:"They are discussed, determined, and documented in parallel Sprints to not disturb feature development."},{key:"C",text:"They should be handled by a separate, specialist team in a parallel Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"During the Sprint Retrospective, the Development Team assesses how to add these expectations to the Definition of Done."},{key:"E",text:"They are added to the Product Backlog and addressed throughout the next Sprints, combined with creating business functionality."}],correctAnswers:["D","E"],explanation:"Add security to DoD in Retrospective and add security items to Product Backlog to address alongside business functionality."},
  {id:15,question:"In an environment where user acceptance testing is required, a development manager proposes to have UAT done every third Sprint because feedback is disrupting work. Is this a good idea?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"No, because the Product Increment won't be transparent and the feedback loop is too long."},{key:"B",text:"Yes, because the Development Team needs stabilization in the Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"It depends on what is stated in their Definition of Done."},{key:"D",text:"Yes, because the Development Team is self-organizing and external people cannot influence the work."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"No, because transparency and short feedback loops are essential in Scrum."},
  {id:16,question:"Another Scrum Master seeks your advice. The Daily Scrum always runs longer than 15 minutes. They suggest splitting the team into two teams. What is your response?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"You're unsure - whether to split a team into two cannot be decided based on this information. You offer to observe."},{key:"B",text:"You disagree - as the root cause may not be that the team is too big."},{key:"C",text:"You agree - splitting the team into two is a good strategy to allow the teams to learn how to run Daily Scrums fast."},{key:"D",text:"You agree - this is an appropriate solution to the problem."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"More information is needed before deciding. Offer to observe."},
  {id:17,question:"At the seventh Sprint Review, the stakeholders seem disappointed and angry. They say the product will not meet their needs and will cost more than anticipated. What factors may have led to this?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Scrum Master has not ensured transparency."},{key:"B",text:"The Project Management Office and its project managers have not been engaged adequately."},{key:"C",text:"The Product Owner has not been interacting frequently with the stakeholders and kept them aware of progress."},{key:"D",text:"The stakeholders haven't been using the Sprint Reviews to actively engage, inspect and evaluate progress."},{key:"E",text:"Changes to project plan were not adequately documented and shared."},{key:"F",text:"The stakeholders were not allowed to enter the development area or be present at the Daily Scrum."}],correctAnswers:["A","C","D"],explanation:"Lack of transparency, PO not engaging stakeholders, and stakeholders not using Sprint Reviews."},
  {id:18,question:"Which four of the following risks to software development are addressed by Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The stability and complexity of the technology."},{key:"B",text:"The skills and working relationships of the people on the team."},{key:"C",text:"The complexity and unpredictability of the requirements."},{key:"D",text:"The clear definitions of stages and gateways in the overall governance model."},{key:"E",text:"The definition of incentive and bonus strategies by Human Resources."},{key:"F",text:"The timescale of the planned work."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C","F"],explanation:"Scrum addresses risks related to technology, people, requirements, and timescale."},
  {id:19,question:"You will be Scrum Master of two new teams that will build a first version of the product. Product management wants advice on the Product Owner's involvement. Which two baseline suggestions would you bring up?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Two Product Owners are necessary, one for each Scrum Team. They report to a chief Product Owner."},{key:"B",text:"One Product Backlog is maintained holding all requirements for the product."},{key:"C",text:"Each Scrum Team has a separate Product Backlog, holding each team's assigned requirements."},{key:"D",text:"Having one Product Owner will improve the clarity of accountability to the teams and to product management."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"One Product Backlog for the product and one Product Owner improves clarity and accountability."},
  {id:20,question:"Development Team members came to express concerns over Ivo. Anyone who pairs with Ivo gets caught up in discussions over design and architecture. Ivo re-opens earlier team decisions. What are two ways to go about this problem?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask Human Resources to have a conversation with Ivo based on the issues the team has raised."},{key:"B",text:"Organize an offsite team building activity to establish a foundation of trust."},{key:"C",text:"To every team member expressing this concern, suggest opening this up with the full team. Propose being willing to help initiate the conversation."},{key:"D",text:"Take Ivo aside to express your concern. Tell him to act as a team player and comply with the team's decision."},{key:"E",text:"At the Sprint Retrospective observe whether the topic is raised. If it doesn't happen, check on how comfortable everybody is with how architecture and design are being handled."}],correctAnswers:["C","E"],explanation:"Suggest opening up with full team and observe whether topic is raised at Retrospective."},
  {id:21,question:"You are Scrum Master for four teams working from the same Product Backlog. Several developers complain that work will require full time commitment from Stella, an external specialist. What would be three acceptable solutions?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Investigate whether applying additional techniques or frameworks for scaling Scrum would be appropriate."},{key:"B",text:"Ask Stella for a plan to hire and train additional people in her domain."},{key:"C",text:"Have the Development Team reorder the Product Backlog so Stella can serve one team full-time in a Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Merge the multiple teams into one large team for the next Sprints."},{key:"E",text:"Create a team with Stella and people from the teams to temporarily work in Stella's domain."},{key:"F",text:"People from the Development Teams with an interest in Stella's domain could volunteer to take on this work."},{key:"G",text:"Organize a release Sprint in which Stella can thoroughly check and complete all the work."}],correctAnswers:["A","C","F"],explanation:"Investigate scaling frameworks, reorder PB for Stella to serve one team, or have people volunteer to learn."},
  {id:22,question:"A Development Team is waiting for an external supplier to deliver a software component. Without it there won't be enough work. They ask the Product Owner to re-order the Product Backlog. What would be good advice?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Tell the Product Owner that his primary concern is the flow of value reflected in the ordering of the Product Backlog. Timeline might be influenced by dependencies but doesn't necessarily change the ordering."},{key:"B",text:"Tell the Product Owner to remove all items involving the external component from the Product Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Tell the Product Owner that the Product Backlog needs to be re-ordered to maximize utilization of the Development Team."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"The PO's primary concern is flow of value. Dependencies influence timeline but not necessarily ordering."},
  {id:23,question:"Which statement about the Sprint Goal is FALSE?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It helps increase focus."},{key:"B",text:"If it doesn't seem achievable, the Development Team has the courage to tell the Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"The Scrum Team discusses openly about alternative ways to reach it."},{key:"D",text:"The Development Team commits to it."},{key:"E",text:"The Product Owner respects the Development Team's opinion on whether they can achieve it."},{key:"F",text:"It is only a forecast and may change within the Sprint as more is learned."}],correctAnswers:["F"],explanation:"The Sprint Goal does NOT change during the Sprint. It provides stability while scope may be clarified."},
  {id:24,question:"What can the Scrum Value of openness easily impact?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Collaboration."},{key:"B",text:"Software quality."},{key:"C",text:"Employee satisfaction."},{key:"D",text:"Time to market."},{key:"E",text:"Stakeholder trust."},{key:"F",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["F"],explanation:"Openness impacts collaboration, quality, satisfaction, time to market, and stakeholder trust - all of the above."},
  {id:25,question:"A Development Team is struggling because not all team members work full time and others work from home. Two team members suggest having the Daily Scrum every three days. What would be three key concerns if the frequency were lower?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Impediments are raised and resolved more slowly which might impact productivity and progress."},{key:"B",text:"The Product Owner cannot accurately report progress about the state of the forecasted work to the stakeholders."},{key:"C",text:"Opportunities to inspect and adapt the Sprint Backlog are reduced. Re-aligning is bound to become even more difficult."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master loses the ability to update the Gantt chart properly."},{key:"E",text:"Less progress information will be shared causing the Sprint plan to become inaccurate and transparency over progress toward the Sprint Goal is reduced."}],correctAnswers:["A","C","E"],explanation:"Lower frequency means slower impediment resolution, fewer adaptation opportunities, and reduced transparency."},
  {id:26,question:"In Sprint Planning, a Development Team works with the Product Owner to create a forecast. Select two things that explain what 'Done' means.",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"All work for which enough expertise and skills are actually present in the Development Team."},{key:"B",text:"All work to create an Increment of software that is ready for acceptance testing by the Product Owner."},{key:"C",text:"Having an Increment of software that could be released to end users."},{key:"D",text:"All work to create an Increment of software that is ready for integration testing."},{key:"E",text:"All work performed as listed in the Definition of Done."}],correctAnswers:["C","E"],explanation:"Done means potentially releasable Increment and all work performed as listed in the Definition of Done."},
  {id:27,question:"The Product Owner is attending the Daily Scrum. The Development Team members have been reporting Sprint progress to the Product Owner. What is the best thing for the Scrum Master to do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Leave the Daily Scrum as it is so that the Product Owner can continue to track progress."},{key:"B",text:"Coach the Product Owner and Development Team members on the purpose of Scrum events and let them figure out how to deal with this situation."},{key:"C",text:"Ask the Product Owner to stop attending the Daily Scrum."},{key:"D",text:"Start attending the Daily Scrum so whenever there is a conflict, the Scrum Master can resolve it."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Coach both PO and Dev Team on the purpose of Scrum events and let them self-organize."},
  {id:28,question:"Marian estimated the project to take seven Sprints based on average velocity of 13. After three Sprints, average velocity is 9, without fully testing all delivered functionality. The Development Team believes velocity of 13 is within reach. What is the most effective way to recover?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Development Team sets the open work aside for release Sprints."},{key:"B",text:"Transparency needs to be restored by adding the undone work to the Product Backlog. The Development Team must deliver not only 13 units but also two additional points to catch up."},{key:"C",text:"In the next Sprints the Development Team keeps making sure selected scope is as 'Done' as possible, at least at the past level of 90%."},{key:"D",text:"The Development Team informs Marian that the progress she has perceived is not correct. The Increment is not releasable. They give Marian their estimate of effort to get past work 'Done' and suggest doing that first. The team also re-estimates the remaining backlog. In the end, it is Marian's call to continue or cancel."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Transparency must be restored. The team should inform the PO of the true state and re-estimate before proceeding."},
  {id:29,question:"True or False: Using Scrum ensures that adding more resources to a project proportionally increases the value delivered.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"True"},{key:"B",text:"False"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Adding resources does not guarantee proportional increase in value in complex environments."},
  {id:30,question:"True or False: When multiple Scrum Teams work on the same product, they should employ a 'Definition of Ready' to maximize their velocity.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"True"},{key:"B",text:"False"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Definition of Ready is not required and should not be used as a gate. It does not maximize velocity."}
];

const psm2Test1Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"An organization has given Peter, a Product Owner, complete ownership over his product including all financial aspects. Can Scrum help Peter with these responsibilities?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Yes, by frequently inspecting the outcomes of the delivered Sprint Increments, Peter can better understand what value is being produced per investment spent."},{key:"B",text:"Yes, Peter can set a fixed budget for each release where each release is an accumulation of multiple Sprint increments."},{key:"C",text:"No, budgeting is outside the scope of the Scrum Framework."},{key:"D",text:"No, managing finances is not defined as a Product Owner responsibility."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Each Sprint is an opportunity to inspect the investment against the returned value."},
  {id:2,question:"An organization wants to apply Scrum with three new teams. The organization is new to Scrum. Which two things would Steven first advise?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Each Scrum Team should have its own Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"There is a single Product Backlog to represent all of the known work needed."},{key:"C",text:"There should be three Product Owners, one for each Scrum Team."},{key:"D",text:"Having one Product Owner to be accountable for maximizing the flow of value."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"For a single product, there should be one Product Owner and one Product Backlog."},
  {id:3,question:"A Scrum Team has six Developers who suggest having the Daily Scrum every other day. What would be three key concerns if the Daily Scrum is held less frequently?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"It will take longer to raise and resolve impediments."},{key:"B",text:"Opportunities to inspect and adapt the Sprint Backlog are reduced."},{key:"C",text:"The Sprint plan will become less accurate and transparency is reduced."},{key:"D",text:"The Scrum Master loses the ability to update the burn-down chart."},{key:"E",text:"The Product Owner cannot inspect utilization of individual team members."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C"],explanation:"Reducing Daily Scrum frequency increases the feedback loop and adds risk."},
  {id:4,question:"At Sprint Planning, the Developers cannot confidently forecast due to unclear requirements. The Product Owner has a clear business objective. Which two actions would you support?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Allow as much time as needed to review Product Backlog items."},{key:"B",text:"Forecast most likely items, create Sprint Backlog, start implementation and adapt throughout Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Extend Sprint Planning until Sprint Backlog is fully formulated."},{key:"D",text:"Discuss in the Retrospective why this happened and what changes will reduce the risk."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Events are time-boxed. Forecast and adapt during Sprint, then improve in Retrospective."},
  {id:5,question:"An organization has 3 products, each with separate Product Backlogs and 2 dedicated Scrum Teams. How many Product Owners might the organization have?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Three Product Owners. One for each product."},{key:"B",text:"Enough to maximize utilization of all Developers."},{key:"C",text:"Six Product Owners. One for each Scrum Team."},{key:"D",text:"One Product Owner for all three products."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"For every Product there is one Product Backlog and one Product Owner."},
  {id:6,question:"The Product Owner suggests reducing the Definition of Done to accelerate delivery. The Developers are hesitant due to technical debt. What are the best ways to explain the risks?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Developers will need time after release to work on technical debt."},{key:"B",text:"Reducing DoD will introduce unknown errors. System becomes harder to stabilize. Velocity decreases unpredictably."},{key:"C",text:"Technical debt is not visible to end users. Innovation rate will be reduced."},{key:"D",text:"Technical debt will need analysis to allocate additional funding."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Technical debt introduces unknown errors and reduces innovation rate."},
  {id:7,question:"The Director of Engineering wants to standardize velocity to evaluate which teams deliver the most value. What are the most appropriate responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Help understand there is no direct relationship between velocity and value delivered."},{key:"B",text:"Have teams estimate in Story Points to understand which teams produce most value."},{key:"C",text:"Ensure each team has equivalent capacity to compare performance."},{key:"D",text:"Teach that velocity is used by the team for Sprint Planning and is localized to that team only."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Velocity is unique to each team for Sprint Planning. No direct relationship to value."},
  {id:8,question:"A Scrum Team has requested a hardening Sprint. What three scenarios has likely occurred?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Definition of Done is not being adhered to every Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"The Definition of Done is weak causing technical debt."},{key:"C",text:"The team is having difficulties releasing during a Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Hardening Sprints are supported by Scrum."},{key:"E",text:"Scrum has been customized suitably."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C"],explanation:"Hardening Sprints indicate DoD issues or integration difficulties."},
  {id:9,question:"What does it mean to say a Scrum Team is self-managing?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Management knows which members work on what tasks."},{key:"B",text:"The team uses collective wisdom to explore solutions."},{key:"C",text:"The team lives up to commitment of delivering all items agreed at Sprint Planning."},{key:"D",text:"The team is empowered to resolve conflicts between members."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Self-managing teams use collective wisdom and resolve their own conflicts."},
  {id:10,question:"Which of the following would NOT be a preferred stance for a Scrum Master?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"The Admin"},{key:"B",text:"A Change Agent"},{key:"C",text:"A Mentor"},{key:"D",text:"A Manager"},{key:"E",text:"A Scribe"},{key:"F",text:"The Scrum Police"}],correctAnswers:["A","E","F"],explanation:"SM is a Change Agent, Mentor, Manager - not an admin, scribe, or police."},
  {id:11,question:"The CEO wants to delay the next Sprint to respond to user feedback. The PO wants to continue. What would be two acceptable outcomes?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Continue with Sprints and add feedback to Product Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Delay the Sprint for customer feedback."},{key:"C",text:"Continue but shorten Sprint time-box for shorter feedback loops."},{key:"D",text:"Continue but allow Sprint Goal to change."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"A new Sprint starts immediately. Add feedback to backlog or shorten Sprints."},
  {id:12,question:"How can technical debt affect velocity?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"They are unrelated."},{key:"B",text:"Velocity may suddenly drop when encountering technical debt."},{key:"C",text:"A team can perceive higher velocity by ignoring technical debt."},{key:"D",text:"Technical debt should not consume more than 10% of capacity."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Technical debt can cause drops or create perception of higher velocity."},
  {id:13,question:"The Daily Scrum is taking longer than 15 minutes due to one Developer. What are the 2 best responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Coach Developers to discuss the problem and take ownership."},{key:"B",text:"Ask that person to go last."},{key:"C",text:"Limit each developer to 2 minutes."},{key:"D",text:"Conduct the Daily Scrum by asking 3 questions."},{key:"E",text:"Speak privately with the person about the purpose of Daily Scrum."}],correctAnswers:["A","E"],explanation:"Coach the team and speak privately with the individual."},
  {id:14,question:"What best describes what 'Done' means?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ready for UAT."},{key:"B",text:"Ready for integration testing."},{key:"C",text:"Potentially releasable Increment."},{key:"D",text:"All work performed per Definition of Done."},{key:"E",text:"All tasks from Sprint Planning completed."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Done means potentially releasable and conforming to Definition of Done."},
  {id:15,question:"What would best demonstrate the Scrum Value of respect?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Not building features nobody will use."},{key:"B",text:"Respect for people, experience, background."},{key:"C",text:"Accepting change requests to avoid conflict."},{key:"D",text:"Accepting additional items into Sprint."},{key:"E",text:"Respecting role accountabilities."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","E"],explanation:"Respect includes valuing people and not wasting resources on low-value features."},
  {id:16,question:"The Product Backlog rarely changes and Sprint Goals are hard to create. What is likely causing this?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprints are too long."},{key:"B",text:"PO is not empowered to make PB decisions."},{key:"C",text:"PO doesn't have business objectives."},{key:"D",text:"Scrum might not be suitable."},{key:"E",text:"Too many Developers."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D"],explanation:"Lack of Sprint Goals relates to PO empowerment, objectives, or Scrum suitability."},
  {id:17,question:"The team couldn't create a shippable increment but completed lots of work and increased velocity. What are the best responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Help them understand working software is more valuable than high velocity."},{key:"B",text:"Introduce a hardening Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"Add a dedicated release team."},{key:"D",text:"Facilitate discussion on improving to ensure shippable Increments."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Working software is primary measure. Focus on making Increments shippable."},
  {id:18,question:"The PO asks how many Sprints for architecture and infrastructure. What are the best responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"20% of each Sprint is allocated for architecture."},{key:"B",text:"Architecture emerges alongside business functionality development."},{key:"C",text:"First Sprint dedicated to technical foundation."},{key:"D",text:"Add work to Product Backlog while delivering business functionality each Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Architecture emerges alongside business functionality. Add to Product Backlog."},
  {id:19,question:"Which three activities describe what a Scrum Master manages?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Reporting on Sprint performance."},{key:"B",text:"How Scrum is understood and applied."},{key:"C",text:"Capacity and utilization of Developers."},{key:"D",text:"Process conforming to Scrum Framework."},{key:"E",text:"Product Backlog items and Sprint Backlog."},{key:"F",text:"Removing impediments."}],correctAnswers:["B","D","F"],explanation:"SM manages how Scrum is understood, process conformance, and impediment removal."},
  {id:20,question:"What should you keep in mind when transitioning from siloed to cross-functional teams?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Easier to compare performance between teams."},{key:"B",text:"Newly formed teams need time to stabilize."},{key:"C",text:"Postpone Scrum until teams are reorganized."},{key:"D",text:"People from different layers need time to work together, productivity may suffer."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Teams need time to stabilize and productivity may temporarily suffer."},
  {id:21,question:"The team decided to reduce Unit Test coverage in the DoD. What two actions are most appropriate?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Reject the decision."},{key:"B",text:"Accept as mutual agreement was made."},{key:"C",text:"Ask what problem they're solving. How will it impact transparency and quality?"},{key:"D",text:"Ask if they can still produce potentially shippable increments?"}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Ask about the problem being solved and if shippable increments are still possible."},
  {id:22,question:"After eight Sprints, sponsors are surprised the product is not as expected. What factors may have led to this?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"PO hasn't engaged sponsors frequently."},{key:"B",text:"Sponsors haven't used Sprint Reviews to engage."},{key:"C",text:"Scope changes not tracked adequately."},{key:"D",text:"Stakeholders not using Daily Scrum."},{key:"E",text:"SM hasn't ensured transparency."},{key:"F",text:"Project plan followed stringently."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","E"],explanation:"Lack of PO engagement, sponsor involvement in Reviews, and transparency."},
  {id:23,question:"What can impact Sprint results?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Relationships between people."},{key:"B",text:"Technology complexity."},{key:"C",text:"Work complexity."},{key:"D",text:"Skills of people."},{key:"E",text:"System stability."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C","D","E"],explanation:"All of these factors impact Sprint results."},
  {id:24,question:"Which statements are TRUE about the Sprint Goal?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Can change during Sprint if not achievable."},{key:"B",text:"Developers have courage to tell PO of challenges."},{key:"C",text:"PO respects Developers' opinion."},{key:"D",text:"Helps increase focus."},{key:"E",text:"Team discusses alternative ways openly."},{key:"F",text:"Developers commit to working towards it."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D","E","F"],explanation:"Sprint Goal doesn't change. All others are true."},
  {id:25,question:"New security requirements need to be addressed. What approaches are most appropriate?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Fully detail and approve before working."},{key:"B",text:"Handle in separate Product Backlog by security experts."},{key:"C",text:"Create complete list with security specialists for Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"In Retrospective, expand DoD for security criteria."},{key:"E",text:"Add to Product Backlog and address in Sprints with business functionality."}],correctAnswers:["D","E"],explanation:"Add to DoD in Retrospective and add items to Product Backlog alongside business functionality."},
  {id:26,question:"The team suggests removing Daily Scrum as they have weekly progress meetings. What are appropriate responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Daily Scrum is opportunity to raise impediments to SM."},{key:"B",text:"Daily Scrum is short feedback loop for aligning on next 24 hours toward Sprint Goal."},{key:"C",text:"Daily Scrum helps PO optimize workload."},{key:"D",text:"Scrum Board must be updated daily."},{key:"E",text:"SM uses Daily Scrum to plan tasks."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Daily Scrum is for raising impediments and short feedback loop for the team."},
  {id:27,question:"Which best describes a Sprint Goal?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Used to check all work agreed to is completed."},{key:"B",text:"Offers flexibility, fosters teamwork, encourages creativity."},{key:"C",text:"Determined collectively based on PO's business objective."},{key:"D",text:"Living artifact that changes as insights emerge."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Sprint Goal provides flexibility and is determined collectively by the Scrum Team."},
  {id:28,question:"What would best demonstrate the Scrum Value of commitment?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Maximizing velocity."},{key:"B",text:"Seeking user and stakeholder feedback."},{key:"C",text:"Working towards Sprint Goal."},{key:"D",text:"Ensuring transparency."},{key:"E",text:"Delivering set scope by set date."},{key:"F",text:"Completing Sprint Backlog as agreed."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D"],explanation:"Commitment is about dedication to actions and effort, not final results."},
  {id:29,question:"Chris often questions technical decisions of other team members. What are two good ways to address the complaints?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Observe if topic is raised at Retrospective."},{key:"B",text:"Facilitate a session through healthy conflict and debate."},{key:"C",text:"Tell concerned members Chris' opinions should be respected."},{key:"D",text:"Tell Chris to be more considerate."},{key:"E",text:"Organize team building session."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Observe at Retrospective and facilitate healthy conflict resolution."},
  {id:30,question:"How can Steven help an organization new to Scrum learn and apply it effectively?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Require all teams to start using Scrum immediately."},{key:"B",text:"Arrange personal coaching sessions."},{key:"C",text:"Schedule formal training sessions."},{key:"D",text:"Impose formal agreement to follow."},{key:"E",text:"Educate people and clients about Scrum."},{key:"F",text:"Extend Retrospectives for formal training."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","E"],explanation:"Coach, train, and educate about Scrum."}
];

const psm2Test2Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"A partially completed item at Sprint end. What should happen?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Include if acceptable at Sprint Review."},{key:"B",text:"Don't include in Increment."},{key:"C",text:"Split into done/undone work."},{key:"D",text:"Estimate remaining work and move to Product Backlog."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Don't include incomplete items. Return to Product Backlog."},
  {id:2,question:"Which two rules help a team self-manage effectively?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Time-boxing events."},{key:"B",text:"Functional sub-teams with handoff phases."},{key:"C",text:"Creating potentially shippable Increment each Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Mix of skills and experience."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Time-boxing and shippable Increments guide self-management."},
  {id:3,question:"Multiple teams need Nicole full-time. What would Steven consider?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Combine teams."},{key:"B",text:"Investigate scaling frameworks."},{key:"C",text:"People volunteer for Nicole's work."},{key:"D",text:"Ask Nicole to hire more."},{key:"E",text:"Reorder PB so Nicole serves one team."},{key:"F",text:"Create new team with Nicole."},{key:"G",text:"Release Sprint for Nicole's domain."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","E"],explanation:"Investigate scaling, volunteer to learn, or reorder PB."},
  {id:4,question:"Peter gives recognition during Daily Scrum. What are valid responses from Steven?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Discuss concerns about behavior impact."},{key:"B",text:"Coach on burndown chart."},{key:"C",text:"Nothing, Steven not needed."},{key:"D",text:"Coach team on Daily Scrum purpose."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Discuss behavior impact and coach on Daily Scrum purpose."},
  {id:5,question:"Team requests hardening Sprint. What three scenarios likely occurred?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"DoD not adhered to."},{key:"B",text:"DoD incomplete causing technical debt."},{key:"C",text:"Difficulty integrating every Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"Acceptable per Scrum."},{key:"E",text:"Scrum customized suitably."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C"],explanation:"Hardening indicates DoD issues or integration difficulties."},
  {id:6,question:"What are benefits of Definition of Done?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Checklist for progress."},{key:"B",text:"Guidance for forecasting Sprint Backlog."},{key:"C",text:"Guidance on remaining work."},{key:"D",text:"Helps defer pending work."},{key:"E",text:"Creates transparency of 'done' state."},{key:"F",text:"Decides when Sprint ends."}],correctAnswers:["B","C","E"],explanation:"DoD guides forecasting, shows remaining work, creates transparency."},
  {id:7,question:"A team member is quiet because his ideas are ignored. Which Scrum Values are neglected?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Commitment"},{key:"B",text:"Respect"},{key:"C",text:"Transparency"},{key:"D",text:"Focus"},{key:"E",text:"Openness"},{key:"F",text:"Courage"}],correctAnswers:["B","E","F"],explanation:"Respect, Openness, and Courage are being neglected."},
  {id:8,question:"Which two behaviors reflect Servant Leadership?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Facilitating Events."},{key:"B",text:"Teaching and coaching on empiricism."},{key:"C",text:"Planning all events in agendas."},{key:"D",text:"Resolving every impediment."},{key:"E",text:"Taking notes at events."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Facilitating and coaching reflect Servant Leadership."},
  {id:9,question:"What should you be aware of when scaling Scrum?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Person on one team is more productive than on multiple teams."},{key:"B",text:"Well-structured PB minimizes dependencies."},{key:"C",text:"Members must work full time on single team."},{key:"D",text:"Event time-boxes must be scaled."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Focus on one team is more productive. Good PB minimizes dependencies."},
  {id:10,question:"New PO joined experienced team. How to help the PO?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Encourage engagement with stakeholders."},{key:"B",text:"Advise attending Daily Scrums."},{key:"C",text:"Arrange team building."},{key:"D",text:"Suggest delegating PB responsibilities to Developers."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Engage stakeholders and leverage team's knowledge."},
  {id:11,question:"How can teams leverage time-boxes for self-management?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ensures commitment to Sprint Backlog."},{key:"B",text:"Encourages best decisions by those closest to problem."},{key:"C",text:"Helps adapt DoD to deliver commitment."},{key:"D",text:"Encourages focus on same problem at same time."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Time-boxes encourage decision-making and focus."},
  {id:12,question:"Steering committee announces budget cuts. Tensions rise. What should the SM do?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Defend original budget."},{key:"B",text:"Focus on delivering highest value items."},{key:"C",text:"Request short break to calm down."},{key:"D",text:"Avoid involvement."},{key:"E",text:"Tell team to stay busy."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Focus on value and request a break."},
  {id:13,question:"Director wants 15% velocity increase. What are appropriate responses?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Explain velocity is for forecasting, not predicting."},{key:"B",text:"Inform of organizational impediments."},{key:"C",text:"Invite to Retrospective."},{key:"D",text:"Inform it takes few Sprints to reach max velocity."},{key:"E",text:"Shorten Sprints and reduce DoD."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Explain velocity purpose and identify impediments."},
  {id:14,question:"Developers struggle with Daily Scrum timing. What responses are appropriate?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask what they think should be done."},{key:"B",text:"Suggest experimenting with different times."},{key:"C",text:"Only hold when everyone available."},{key:"D",text:"Contact members as reminder."},{key:"E",text:"Adapt time based on schedule."}],correctAnswers:["A","B"],explanation:"Ask team and suggest experimenting."},
  {id:15,question:"What reflects a self-managed team?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Focused within functional role."},{key:"B",text:"Can reduce Daily Scrum frequency."},{key:"C",text:"Collectively deciding and re-planning work."},{key:"D",text:"Cross-functional individuals."},{key:"E",text:"Creates Sprint Backlog reflecting DoD."}],correctAnswers:["C","E"],explanation:"Collectively deciding and creating Sprint Backlog."},
  {id:16,question:"Distributed team proposes Daily Scrum only on Mondays. What responses from Steven?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Coach on daily frequency value."},{key:"B",text:"Ensure all agree."},{key:"C",text:"Help understand risks of reduced communication."},{key:"D",text:"Reject and require following process."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Coach on value and risks."},
  {id:17,question:"What should you be aware of when working in complex domain?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Requirements complexity and uncertainty."},{key:"B",text:"Technology stability and complexity."},{key:"C",text:"Skills and relations between people."},{key:"D",text:"Timescale of planned work."},{key:"E",text:"Handoff stages clarity."},{key:"F",text:"Senior/junior distribution."}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C","D"],explanation:"Requirements, technology, people, and timescale."},
  {id:18,question:"Five teams new to Scrum. What would Steven support for integrating Increments?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Each team delivers in own code branch."},{key:"B",text:"Each team delivers at Sprint end, integrate in next Sprint."},{key:"C",text:"All teams agree on mutual DoD for potentially shippable Increment."},{key:"D",text:"Wait for infrastructure."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Shared DoD for integrated, potentially shippable Increments."},
  {id:19,question:"What approach best conforms with Scrum values when forming teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"POs create skills matrix."},{key:"B",text:"Leadership allocates by skills."},{key:"C",text:"Provide boundaries and support self-organization."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Support self-organization within boundaries."},
  {id:20,question:"How much time for Product Backlog refinement?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"As much as team agrees is necessary."},{key:"B",text:"As much as PO deems necessary."},{key:"C",text:"Up to 10%, up to 90% in early Sprints."},{key:"D",text:"No more than 10%."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Team decides how much refinement is needed."},
  {id:21,question:"Three teams need Dan. What should Steven do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Manage Sprint Backlogs for even utilization."},{key:"B",text:"Assign to most urgent first."},{key:"C",text:"Facilitate discussion and support their decisions."},{key:"D",text:"Ask Dan to hire more."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Facilitate and support team decisions."},
  {id:22,question:"Team struggles at Sprint Planning with long discussions. What response?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Hire Business Analyst."},{key:"B",text:"PO works with stakeholders between Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"Create Sprint Backlogs in advance."},{key:"D",text:"Developers help PO with refinement during Sprint."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Refinement during Sprint with Developers helping PO."},
  {id:23,question:"Customers complain about slow performance. What response from SM?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Wait for Retrospective."},{key:"B",text:"Tell testers to add performance testing."},{key:"C",text:"Create PBIs for hardening Sprint."},{key:"D",text:"PO talks with Developers about performance and stronger DoD."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"PO works with Developers on performance and DoD."},
  {id:24,question:"Which discussion would NOT be helpful in Retrospective?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"More emphasis on unit testing."},{key:"B",text:"Build process is manual, need automation."},{key:"C",text:"John struggles to find defects, needs training."},{key:"D",text:"Regression tests too slow, need review."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Singling out one person for training without full context is not helpful."},
  {id:25,question:"How to determine if PO provides enough availability during Sprint?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Observe PO attendance at Daily Scrum."},{key:"B",text:"Observe if Increment meets PO expectations."},{key:"C",text:"Observe when Developers need to ask PO questions."},{key:"D",text:"PO must always be present."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Observe when Developers need PO questions answered."},
  {id:26,question:"Conflict at Daily Scrum about item being done. What should Steven do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Go through DoD and dictate meaning."},{key:"B",text:"End discussion immediately."},{key:"C",text:"Facilitate session to resolve conflict and refine DoD."},{key:"D",text:"Bring PO to decide."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Facilitate conflict resolution and refine DoD."},
  {id:27,question:"A Developer isn't attending Daily Scrum. Team says it's OK. What response?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Run Daily Scrum and require attendance."},{key:"B",text:"Talk privately about participating."},{key:"C",text:"Ask about value of all attending and risks of non-attendance."},{key:"D",text:"It's team's responsibility."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Ask about value and risks."},
  {id:28,question:"Team growing, decides to split into 2 teams. Primary concern?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Maintain original velocity."},{key:"B",text:"Enough work for everyone."},{key:"C",text:"Evenly distributed capacity."},{key:"D",text:"Minimizing dependencies."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Minimize dependencies between teams."},
  {id:29,question:"Where is best location for Daily Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Wherever Developers decide."},{key:"B",text:"Near product management."},{key:"C",text:"Same as workspace."},{key:"D",text:"In front of Scrum board."},{key:"E",text:"Wherever SM decides."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Developers decide the best location."},
  {id:30,question:"Daily Scrum taking 30 minutes. Steven thinks they should split. What response?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Agree, smaller teams reduce time."},{key:"B",text:"Disagree, single team less complex."},{key:"C",text:"Unsure, need more information. Offer to observe."},{key:"D",text:"Disagree, Developers decide how to run it."}],correctAnswers:["C"],explanation:"Need more information before deciding. Offer to observe."}
];

const psm2Test3Questions = [
  {id:1,question:"Paul estimated 10 Sprints but velocity is 18 instead of 20 and integration tests aren't complete. What is the most effective way to recover?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Strive for 90% done."},{key:"B",text:"Developers inform Paul projections are incorrect, suggest doing previous work first, re-estimate remaining. Paul decides to continue or cancel."},{key:"C",text:"SM manages Sprint Backlog."},{key:"D",text:"SM moves work to separate PB for release Sprints."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Be transparent and let PO decide."},
  {id:2,question:"Developers report daily tasks to PO at Daily Scrum. What should SM do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Ask PO to stop attending."},{key:"B",text:"Help understand Daily Scrum purpose and let them decide."},{key:"C",text:"Allow PO to participate."},{key:"D",text:"Facilitate to avoid conflicts."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Coach on purpose and let them decide."},
  {id:3,question:"How should work be distributed in scaled Scrum with multiple teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Highest capacity team pulls first."},{key:"B",text:"Equal Story Points per team."},{key:"C",text:"PO assigns items."},{key:"D",text:"Developers pull in agreement with PO and other teams."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Developers pull work in agreement with PO and other teams."},
  {id:4,question:"Who should coordinate work between multiple Scrum Teams?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"SM synchronizes Sprint Backlogs daily."},{key:"B",text:"Coach teams to form with skills to create integrated Increment."},{key:"C",text:"Use version control to eliminate dependencies."},{key:"D",text:"Elect member to attend other Daily Scrums."},{key:"E",text:"PO assigns team labels to PBIs."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Teams should have skills to create integrated Increments."},
  {id:5,question:"PO and Developers relationship has worsened. What should Steven do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Raise in Retrospective, discuss why changes occur."},{key:"B",text:"SM ensures stable velocity."},{key:"C",text:"Team building session."},{key:"D",text:"Explain PO is accountable for value."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Address in Retrospective."},
  {id:6,question:"Second team added to product with velocity 50. What's impact on original team?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"No impact."},{key:"B",text:"Velocity temporarily drops."},{key:"C",text:"Velocity increases."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Supporting new team temporarily reduces velocity."},
  {id:7,question:"Requirement changes slowed your team. Program manager upset. What could you do?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Work with program manager on ordering and value to reassess delivery date."},{key:"B",text:"Shorten Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"Remove items to meet deadline."},{key:"D",text:"Add developers."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Work together on ordering and realistic expectations."},
  {id:8,question:"What happens if openness reduces?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Harder to collaborate."},{key:"B",text:"Quality can drop."},{key:"C",text:"Less happy."},{key:"D",text:"Slower time to market."},{key:"E",text:"Stakeholders lose trust."},{key:"F",text:"All of the above."}],correctAnswers:["F"],explanation:"All of the above."},
  {id:9,question:"Manager suggests UAT at end of release cycle. How do you respond?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Increments won't be transparent and feedback loop too long."},{key:"B",text:"Depends on DoD."},{key:"C",text:"Agree, easier to schedule."},{key:"D",text:"Disagree, need full-time SMEs."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Transparency and short feedback loops are essential."},
  {id:10,question:"PO surprised about technical debt at fifth Retrospective. What factors?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Not used Retrospectives effectively."},{key:"B",text:"Not enough attention to quality."},{key:"C",text:"No discussions about technical debt."},{key:"D",text:"SM hasn't ensured transparency."},{key:"E",text:"All of the above."},{key:"F",text:"None."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"All factors contributed."},
  {id:11,question:"PO concerned Developers won't finish Sprint Backlog. What response from Steven?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Remind Developers of commitment."},{key:"B",text:"Sprint Backlog is a forecast. Unknowns may emerge."},{key:"C",text:"Tell PO not to worry."},{key:"D",text:"Defer to another team."}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Sprint Backlog is a forecast. Unknowns may emerge."},
  {id:12,question:"When is best time for Daily Scrum?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Mornings."},{key:"B",text:"SM decides."},{key:"C",text:"End of day."},{key:"D",text:"Depends on PO."},{key:"E",text:"Developers decide within Scrum framework."}],correctAnswers:["E"],explanation:"Developers decide."},
  {id:13,question:"Scrum must be customized for multiple teams on same product.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Scrum has built-in flexibility for multiple teams."},
  {id:14,question:"Multiple teams should demonstrate in separate code branches at Sprint Review.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Teams should integrate into single Increment."},
  {id:15,question:"PBIs can include test descriptions to prove completeness.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Items can describe expected changes when done."},
  {id:16,question:"Increasing investment increases value delivered.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"More resources doesn't guarantee more value."},
  {id:17,question:"PBI must fulfill Definition of Ready before Sprint Planning.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"DoR should not be a gateway for Sprint Planning."},
  {id:18,question:"Version control tools will fix collaboration issues with multiple teams.",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"TRUE"},{key:"B",text:"FALSE"}],correctAnswers:["B"],explanation:"Tools alone cannot fix collaboration issues."},
  {id:19,question:"Who supports the SM in removing impediments?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Customer"},{key:"B",text:"Management"},{key:"C",text:"Product Owner"},{key:"D",text:"Developers"}],correctAnswers:["B","C","D"],explanation:"Management, PO, and Developers support impediment removal."},
  {id:20,question:"Which two statements are true about early feedback?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"More time for new features."},{key:"B",text:"Enables delivering highest value first."},{key:"C",text:"Reduces testing time."},{key:"D",text:"More likely to build what customer wanted."}],correctAnswers:["B","D"],explanation:"Early feedback enables value prioritization and customer satisfaction."},
  {id:21,question:"Distributed team has difficulty with conference calls. What two appropriate actions?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Developers choose suitable tools."},{key:"B",text:"Introduce tools used elsewhere."},{key:"C",text:"Raise impediment to management."},{key:"D",text:"Wait for Developers to solve."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Developers choose tools and raise impediment to management."},
  {id:22,question:"Which two statements are correct during Sprint?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint Goal emerges during Sprint."},{key:"B",text:"Scope may be clarified."},{key:"C",text:"Scope may be re-negotiated."},{key:"D",text:"Developers focus on completing all items."}],correctAnswers:["B","C"],explanation:"Scope may be clarified or re-negotiated."},
  {id:23,question:"What should be delivered at end of first Sprint?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Potentially shippable Increment."},{key:"B",text:"Plan for subsequent Sprints."},{key:"C",text:"At least one piece of working software."},{key:"D",text:"Refined Product Backlog."},{key:"E",text:"Proof of concept."}],correctAnswers:["A","C"],explanation:"Potentially shippable Increment with working software."},
  {id:24,question:"Identify INCORRECT statements about time-boxing.",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Sprint 4 weeks, Planning 8 hours, Daily 15 min."},{key:"B",text:"Daily 15 min, Review 4 hours, Retro 3 hours."},{key:"C",text:"Review 6 hours, Retro 8 hours, Planning 8 hours for 1 week."},{key:"D",text:"Retro 4 hours, Daily 15 min, Sprint 1-6 weeks."}],correctAnswers:["C","D"],explanation:"Review is 4 hours max, Retro 3 hours max, Sprint 4 weeks max."},
  {id:25,question:"A time-box is:",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Event starting at specific time."},{key:"B",text:"Event with minimum time."},{key:"C",text:"Event with maximum time."},{key:"D",text:"Event that must happen by specific time."},{key:"E",text:"Agreed period working toward goal, stopping when time reached."}],correctAnswers:["C","E"],explanation:"Time-box has maximum duration and is agreed period for working toward goal."},
  {id:26,question:"What are common outcomes of Daily Scrums?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Clear on next steps toward Sprint Goal."},{key:"B",text:"PO informed of progress."},{key:"C",text:"Impediments discussed and solutions selected."},{key:"D",text:"Impediments identified for SM."}],correctAnswers:["A","D"],explanation:"Clear on next steps and impediments identified."},
  {id:27,question:"Which characteristics are exhibited in effective agile team members?",type:"multiple",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Competence"},{key:"B",text:"Decision-making ability"},{key:"C",text:"Mutual trust and respect"},{key:"D",text:"Openness"}],correctAnswers:["A","B","C","D"],explanation:"All are characteristics of effective agile team members."},
  {id:28,question:"When is Sprint Backlog created?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Before Sprint Planning."},{key:"B",text:"During refinement."},{key:"C",text:"1-2 Sprints ahead."},{key:"D",text:"During Sprint Planning."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Sprint Backlog created during Sprint Planning."},
  {id:29,question:"What is self-managing?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Achieving results by focusing on team needs."},{key:"B",text:"Delivering max value in min time."},{key:"C",text:"Prioritizing high value deliverables."},{key:"D",text:"Allowing all facets to be observed."}],correctAnswers:["A"],explanation:"Self-managing means focusing on team needs to achieve results."},
  {id:30,question:"Which is NOT an example of Empirical Process Control?",type:"single",choices:[{key:"A",text:"Scrumboard for visibility."},{key:"B",text:"Release Planning for coordination."},{key:"C",text:"Prioritized PB for stakeholders."},{key:"D",text:"Fixed time for each process."}],correctAnswers:["D"],explanation:"Fixed time is not empirical - it's prescriptive."}
];

const examStructure = {
  PSM1: [
    { id: 'psm1-test1', name: 'Test 1', questions: psm1Test1Questions },
    { id: 'psm1-test2', name: 'Test 2', questions: psm1Test2Questions },
    { id: 'psm1-test3', name: 'Test 3', questions: psm1Test3Questions },
    { id: 'psm1-test4', name: 'Test 4', questions: psm1Test4Questions },
    { id: 'psm1-test5', name: 'Test 5', questions: psm1Test5Questions },
  ],
  PSM2: [
    { id: 'psm2-super1', name: 'Super 1', questions: psm2Super1Questions },
    { id: 'psm2-super2', name: 'Super 2', questions: psm2Super2Questions },
    { id: 'psm2-super3', name: 'Super 3', questions: psm2Super3Questions },
    { id: 'psm2-test1', name: 'Test 1', questions: psm2Test1Questions },
    { id: 'psm2-test2', name: 'Test 2', questions: psm2Test2Questions },
    { id: 'psm2-test3', name: 'Test 3', questions: psm2Test3Questions },
  ]
};
